<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hierosulias mastix, or A scourge of sacriledge: in answer to a pamphleter calling himself Anthony Pearson, concerning The great case of tythes. Wherein many gross fallacies and untruths of the pamphleter are discovered and convinced. / By Joh. Reading, once a student in Magdalen Hall in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Reading, John, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R447A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182394</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05097)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2792:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hierosulias mastix, or A scourge of sacriledge: in answer to a pamphleter calling himself Anthony Pearson, concerning The great case of tythes. Wherein many gross fallacies and untruths of the pamphleter are discovered and convinced. / By Joh. Reading, once a student in Magdalen Hall in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Reading, John, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by D. Maxwell, and are to be sold by George Sawbridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two words in title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Initial letters.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page stained with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pearson, Anthony, 1628-1670?. --  Great case of tythes.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179525:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ἸΕΡΟΣΥΛΙΆΣ ΜΆΣΤΙΞ. OR A SCOURGE OF SACRILEDGE: In Anſwer to a Pamphleter calling himſelf <hi>ANTHONY PEARSON,</hi> Concerning The Great Caſe of Tythes.</p>
            <p>VVherein many groſs Fallacies and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths of the Pamphleter are diſcovered and convinced.</p>
            <p>By JOH. READING, once a Student of <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> Hall in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>It is a ſnare to the man who devoureth that which is holy: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> after vowes to make enquiry. <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 20.25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are curſed with a curſe: for ye have robbed me, even this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>le Nation, &amp;c. <bibl>
                     <hi>Mal. 3.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> abhorreſt Idol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doſt thou commit Sacriledge? <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>well,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>George Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg</hi> at the ſign of the Bible on Ludgate-Hill. 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:179525:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179525:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> EDWARD NICHOLAS K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Principal Secretary of State, and one of His Majeſties moſt honorable Privy Council. <hi>Grace, Mercy, and Eternal Happineſs in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been the conſtant practice of the Adverſary to oppoſe Truth, and to uſe his power to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of Faithful Miniſters and Profeſſors thereof: Sometimes like an envious Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtim, by caſting dirt and earth into the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living Waters,</hi> opened by the hard labors of godly men: Sometimes by caſting out of his mouth water as a flood after the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>(the Church)</hi> that he might cauſe her to be carried away of the flood: Sometimes by <hi>ſuperſemination</hi> of his pernitious <hi>Tares</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the good Wheat in the <hi>Lords Field</hi> Hence were, and now are thoſe multitudes
<pb facs="tcp:179525:3"/>
of <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Errors,</hi> which in all ages of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> have infeſted the <hi>Church of Chriſt.</hi> In this laſt age, Satan knowing that his <hi>time is ſhort,</hi> hath more furiouſly raged, moving all his <hi>engins,</hi> and uſing all his ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, for his ſiege againſt the <hi>holy City,</hi> and <hi>Tents of the Saints.</hi> Amongſt other his artifices, knowing how much innate ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice inclineth vulgar mindes to <hi>ſacriledge;</hi> he hath lately tempted many to endeavor the utter taking away of Tythes, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, as ancient as his Church on Earth; well-knowing, that by ſubtracting the <hi>Oyl</hi> from the <hi>Tabernacle Lamps,</hi> the light will ſoon go out, and the people muſt be left to a darkneſs, worſe then <hi>Egyptian.</hi> This fearful condition was coming on us ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitately, as that the enemies of Truth were not aſhamed openly to boaſt, That within one years time, they would not leave either <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Prieſt</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> But <hi>bleſſed be God</hi> who hath broken the jaw-bones of theſe ravenous Lions, and prevented their miſchievous deſigns, by his gracious and marvellous providence, reſtoring his Sacred Majeſty in peace unto his long
<pb facs="tcp:179525:3"/>
afflicted people, and them by Him to their juſt Laws and Liberties; and therewith the free exerciſe of the true Religion main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by our former <hi>Princes</hi> of ever-bleſſed Memory. In which reſpect, though divers able <hi>Champions</hi> of Chriſt and his Church, have encountered the adverſaries of theſe <hi>Church Rites,</hi> with ſuch full abilities, as that they have left little to be added hereto, <hi>Quod non fit dictum prius.</hi> Yet ſeeing this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict hath not ſo been ended, but that new enemies ſtill gird themſelves to the battle, it is neceſſary that they be inveſted and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: Therefore having brought to me from an adverſary of all good, this piece which I endeavor to confute, as I conceive, by way of challenge; I could neither with credit to our <hi>Cauſe,</hi> nor good conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, be ſilent, or leave the <hi>truth</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out defence; my hope being, that I may hereby undeceive ſome who have miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the <hi>caſe,</hi> which this adverſary with his <hi>Jeſuitical Arguments,</hi> ſo ſtingily and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumeliouſly, laboreth in.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:179525:4"/>Why I preſume to prefix your Honors Name to this homely Tract, none need de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, who know the great favors which your Honor hath done for me; others I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to underſtand, that in point of gratitude, I humbly acknowledg the debt which I am no otherways able to pay, then by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, and my daily and hearty Prayers to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> abundantly to retribute for me, by his preſerving your Honor, and all yours. Which he really profeſſeth, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors moſt obliged and humble Servant</hi> John Reading.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179525:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>STanders by ſee more then the Actors, eſpecially in buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Polemical, wherein ſundry motions are not ſo much compoſed unto comelineſs,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 16.20, 21</note> as preſent neceſſity of defence and offence. It is very rare therefore, that any piecce of writing, like the Manna, fitteth every palate, or is as ſtrong meat to the ſtrong, and as Milk to thoſe who are of leſs exerciſed ſenſes: Hence are ſuch variety of Cenſurers; one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth by that he Readeth, another is imbittered by Truth it ſelf, becauſe ſome Spirit of Error poſſeſſeth him, which like a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouriſh diſtemper, makes the moſt wholſome things ſeem unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury. It is an Inſipid Diſcourſe which falleth under no cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. If in this <hi>velitation</hi> ſome things are let fall, ſeeming more <hi>Sarcaſtical</hi> and ſharp, then the gravity of the cauſe may ſeem to allow. I deſire the prudent reader to conſider, that I deal with an adverſary who careth not whether, <hi>Dolus an vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> right reaſon or abſurd and fallacious <hi>Mediums,</hi> fair lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or railing ſcurrility, brings his deluded reader to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſafe and impregnable concluſions on his ſide.</p>
            <p>If any ask why I meddle with this Argument, which ſome years paſt hath been diſcuſſed by ſo many learned writers? the buſineſs in hand ſpeaks my defence. This bold <hi>Champion</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> upon the matter cryeth out, <hi>Give me a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.10</note> in his oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> and reviling <hi>Gods Iſrael;</hi> and ſhould we ſleep? The Enemy endeavoureth to bring Gods curſe upon us, and ſhould not we arm and ſtand up in the Gap? For my part, however leſs able then many, yet <hi>for Sions ſake</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold my peace, nor ſleep, becauſe the <hi>Ark, and Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.11</note> 
               <hi>and Judah abide under tents, and the ſervants of my lord are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped in the open fields.</hi> Here is an emergent danger of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement caſt in among the people, by which a dreadful curſe must inevitably fall upon them, becauſe the Lord hath ſpoken it, and ſhould we be ſilent? Conſider who it is that ſaith, <hi>Ye have robbed me,— Ye are curſed with a curſe:</hi> Remember
<pb facs="tcp:179525:5"/>
who it is that ſaith to the Prophet concerning thoſe ſinners whom he warneth not,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.18</note> 
               <hi>Their blood will I require at thy hands.</hi>— Truly my hope is, if my endeavours gain none of our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries,<note place="margin">Matth. 8.</note> who are carried on with the foul ſpirits of <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>varice,</hi> like that precipitate Hoard, to their own deſtruction, yet by Gods mercful aſſiſtance we may ſtay and confirm our own,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Henod.</note> leſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceived by others examples, they ſhould likewiſe err in unjuſt gains, embracing their own miſchief. How ever, I would no have this bragging enemy go away with his vain oppinion:—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haec dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>felli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have endeavoured to ſatisfie thoſe who are not willing to be deceived, but to know the Truth and their Duties; hoping that others with their greater abilities, will ſtand up to defend the <hi>Church-rights,</hi> and ſo theſe blaſts of <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and other <hi>Sectaries</hi> deſigns and practiſes againſt the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſhall prove but as winde ſhaking trees, and thereby cauſing them to take the ſtronger root. Sure I am that ſuch pernicious pieces as this againſt <hi>Tythes,</hi> have in other caſes, formerly awakened good Authors, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned them to write many things for the neceſſary defence of the Truth, and Rites of the <hi>Church of Chriſt;</hi> ſo that the Adverſaries thereof, in the iſſue, proved but as thoſe Geeſe which gave the Alarum to the Court of Guard in the Capitol, whereby both that and the City were preſerved. Of theſe things let the prudent <hi>Reader</hi> judge; and the good <hi>Lord God</hi> open all our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, that knowing the Truth, conſenting and obeying, we may be happy in the God of Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 4. line 35. read, preached the Goſpel. p. 6. l. 7. now ere. p. 8 l. 2 not certain. p. 9. l. 15. nay, but do you not know? p. 11 l. 10. Phariſes and Scribes. p. 12. l. 14. as received. p. 13 l. 20. which could not. p. 16. l. 30. where they pleaſed. p. 17. l. 7. notoriouſly faulty. p. 18 l. 9. <hi>deſerens. ibid.</hi> l. 5. <hi>Nicene.</hi> p. 19. l. 33 when you mind but. p. 21. l. 11. Mr. <hi>Selden.</hi> p. 29. l. 3. <hi>at nunc.</hi> p. 31. l. 27. hives of drones. p. 40. <hi>antepenult.</hi> would gladly. p. 51 l. 31. captions. p. 53. l. <hi>ult.</hi> to the faithful <hi>Moſes.</hi> p. 55. l. 14. Miniſter. p. 56. l. 28. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 2.1. p. 57. l. 15. levity of the Greeks. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 23. arrangeth. p. 59. l. 11. proportion between. p. 63. l. 30. not unwillingly, grudgingly, or. p. 64. l. 27. as honeſty. p. 66. l. 28. concerning whom we only ſay. p. 68. l. 3. <hi>alta pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 74. l. 7. laws. p. 78. l. 16. unhappy. p. 81. l. 11. faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 13. and all Miniſte s.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179525:5"/>
            <head>The Great Caſe of Tythes Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the Countrymen Farmers,</hi> &amp;c.] The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor very conſiderably addreſſeth this Pamphlet to thoſe who are as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-men to men of War; where he may probably expect ſome purchaſe, and not many knocks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is for your ſakes,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Job. 1.7. &amp; 2.2. 1 Pet. 5.8.</note>] Satan might have ſaid as much to ſinners, and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees to their <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> for whoſe ſakes they travelled, not to ſave, but to deſtroy them; Are they not much beholden to you? There is but one God, one truth, which whether you or we follow, let the prudent Reader judg, when he hath ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered what is here objected and anſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You might be truly informed,]</hi> Be but ſincere to make that one word <hi>(truly)</hi> good, and I will have no controverſie with you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of all that I could find written,</hi> &amp;c.] I, on your ſide; I do not conceive that you would be ſo tenacious of your error, had you but ſo diligently read the truth, which many have clearly written on this ſubject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>More than two years laſt paſt]</hi> You ſee me to confeſs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther much want of apprehenſion, or will to underſtand any, but thoſe who were of your party and opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſhall be acceptabl to me to receive it]</hi> on which promiſe, I offer you this following diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The ſtate of the queſtion in hand, underſtand thus; <hi>Whether Tithes for Goſpel Miniſters maintenance are due to them, by the unchangeable morality of Gods Law?</hi> This we affirm; hence we claim; to this what ever you object, we ſhall endeavour to anſwer; againſt this law, no reaſon can conclude, no authority or decrees of man be of value. To your objections now; you ſay of Tithes.—</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179525:6"/>—<hi>But they were for the Levites]</hi> That the Prieſts you ſay received no Tithes of the People, for theſe belonged to the <hi>Levites:</hi> whence if you would infer, that Tithes belong not unto Goſpel Miniſters, ſucceding them, it were a meer cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to beguile your Reader; for we are to know, that firſt <hi>Prieſts</hi> were <hi>Miniſters of the Lord,</hi> Joel 1.9, 13. &amp; 2.17 and next, in that Tithes are confeſſed to have been due to the <hi>Levites,</hi> they muſt be confeſſed to have been due to the Prieſts; for all the Prieſts were <hi>Levites,</hi> though all the <hi>Levites</hi> were not Prieſts. The Prieſts were of an higher order and dignity, in the ſervice of the Tabernacle, in which they were to Miniſter; the <hi>Levites</hi> were to bear the burdens of the Tabernacle, when it was to be removed; to prepare the wood, water, fire, veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and inſtruments, for the Sacrifice and holy rites, &amp;c. Now the Prieſts as they had a more excellent Office, ſo had they a more honorable Portion. For firſt, they had the Tythe of their brethren, the <hi>Levites</hi> part, the tenth part of the Tythe of all the Land; which becauſe they were but few, (as I ſhall ſhew anon) was a large allowance unto them: So that as the learned Mr. <hi>S. Nettles</hi> obſerveth it,<note place="margin">Anſ. to the Jewiſh part the hiſtory Tythes.</note> it appears by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, that the Prieſts received Tythes, as well as the <hi>Levites;</hi> 
               <q>So much doth <hi>Chimki</hi> intimate on <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the people to pay the tenth of their yearly encreaſe unto the <hi>Levites,</hi> and the Prieſts; and this is plainly taught by the Apoſtle, Heb. 7.5. <hi>For verily they which are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Levi, <hi>which receive the office of the Prieſthood, have a Commandment to take according to the Law, Tythes of the people, &amp;c.</hi> which by <hi>Lyra</hi> is explained thus, <hi>Levitae genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter recipiebant decimas à reliquo populo: inter Levitas autem illi qui erant majores illius tribus, videlicet Sacerdotes ſummi, filii Aaron, non ſolum accipiebant decimam cum Levitis à po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo, ſed etiam, de parte Levitarum recipiebant quae vocabatur decima decimae.</hi> Num. 18. And therefore by all this it is evident, that the Prieſts received Tythes of the people, and not only the inferior <hi>Levites.</hi>
               </q> Hererto add, that in the general grant of the tenth to the Children of <hi>Levi,</hi> for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in reſpect of their ſervice in the Tabernacle, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.21. The whole Tribe both Prieſts and <hi>Levites</hi> are included.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179525:6"/>
Here it ſeems the Pamphleter followed Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> too cloſe, and caught ſome knock, which made him forget his own words; <hi>pag.</hi> 12. when he comes there to ſpeak of the Popes working under colour of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> lawes, he ſaith <hi>(By which Tythes were given to the Levitical Prieſthood) dic ſodes,</hi> How given to the Prieſt-hood, if no Prieſt received them? Truly, Prieſts were by their vocation, more honorable then the reſt of the <hi>Levites,</hi> as being to perform the holy ceremonies within the Sanctuary, therefore they received a more honorable portion than the reſt of the <hi>Levits;</hi> for they had the tenth of their part of the Tythes of all the land. Now becauſe they were but few in reſpect of the whole Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> of which were num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred above 22000, Therefore conſidering the firſt fruits, and their fees out of the Sacrifices, and other offerings,<note place="margin">Num. 3.39, 43.</note> beſides their part of the Tythes, they had a very large allowance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them, by the Lord. I had done with this point, but that I deſire the Reader to conſider how our adverſary croſſeth himſelf; ſomtimes denying, ſometimes affirming the ſame thing. <hi>pag.</hi> 1. he ſaith, <hi>No Tythes did the Prieſts receive of the People;</hi> but <hi>pag.</hi> 3. he ſaith, <hi>The Prieſt-hood which had a Command to take Tythes of their brethren.</hi> Thus his firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation failes him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So was their maintenance diſtinct]</hi> That which you ſaid im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently before, you now make an introduction,<note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> to that which you would fetch in, <hi>ſcil.</hi> That the <hi>Levites</hi> maintenance was Tyths, but the Prieſts was diſtinct from that; <hi>ergo,</hi> What? the Prieſts maintenance was not Tythes, neither ought the Miniſters ſucceding them to be Tythes; but you have marred this argument, by your own former conceſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which were figures, &amp;c.]</hi> Who, or what were figures, becauſe you expreſs not, I owe no anſwer; only I conjecture what you reach at.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Changing the Prieſthood, which had a command to take Tythes of their brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>there was made of neceſſty alſo a change of the Law]</hi> True there was made a change of all that was changeable therein; that is, the ceremonial part thereof; if you mean a change of all ſimply, you had need ſtudy the point wo years more; for here would be a begging the queſtion and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179525:7"/>
paralogiſme, <hi>a dicto ſecundum quid, ad dictum ſimplicitèr.</hi> There was a change of the Law, not ſimply, and in all the branches thereof (as the <hi>Antinomians</hi> would have it) but of the ceremonial and judicial part thereof. The morality is unchangeable in the whole and every part thereof; ſave only, that which was even therein ceremonial, and ſo alterable; as bringing titles to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. obſervation of the ſeventh-day-Sabbath from the Creation, &amp;c. But the morality is unalterable and indiſpenſable, in reſpect of all times, places and perſons. In the reſt which followeth, you ſeem a while to fight with your own ſhadow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor did the Apoſtles</hi> (you ſay) <hi>go about to eſtabliſh the law by which Tythes were given]</hi> your foundation is here laid on a falſe ground, and ſuch will your ſuperſtruction be; you ſuppoſe Tythes given by the ceremonial Law; in <hi>Abrahams</hi> example (as we ſhall hereafter ſee in its convenient place) it appears, that Tythes were due ſome hundreds of years before God gave the ceremonial Law by <hi>Moſes;</hi> and God did not then give tithes to the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> as a new donation for their maintenance, but only determined them according to that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age of his Church; as for the moral Law, on which Tithes are grounded,<note place="margin">Rom 3.31.</note> the Apoſtle ſaith plainly—<hi>Do we then make void the law through faith? God forbid: yea we eſtabliſh the law.</hi> Yea, out of the ceremonial law, he takes out this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, appliable for Miniſters of the Goſpel, <hi>Who goeth a warfare any time at his own charges?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.7. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? &amp;c. for it is written in the law of Moſes, Thou ſhalt not muzle the mouth of the Ox that treadeth out the corn—for our ſakes no doubt this is written, &amp;c. Do ye not know, that they which Miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple? And they which wait at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar? Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But freely preacheth the Goſpel,</hi> &amp;c.] What inferr you from hence? The Apoſtles required no Tythes, <hi>ergo</hi> Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ought to require none. Firſt, I ſay, if the Apoſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample (without reſpect to the difference of the ſeveral ſtates
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179525:7"/>
of the Church newly planted, and peaceably conſtituted) muſt preſcribe us in all things, then are we bound to ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions; to have no ſetled charge, but to travel up and down to preach to all Nations; which implies not a few impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities. Secondly, If your concluſion be, the Apoſtles took no Tythes, <hi>ergo</hi> the Goſpel-Miniſter hath no right to them: The anſwer is apparent in the forecited place, where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, It was not <hi>becauſe he had no power,</hi> but for the exigents of thoſe times. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſtianity was yet but a ſtranger on Earth, believers being very few, in reſpect of the numerous heathens bred up in Idolatry.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tythes, (whereof the heathens had ſome knowledg by the principles of nature, or otherwiſe) were generally paid to the Idol-Prieſts of the Pagans and Idol-ſervice, as by Tythes paid to <hi>Hercules,</hi> and many other like may appear. See Sir <hi>H. Spelman</hi> larger work of Tythes, <hi>c.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſtians being generally in Cities, they had few pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Tythes, and ſo they were incompetent to maintain Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the firſt 300 years until the reign of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution almoſt every where raging, ſo that few Chriſtians were maſters of their own lives, liberties or poſſeſſions, but were almoſt every day <hi>counted as ſheep for the ſlaughter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.36. 2 King. 5.26.</note> almoſt every place ſtreaming Chriſtian blood: Therefore as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to <hi>Gehazi, Was this a time to take?</hi> And that from new converted people, lately clenſed from the filthy Leproſie of ſin? Was it not rather a time to give if they poſſibly could, to the relief of thoſe they taught? Every thing hath its time; the time was not yet come, that a conſtituted Church ſhould demand her own. In the Wilderneſs wherein the people were in frequent travels, the very ſeal of Gods Covenant Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was intermitted by the ſpace of 40 years together, and in the Apoſtles times, their often journying, and perils of waters,<note place="margin">Joſh. 5.7</note> perils of robbers,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.26, 32 33.</note> &amp;c. and frequent perſecution enforcing them to flie for their lives, gave them no poſſible means of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Tythes, but as the <hi>Levites</hi> received them not in their travel, but when they were ſetled in <hi>Canaan;</hi> ſo the Apoſtles,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179525:8"/>
after Chriſts aſcenſion being in continual travel through one part or another of the world, and one while in priſon, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while in flight and perſecution; what, convenience in ſuch condition had either Chriſtians to pay or Miniſters to receive Tythes, which were to be taken in the ſeaſons of their matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and only on thoſe places where they grew to be due? nor ere that time came, they who in right ought to receive them, were by the guidance of the holy Ghoſt, in ſome other Country preaching the Goſpel, many hundred miles from the place where their Tythes grew due. See it in S. <hi>Peters</hi> example, walking through all quarters, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.32. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sometimes at <hi>Lydda,</hi> or <hi>Joppa;</hi> ſometime at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at <hi>Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Egypt</hi> ſometimes; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.13. or the Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> ſomtimes at <hi>Antioch, Seleucia</hi> in <hi>Syria, Salamis, Paphus</hi> in <hi>Cyprus, Perga</hi> in <hi>Pamphilia, Antioch</hi> in <hi>Piſidia, Iconium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13. Act. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>Lyſtra, Derbe</hi> in <hi>Lycaonia, Phrygia, Galatia, My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, Samothracia, Philippi</hi> in <hi>Macedonia</hi> of <hi>Greece; S. Barthol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi> in <hi>India;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerom Catal. Script. Eccleſ.</note> 
               <hi>S. Thomas</hi> in <hi>Perſia, Hyrcania, Bactria; S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> in <hi>Ethiopia, &amp;c.</hi> What ſhould theſe men have done with their Tythes? Where ſhould they have had Barns for them, who were ſo little maſters of their ſelves? What ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity could they have had, either to gather or keep ſuch things from rapine and ſpoil? If in a Church and State ſo lately ſetled, ſo happily governed in peace, we have had ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of plundering and ſequeſtration, What think you could have come to the Apoſtles and their primitive ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, if before the Churches peace, they had claimed their Tythes?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Charity of Chriſtians in thoſe firſt ages of the Church was ſo abundant toward thoſe that taught them, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14, 15.) that they needed not any other ſupply by Tythes; but when that began to grow cold, it was but reaſon that their due to Tythes ſhould be revived, and their proper right clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and received. How long this charitable contribution con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, it is uncertain, but as it decayed, good Princes by Gods providence in the overſpreading encreaſes of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, did well to make laws for the maintenance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and for the ſame, what ſo good a way could they take,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179525:8"/>
as that by Tythes, which Gods wiſdom had apointed? So Princes gave not Tythes to the Clergy, by their laws, but only as need required, reſtored them to the juſt Proprieters. God gave them, though in ſeveral ages he put it into the minds of Councels to require them, and of religious Princes to make co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive laws, to bind their Subjects to pay them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Another cauſe of intermiſſion of their claim, was that high opinion of the devouter Clergy of voluntary poverty; which dream of theirs, Gods providence made uſe of, to make their perſons venerable, and their doctrine of more eſteem among the Gentiles, when they ſaw that their teachers aimed not at their own eaſe, ſafety, honor or enriching, but only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of ſouls.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, Fear of ſcandal cauſed, not only St. <hi>Paul</hi> to forbear his claim, and uſing his juſt power 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12. 2 Cor. 11.12. but others alſo. Hence probably it came to to paſs, that ſo little mention is made of Tythes in the primitive age of the Church, or the exaction of them; yet we muſt remember that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; it was not that he had not power to have uſed his right, as he plainly ſhews; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4, 6, 7, 9, 10, 11, 12, &amp;c. So that if it be granted that in thoſe ſeveral obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, for ſome ages we neither read of any claim, or uſe of Tythes: What can our adverſaries hence infer? No uſe or claim, <hi>ergo,</hi> no <hi>jus decimandi?</hi> Neither read we of any uſe of the Sabbath, in all the hiſtory of the Patriarchs recorded by <hi>Moſes,</hi> or of any Prieſtly or Prophetical function, neither taxing the neglect, or exhorting to the uſe or obſervation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but can we reaſonably conceive, that theſe ancient Saints either ſo long omitted the ſanctification of the Sabbath, or Prieſtly exerciſes of Religion? no uſe, therefore no opinion of the right. What think you of the 40 years intermitting Circumciſion (whereof we have before ſpoken) did that take away all opinion of the right?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Weekly Offerings for the Saints, &amp;c.]</hi> for the poor Saints: What argument is this againſt Tythes? Good Chriſtians now relieve the neceſſities of the Saints, where collections are made for them; Doth this impeach their duty of paying Tythes? Nay, <hi>but this ought ye to do, and not to leave the other undone.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179525:9"/>
—This way of contribution continued in the Church, &amp;c.]</hi> how long, it is not uncertain; but certainly the Pamphleter was not well adviſed, to ſay that it continued till the great perſecution under <hi>Maximinian</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian</hi> about the year 304. before which time his vouchers, <hi>Tertullian, Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> were dead; which appears (ſaith he) by the writings of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Origen, Cyprian. Tertullian</hi> flouriſheth about the year 208. then wrote he againſt <hi>Marcion: Origen</hi> flouriſhed about the year 232. and died about the year 252. And <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> was crowned with Martyrdome (by <hi>Euſebius</hi> computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in the year 259. in the eight perſecution under <hi>Valerian,</hi> as other Chronologers reckon. <hi>Diocleſian</hi> cauſed that long and bloody Perſecution, which was the tenth in order. Your ſelf confeſs in your next Paragraph ſave one,<note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> that <hi>Cyprian</hi> lived about the year 250. Now ſuppoſe that the ſpecified contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution did continue till the year 304. how can that appear by the writings of <hi>Tertullian, Origen</hi> and <hi>Cyprian?</hi> Did dead men write for your Aſſertion? But learn to bring your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes cloſer together; and at leaſt to hold the Poets rule, to write <hi>ficta poſſibilia:</hi> poſſible, though not true things.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note>
               <hi>By whoſe writings it alſo appears, that there was not the leaſt uſe or practiſe of the payment of Tythes in thoſe former ages]</hi> Hence you would conclude that there ought to be none now, but that Miniſters muſt live on the abundant charity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions of charitable people now. To which I firſt anſwer, Shew us that charity of people towards their Miniſters now adays, and then urge their example againſt Tythes; but while you take from us all that you can, their example is improperly pleaded againſt us, which you will not have to hold for us. Next I ſay, that by their writings it neither doth, nor can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear which you here ſay; and how prove you this your ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative?—<hi>There was not the leaſt uſe or practice of payment of Tythes in thoſe former ages, beſides thoſe which we have to ſhew for the contrary.</hi> Know you not, that many excellent wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are loſt, and ſo never come to our ſight? Like divers famous Cities mentioned by <hi>Strabo</hi> and other <hi>Geographers,</hi> whereof little elſe now remains, but the bare names: read the induſtrious <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his complaint, in the end of <hi>Jerom's</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:179525:9"/>
Catalogue of Eccleſiaſtical writers, where after other expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of our loſs of eminent Authors, he concludeth—<hi>Verum hic dolor extimulare debet onmes bonis addictos autoribus, ut id certè quod ſupereſt, tanto legant avidius, quanto minus eſt quod temporum ruina nobis fecit reliquum;</hi> moreover who knows not, that both ſacred and Eccleſiaſtcal, and other Authors wrote many Treatiſes, <hi>pro re natâ,</hi> and as enemies of the truth gave them emergent occaſions of neceſſary defence thereof, without which moſt probably they had therein been ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: For what need they have written, or armed themſelves or others, when none oppoſed? But now <hi>dato, &amp; non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſo;</hi> Suppoſe that we read not in the writings of ancient Councels or Fathers any the leaſt uſe or practiſe of the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tythes; What? Therefore no Tythes were paid in thoſe former ages? Nay, but you do not know, that all that which our Saviour Chriſt himſelf did, never came to our knowledg? <hi>Many other ſigns truly did Jeſus in the preſence of his Diſciples, which are not written in this book,</hi> John 20.30. &amp; 21.25. There ſeems an impoſſibility of writing all: done, but not written concludes, <hi>à non ſcripto, ad non factum, non valere argumentum.</hi> Again, in the writing of the hiſtory of the Creation, Moſes mentioneth not the Creation of Angels; What will you ſay that Angels were not created, becauſe in <hi>Moſes</hi> writings we read not of their Creation? Nay, but <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Thus the heavens and the earth were finiſhed and</hi> all <hi>the hoſt of them.</hi> You may ſay, and that truly, in that general word <hi>all,</hi> are comprehended the particulars, though not <hi>nominalitèr</hi> and expreſly named; for indeed <hi>omne,</hi> or <hi>totum eſt, extra quod nihil eſt;</hi> and why, I demand, where the Apoſtle ſaith, Gal. 6.6. <hi>Let him that is taught in the word, communicate unto him that teacheth in</hi> all <hi>good things;</hi> that is, in all his goods, for he would not teach any to offer <hi>è rapina holocauſtum,</hi> to rob others to pay his teacher: and why may not the Apoſtles <hi>all</hi> comprehend the unſpecified particulars, Tythes and Offerings, as well as <hi>Moſes, all</hi> comprehendeth unſpecified Angels? By this it appears how feeble your main argument is to prove, no uſe or practiſe of payment of Tythes, becauſe we read them not commanded or paid in expreſs words
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179525:10"/>
in the New Teſtament, and ſeldome in ancient councels of the firſt age of the Church; yet ye will not deny Tythes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſpecified and paid; Heb. 7. <hi>Abraham paid Tythes, or gave a tenth of all to Melchiſedech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 5.</note>Of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> you ſay, <hi>But his authority he produceth wholly from</hi> Moſes <hi>writings]</hi> And would you deſire better authority then <hi>Moſes</hi> writings, which Chriſt the Lord of the Prophets citeth? See whither blind zeal precipitates men?</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>They impoſed their own opinion with ſo heavy Penalties]</hi> How were they their own opinions, if from the Law given to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> they take (as you confeſs) their whole Doctrine?<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> St. <hi>Peter</hi> would teach you better, <hi>That no propheſie of the Scripture is of any private interpretation; But h ly men of God ſpake, as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And what ſay theſe men of God as to this matter, more or leſs then God ſpake by the Prophets <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Malachi, Ye are curſed with a Curſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 33.11. Mal. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ye have robbed me in Tythes and Offerings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. 6.</note>You ſay <hi>Tythes, Eaſter, Pentecoſt]</hi> Now for another ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary: Our queſtion is concerning <hi>Tythes;</hi> What are <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> to that? Will he not bring the Poles Artick, and an-Arcick together if he pleaſe?</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>It was not a general received Doctrine that Tythes ought to be paid]</hi> Nor as it ſeems by you, is it now; it ſufficeth us that the devouter ſort (as your ſelf confeſs,) <hi>gave Tenths or greater parts of their annual encreaſe;</hi> And who knowes not that the better part of the people is very ſeldome the greater.</p>
            <p>You ſay,—<hi>Fathers, Popes, Biſhops] Praeſto:</hi> pretty <hi>Leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demain:</hi> you ſhuffle in <hi>Popes,</hi> hoping as it ſeems in that company to render Fathers and Biſhops odious to the vulgar; but if we conſider the original of that name, <hi>Papa</hi> was once a name of honour and reverence, importing only <hi>Patrem Patriae,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Country; and ſo was it long uſed in the better part, as <hi>Cypriano Papae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian l 2. ep. 7. 16. l. 3. ep. 11, 12.</note> ſo <hi>ad Cornelium Papam.</hi> This uſe of that name continued until after the time of <hi>Gregory,</hi> (the laſt of the good Roman Biſhops and the firſt of the bad.) When <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> 3. obtained of the Emperor <hi>Phocas,</hi> that the Church of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179525:10"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be called <hi>Caput omnium Eccleſiarum,</hi> which his predeceſſor <hi>Gregory</hi> gave for the mark of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or his fore-runner, then was his Seat quickly exalted to Supremacie; not only above all Biſhops of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, but alſo to a claim of Superiority over Kings, Princes and People: hence the name <hi>Papa, Pope,</hi> began to fall into an odium with all thoſe who received not the marke of the beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. But if <hi>Popes</hi> did in any thing declare or determine Truth and Equity, would you <hi>eo nomine,</hi> reject it? Remember that the Phariſees, Scribes, ſitting in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair (though bitter enemies to the Perſon and Doctrine of Chriſt) were to be heard: Yea, If the devil confeſs Chriſt to be the Son of the moſt high, would you reject it, as deviliſh? Nay, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that though the Devil ſpake it, it is the truth of God, which when Satan uttereth, he ſpeaks not his own. God hath ſo over-ruled ſome wicked men, as to make them inſtrumental to that eminent good, which he, who can do nothing but good, fore-ordained to do by them. See it in the example of <hi>Judas,</hi> the high Prieſts, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilat,</hi> Act. 4.27, 28.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>None of the firſt</hi> 8 <hi>general Councils of the Church, did ſo much as mention the name of Tythes]</hi> While none contradicted, there was no cauſe why they ſhould ſpeak of them; yet were the iſſue and determination of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie put upon antiquity, we could ſay enough thereof: We can prove that Tythes are more ancient then the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who ſhews that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid them; and you cannot ſhew them taken away by any law of God: why general Councels did not make Canons for them,<note place="margin">Agobardus ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Mr. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note> ſome give this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Nulla enim compulit neceſſitas, fervente ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> religioſa devotione, &amp;c.</hi> indeed the actual payment of Tythes was not exacted in the infancy of the Church of Chriſt, but reſpited until the greater intereſts of Faith and Obedience to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel were ſetled in a Church conſtituted: yet <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth that there was much due unto him, in reſpect of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> but concluded that he had not uſed that liberty, but as the time, and preſent condition of the Goſpel required, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all things, that he might not hinder the propagation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179525:11"/>
thereof; and that he might ſtop the mouths of backbiters. Add hereto, that there appeared more probability that men of the world and Pagans, would more readily entertain the truth which coſt them nothing, and when the Miniſters could not be ſuſpected to preach for gain, honor or any ſelfiſhneſs, but only for their auditors Salvation.</p>
            <p>That which you ſay, <hi>That Tythes were never ſo much as named in the firſt</hi> 8 <hi>general Councels]</hi> makes nothing againſt their right; yet you may know, that though we avow not the Canons attributed to the Apoſtles, to be indeed the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of thoſe fathers, yet that the firſt of them are very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and neer the Apoſtles times, it may appear in that <hi>Dionyſius exiguus,</hi> who lived within 400 years of the Apoſtles, tranſlated them out of the Greek, and received long before in the Eaſtern Church:<note place="margin">Sr. Henry Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans large work of Tythes, c. 20. of which City you may ſee Plin. lib. 3. c. 1. Stra. lib. 3. &amp;c. Bin. To. 4.</note> See thereof the fifth Canon; likewiſe the Council <hi>Agrippinenſe</hi> is cited, <hi>Anno</hi> 356. Decreeing that Tythes ſhould be called <hi>Dei cenſus,</hi> Gods rent. The <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium Hiſpalenſe,</hi> or <hi>Spalenſe,</hi> as <hi>Garſias</hi> citeth it, held about the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> 1. about the year 603. in a fragment thereof ſaith, <hi>Omnes primitias &amp; decimas, tam de pecoribus quam de frugibus, dives ſimul &amp; pauper Eccleſiis ſuis rectè offerant:</hi> The ſame citeth <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. and thereon ſaith, <hi>Sicut enim Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus omnia dedit, ita de omnibus decimam exigit, ut de fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus agri, &amp;c. ſiquis autem haec omnia non decimaverit, praedo Dei eſt, fur, &amp; latro, &amp; maledicta quae intulit Dominus Cain—con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geruntur.</hi> That is, all the firſt fruites and Tythes, both of Cattle and Fruits, let both rich and poor, duly offer (or ſet out) to their Churches; for as the Lord gave all, ſo of all he requireth the tenth, as of the fruits of the field, &amp;c. If any man will not pay Tythes of all theſe, he is a Thief, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of God, and the curſes which the Lord brought on <hi>Cain</hi>—are heaped upon that man. The ſecond Councel of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſcon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carranz. Sum. Concil.</note> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 588. by ſome accounted a general Councel, (becauſe therein all the <hi>Metropolitan</hi> Biſhops met) ſaith <hi>Canon</hi> 5. <hi>Leges nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> divinae conſulentes Sacerdotibus ac Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtris Eccleſiarum, pro haereditaria portione omni populo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperunt, decimas fructuum ſuorum locis ſacris preſtare—quas leges Chriſtianorum congeries longis temporibus cuſtodivit inteme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratas:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179525:11"/>
unde ſtatuimus, ut decimas Eccleſiaſticas omnis populus inferat.</hi> That is, Divine Laws providing for Prieſts and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Churches, have commanded all the people for an hereditarie portion, to bring the Tythes of their fruits to the holy places, which laws, multitudes of Chriſtians have kept inviolable a long time. Therefore we decree, that all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall bring in their Eccleſiaſtical tenths. <hi>Concil. Turo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſe</hi> held in the time of <hi>Charls</hi> the great, <hi>An.</hi> 813. ſaith, <hi>Nonas ac decimas, qui res Eccleſiaſticas tenent, ſolvere recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Eccleſiarum ordinati ſunt.</hi> It were eaſie to add hereto many more Teſtimonies of ancient Councels; but becauſe others have ſufficiently travelled herein, I ſhall refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der who is deſirous to be further ſatisfied, to the large work of the learned Sir <hi>H. Spelman, c.</hi> 20. Dr. <hi>Tilſley</hi> Animad. on hiſt. of Tythes, Preface and Catalogue; only let me have leave to inform them, who know not what is the difference between a general and a provinciall Councel. In a general Council <hi>omnes provinciarum Epiſcopi conveniebant:</hi> yet the forecited Councel of <hi>Matiſcon</hi> ordained, <hi>Ut quolibet triennio, univerſalis Synodus celebraretur;</hi> which would not be intended concerning a General Councel in the firſt acceptation, except that <hi>Matiſcon</hi> Councel may be allowed for a general one, as ſome account it: for a <hi>Provincial</hi> could not preſcribe a <hi>General</hi> one, though the <hi>General</hi> might preſcribe the <hi>Provincial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Provincial</hi> thus differed from the <hi>General,</hi> in numbers of voices and ſuffrages, as in that it was of inferiour authority to the <hi>General.</hi> But concerning this matter, I ſhall content me to obſerve, That</p>
            <p n="1">1. No humane Conſtitutions, can any more give credit to precepts divine, on which all muſt ground, then many Torches can give light to the Sun, which can be diſcerned by none but its own light, nor can all teſtimonies or decrees of men impair the truth of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Teſtimonies of men, are not to be valued by number, but weight; nor weighed by any, but the ſtandard of the Sanctuary, the word of God; and ſo far forth to be received, as they hold weight therewith; that is, divine truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt promiſed his preſence, <hi>where two or three ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179525:12"/>
be gathered together in his name,</hi> whoſe truth is not limited unto, or by multitudes in Councels: As the little Mole-hill may as truly have the Sun-beams ſhining upon it, as the vaſt Mountain; ſo may few gathered together in Chriſts name, be as truly aſſiſted by the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, as where a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude are met together. Yet here are two Cautions very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be held: 1. That not every aſſembly which ſaith, <hi>lo here is Chriſt,</hi> is to be taken for ſuch as are indeed gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the name of Chriſt; but ſuch are ſo to be eſteemed, who ſincerely hold the truth of Chriſt 2. Though holding the truth of Chriſt with a comfortable aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit, as to their own particular Intereſt; yet may they not preſume to make and give Laws for the Churches publick diſcipline: But if Chriſt be with them, they muſt ſhew it in their peaceable obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to authority and order; either actively, (if with good conſcience they may) or paſſively, if otherwiſe they cannot.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We may note, that in the general Councels venerable for truth and antiquity, ſome have diſſented and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18.19. 1 King. 22.6, 8</note>5. The major part have not always been the beſt, nor the leſſer the worſt: <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets were hundreds againſt one <hi>Elijah,</hi> and ſo againſt one <hi>Micaiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Generall Councels, though exceeding the Provincial in number and ſuffrages, yet may they not excel them in weight; there may be error of many (as may appear in the ſecond Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Councel, <hi>can</hi> 7. Decreeing for Images; and the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> &amp;c.) and there may be truth in few. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the Councel at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were not many, but ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to determine for the world, becauſe aſſiſted by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Provincial Councels as occaſion was offered them, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that Tythes ſhould be duly paid; which if the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral did not meddle withall, it may be conceived, that it was becauſe they had no occaſion thereof preſented to them by any complaint: and they being then in purſuit of the enemies of truth, would not divert to the care of things thereto ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, and much inferior.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:179525:12"/>Theſe things laid down, the prudent Reader may be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied concerning this argument of Councels, and perceive the weakneſs thereof, and the falſhood of that aſſertion, that theſe Councels did not ſo much as name or mention Tythes, until the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councel, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1119. and after a little pawſe he ſaith, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1180. Oh for the whetſtone!</p>
            <p>—<hi>For the uſe of the poor] This ointment</hi> (ſaid <hi>Judas) might have been ſold for much and given to the poor,</hi> but this he ſaid,<note place="margin">pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>not that he cared for the poor, but becauſe he was a thief, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26 9.</note> Joh. 12.6. Now whether the poor are here intended and mentioned for love and care of them, or malice to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, againſt whom you bring this argument, God knows, and all good men know, that a Sacrilegious perſon is a thief. I fear your Charity would be contented that any one (the devil not excepted) ſhould have your Tythes, would he but ſend his Tything-Carts abroad for them, ſo that Miniſters might be deprived of them, your work were done: If ſome <hi>Charles Martell</hi> would take the Churches eſtate to pay Souldiers, you would reſolve upon the queſtion it were Chriſtian policy. But to your often repeated objection, we ſay that there were Tythes allotted for the poor, diſtinct from the Miniſters Tythes, who have willingly relieved the poor, and would do ſtill, but that you have ſo pillaged them, that you have ſcarce left themſelves bread.</p>
            <p>You ſay farther—<hi>not any (Councels) that expreſly ſuppoſed them a duty of common right, before the Councel of Lateran, held in the year</hi> 1215.] Were this ſo much as probable, it would condemn the Chriſtian world, and the Prelates of much defect herein. We are too ſure that many are faulty herein now, becauſe Satan hath blinded the minds of many, and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up ſundry impoſtors to write and ſpeak againſt the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God for ſupport of the Miniſtry, his deſign being to ſteal away the oyl from the Tabernacle lamps, that their light failing, his Kingdome of darkneſs may be advanced: but if now, Governors ſhould ſet out ſome more ſtrict decrees for Miniſters, more eaſie recovery of their Tythes then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly have been, ſeeing the apoſtacy of ſo many ſectaries; would thoſe decrees be any proof in future ages, that Tythes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179525:13"/>
were never ſuppoſed a duty of common right, before the year 1659. or ſome following time.</p>
            <p>Yet (you ſay) <hi>were they free to diſpoſe them, were they pleaſed until the Popiſh Councels reſtrained their liberty]</hi> Say now, <hi>bona fide,</hi> were Tythes, due to Prieſts and <hi>Levites</hi> under the Law, or Miniſters of the Goſpel, ever free to be diſpoſed of by the people, in a ſetled ſtate of any Church conſtituted, where the people pleaſed? If you mean tenths for the poor, they are out of the verge of this preſent controverſie, and ſo you trifle: If you mean Tythes for Miniſters, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Gods ſervice, we juſtly require your proof; we know that under the law God never allowed any ſuch liberty to his people; neither can it appear in the Goſpel, that ever he left the Miniſters thereof to a leſs certain and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate maintenance, then he did the Prieſts and Levites; here now being the Miniſtry of a more excellent Teſtament eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed upon better promiſes; and how elſe did <hi>Paul</hi> avow his power therein, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. however in thoſe times of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches troubles, he uſed it not?</p>
            <p>You ſay farther—<hi>The old Roman doctrine, that Tythes ought to be paid]</hi> And was the law for paying Tythes, old <hi>Roman</hi> doctrine? Was <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>Roman?</hi> Or was Chriſt a <hi>Roman,</hi> who allowed the ſame in the Phariſees practiſe? But, to take your meaning, with favourable interpretation of unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed words; I muſt put you in mind, that the old <hi>Roman</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was pure,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.8.</note> when S. <hi>Paul</hi> commended their faith, and ſo it continued unto their latter apoſtacy. I ſo much reverence antiquity, as to avow, that, <hi>quod antiquiſſimum, veriſſimum.</hi> To your following Allegations, I ſay, what laws and canons for Tythes among the Saxons determined, doth not prove that Tythes are not due to Miniſters by divine right? And as to the reſt, I ſay, if they made laws to bind the people to obey Gods moral Law, they did well therein: and concerning the people ſo bound, it is pity that they (as we now) needed ſuch coercive laws to reſtrain their Sacriledge.</p>
            <p>To that which you ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. <hi>That notwithſtanding the many Laws, Canons and Decrees of Kings, it was left to the owner to confer it where he pleaſed;]</hi> We anſwer to theſe tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179525:13"/>
if they were true, that is no wonder, if there was no abſolute reformation at once, ſpecially there where the peoples great <hi>Diana,</hi> ſecular intereſt, hath a part. But now conſider, Of what ſtrength is your argument, <hi>à facto ad jus faciendi?</hi> They did (ſay you) leave it to the owner, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it where he pleaſed; <hi>ergo,</hi> it was juſt and lawfull ſo to do; that conſequence will appear notoriouſly faulty in other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. For example, The people of <hi>Judah</hi> built them <hi>High places and Images, and Groves on every high hill:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">1 King. 14.23.</note> in <hi>Aſa's</hi> good reign, <hi>The high places were not removed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 15.14.</note> In that miſcellanie of Religion, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.29.32. (to which may be added our modern confuſion) <hi>Every Nation made Gods of their own, and put them in the houſes of the high places which the Samaritans had made, &amp;c. and made unto themſelves of the loweſt of them, Prieſts of the high places. So</hi> Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam <hi>made Prieſts of the loweſt of the people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 33.17.</note> 
               <hi>which were not of the ſons of</hi> Levi; <hi>whoſoever would, he conſecrated him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 12.31.</note> 
               <hi>and he became one of the Prieſts of the high places. And this became a ſin to the houſe of</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>even to cut it off: he made him Prieſts for the Devils, and for the Calves which he had made:</hi> 2 Chron. 11.15. Under him the people fell to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; their fact concluded it not juſt: and in the Prophet <hi>Malachies</hi> time, the people did not pay their Tythes and Offerings: Did that exempt them from the curſe,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> becauſe there were multitudes of offenders? No, no, it brought it upon the whole Nation; no examples of multitudes ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe Sacriledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Pariſhes</hi> (you ſay) <hi>are but of late erection]</hi> What would not he make his ignorant Reader ſwallow?<note place="margin">Page 10.</note> 
               <hi>Damaſus</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> who lived about the year 260. ſaith, <hi>Presbyteris Eccleſias diviſit, &amp; caemiteria parochiaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; dioeceſes conſtituit: he diſtributed unto Prieſts, Churches and Church-yards, and appointed Pariſhes and Dioceſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vit. Pontif. Dionyſ. init.</note> So alſo <hi>Platina</hi> in the life of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> teſtifieth, in the 2d. Councel of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> the argument of the 11 Canon is,<note place="margin">Bin. Concil. To. 1.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t nullus parochiam alienam praeſumat invadere. That no man ſhould preſume to invade anothers Pariſh:</hi> which Councel though but Provincial, was confirmed by a general Councel in <hi>Trullo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rranz. ſum. concil.</note> this was held
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179525:14"/>
in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time, that ancient Martyr. In the decrees of <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> in the year 230. it is ſaid of lands dedicated and given to the Church—<hi>ipſae verores inditione ſingularum parochiarum, &amp;c.</hi> In the <hi>Ancyran</hi> Councel,<note place="margin">Ib. Carran.</note> held about the year 308. approved by the <hi>Necene,</hi> it was decreed that Biſhops and their Miniſters, ſhould endeavour utterly to root out that devilliſh invention and art of ſortiledge—<hi>è parochiis ſuis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. Carran. pag. 157.</note> In the 3 Canon of the Councel of <hi>Antioch,</hi> we read thus, <hi>Si quis presbyter aut diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, aut omnino quilibet ex Clero parochiam propriam derens vel omnino demigrans in alia parochia, &amp;c.</hi> This Councel was approved in the ſixt general Councel of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> In the Councel of <hi>Sardis,</hi> it was ordained, Canon 18.19. That no Biſhop ſhould ordain a Miniſter, <hi>ex aliâ parochiâ,</hi> without the conſent of his Biſhop. In the <hi>Laodicean</hi> Councel, Canon 14. ſee the like. It were eaſie to weary the Reader with ſuch proofs: And is not it a notorious falſhood to ſay that Pariſhes are but of late erection? One thing is here conſiderable, that when there were but few Chriſtians, Pariſhes were of much greater circuit of land, then ſince the more abundant plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Goſpel, wherein for the eaſe and accommodation of Pariſhioners, many Chappels of eaſe erected, have ſince by Acts of Parliaments been made Pariſh Churches, ſubject to the Biſhops and their Dioceſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note>
               <hi>The people</hi> (you ſay) <hi>then generally being Papiſts, did yield their obedience]</hi> Yet that God had ever ſome good corne among thoſe tares I conceive you have ſo much faith to believe, (if you believe that he had in all ages a Catholick Church,) though poſſibly you have not ſo much Charity as to confeſs that he had ſuch excellent Saints then, as are among you now in this laſt and worſt of ages.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>What before was owned for a gift, was now claimed as a debt]</hi> Shew, if you are a true man, who ever owned it as a gift or free benevolence of men, except thoſe who knew not, or would not acknowledge the divine inſtitution of Tythes: we own them as Gods gift, and therefore as mans due to be paid unto us. God made us not your almes-men, but in things ſpiritual our peoples rulers;<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7, 17.</note> watchmen and guides ſet <hi>over them in the Lord.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.12. And ſo not to live of your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179525:14"/>
benevolence, but duty, as ſpiritual Parents; and ſhew if you can, why that duty ſhould be leſs determinate and certain, then it was under the law to Prieſts and Levites: that he ever reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of the reſt which he gave to Iſrael, to himſelf and to his ſervice, never leaving it arbitrary to mans will or wiſdom to appoint, no not to <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf; And how prove you that he leaves us to your will and charity now? All acknowledg a Law for paying Tythes to thoſe who ſerve about holy things, ſhew us in any one Text of the Old or New Teſtament where that law is repealed, or the whole of Miniſters maintenance left to the peoples pleaſure?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeing</hi> (you ſay) <hi>themſelves in a ſnare]</hi> To you it ſeems that the ordinance of God is a ſnare; this diſcovereth your dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condi ion, and is an impious expreſſion.</p>
            <p>Again you ſay, <hi>The Pope hath been imperious, or in a great heigth of pride]</hi> What is that to us? If ſo, it was his ſin, for which he is reſponſible to God, who can make wicked men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to ſome eminent good; as in the example of <hi>Judas</hi> (as to the paſſion of Chriſt for our Redemption and Salvation) appeareth; to whom we may add the reſt, who did therein that which the hand and Councel of God determined before to be done. And who can deny but that he might alſo work good by the Popes commanding Tythes to be paid for the ſupport of the preaching of the Goſpel, to the then living elect, the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtrument of Salvation, however it proved a ſavour of death to many, poſſibly of thoſe that preached it, but obeyed it not.</p>
            <p>Next you trouble your readers about <hi>Canon-laws,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial payment of Tythes ſetled.</hi> What, ſuppoſe you that no good could be profeſſed, done or ſetled in that time, wherein error and wickedneſs had miſerably overſpread a Church? I ſuppoſe you will not on ſecond thoughts conclude ſo; when you mind not the propagation of the Goſpel in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when the Jews, Princes, Prieſts and people generally perſecuted the faith of Chriſt,</p>
            <p>Next you talk of the poor;<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> 
               <hi>For whoſe ſakes</hi> (you ſay) <hi>Tythes were chiefly given]</hi> If you mean that theſe ſpecified Parliaments did ſettle Tythes chiefly for the relief of the poor,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179525:15"/>
you do but trifle; knowing that Tythes were anciently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for ſeveral uſes. 1. Ornament of Churches. 2. For the poor. 3. For love Feaſts. 4. For Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. What ever Parliaments enacted, muſt be judged by Gods laws: human law is to our duty <hi>à menſura menſura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> à lege divina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae. q. 19.</note> whoſe end is the utility of men; therefore to that ſupream power and juſtice muſt we look, and in that reſt. So that this your argument is childiſh and impertinent, except you could ſhew that we take human Laws and Statutes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, to be the ground of our right to Tythes; we ſay after that ancient Councel of <hi>Matiſcon</hi> forecited; God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for our inheritance, or hereditary portion.</p>
            <p>You ſay moreover, <hi>He that did not pay, no great puniſhment could they inflict on him, but excommunication]</hi> You mean I ſuppoſe that men could not, you cannot be ignorant of the power of God to puniſh the Sacrilegious, who hath denounced the curſe on them:<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> but was excommunication no great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> in the Apoſtles ſence delivering to Satan? Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly you account this puniſhment the leſs, becauſe herein the ſacrilegious were but delivered to their own Maſter. As for the exemptions you mention, we diſlike them as well as you: as little to your purpoſe is that which you ſay in your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing cenſure of Popiſh imitation of Jews,<note place="margin">l. 1. c. 7. c. 8. &amp;c. ib. c. 4. &amp;c.</note> which as to thoſe rites which your <hi>Durand</hi> citeth in his <hi>Rationale,</hi> we ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſlike.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>being a Papiſt. &amp;c.]</hi> One thing is remarkable, you uſe to call all Popery, which ſuits not with your fancy. If <hi>Henry</hi> 8. did any thing according to Gods Will and Word, that is no more Popiſh, than that was Devilliſh, which the Devil ſaid, <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Henry</hi> 8. was a Papiſt, and he made a Law, that every man ſhould ſet out his Tythes; What is the concluſion yon drive to; <hi>ergo,</hi> paying of thoſe duties is Popiſh; Poor Sophiſtry! You are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that this were a Sophiſm, <hi>Non cauſae pro cauſâ:</hi> His being a Papiſt, was not the cauſe of his making that law for Tythes, but (as your ſelf confeſs) becauſe he believed that Tythes were due to God and his holy Church. In that you call that the Popes doctrine, (which by your own party is confeſſed to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179525:15"/>
grounded on the Law of God,) you commend the Popes Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, though with an intent to calumniate ours.</p>
            <p>And you ſay, <hi>Firſt of our Parliament laws for Tythes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and that upon which the reſt are grounded.]</hi> Here is another noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious untruth: Was our <hi>Henry</hi> 8. before <hi>Athelſton,</hi> who reigned in this land about the year of our Lord 924? Would you have your readers believe that <hi>Henry</hi> 8. made a Law, about 600 years before he was born, and crowned King? Was he King of this land before <hi>Edgar,</hi> living about the year 959? or before <hi>Canutus,</hi> who reigned here about <hi>An.</hi> 1016? or <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Conquerer, <hi>Henry</hi> 1 <hi>Henry</hi> 2. <hi>Henry</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Hiſt of Tythes c. 8.</note> by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Selden</hi> cited as Law-makers for the payment of Tythes to the Miniſters? One thing out of the learned <hi>S. H. Spelman,</hi> I deſire the Reader to conſider; King <hi>Henry</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Large work of Tythes.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>In the</hi> 9th. <hi>year of his reign, by that ſacred Charter made in the name of himſelf and his heires for ever, granted all this anew unto God. We have granted,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>unto God, and by this our preſent Charter have confirmed, for us and for our heirs, for evermore, that the Church of</hi> England <hi>ſhall be free, and ſhall have all her holy rites inviolable.</hi> Magna. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <q>And that this Charter might be immortal, and like the ſanctified things of the Temple forever inviolable; It was not only forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Kings Seal, (the ſacred anchor of the Kingdome) but by his ſolemn Oath, and the Oath of his Son, and the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Kingdom: yea, the whole Kingdom yielded themſelves to ſtand accurſed, if they ſhould at any time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter impeach this grant; and therefore in the 25 <hi>Edward</hi> 1. a ſpecial Statute was made for confirmation of this Charter; wherein, among other things it is ordained, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhall excommunicate the breakers thereof; and the very form of the ſentence is there preſcribed, according to which, upon the 13 <hi>Mai. An.</hi> 1304. <hi>Edward</hi> 1. <hi>Boniface</hi> the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and five other Biſhops ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly denounced this curſe in Weſtminſter-Hall, the King himſelf with a great part of the Nobility being preſent: Firſt againſt all them that ſhould willingly and malitiouſly deprive or ſpoile Churches of their rites. Secondly, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that by any art or device, infringed the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179525:16"/>
of the Church or Kingdom granted by <hi>magna Charta.</hi> Thirdly, Againſt thoſe that <hi>ſhould make new Statutes againſt the Articles of theſe Charters,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now conſider, you that have <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts to love and pity your Country: what theſe <hi>Pamphleters</hi> aim at, who lay ſtumbling blocks before the people, that they may bring the curſe upon this Nation, which muſt inevitably come upon it, (if ſacrilegious hands be permitted to take away the Churches rites) for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>If Tythes had no other ground, but only the laws of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and that they were not before the enacting of thoſe laws, and ſolemn dedications due; yet conſider 1. What came to <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.4. &amp;c.</note> the Apoſtle told him, that whilſt the land remained in his hands, it appertained unto him as a true proprietor, and when is was ſold and in money, that was alſo his own; it was then arbitrary, and he might have otherwiſe diſpoſed of it; but when he had given it to the advancement and ſervice of the Goſpel, he made it ſacred, and all due to God and his aſſignes; and therefore keeping back any part thereof, he lyed to God: and if it were ſacriledg to take away any part of that which had been dedicated to holy uſes, by a mans own donation and dedication of the whole; What is it to rob and take away from the Church that which God his ſelf hath dedicated and conſecrated to the ſame, (ſuppoſe in money, glebe, or other land given toward the maintenance of Gods worſhip, or Tythes) on which came alſo a ſecond bond, by the Vow, Oath, and free-will offering of the whole body of a republick in the repreſentative thereof, conſiſting of King, Nobles, Clergy and Commons lawfully aſſembled in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament? But ſome ſay though our former Kings and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments were bound by their vow and dedication of Tythes, or Lands given to the Church or Churches, becauſe they lifted up their hands to God to give the ſame, what is that to us? very much: for lawfull vows of fathers deſcend and are obligatory to their Children and poſterity; and ſo in the bleſſing to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, as we may ſee in the example of the <hi>Rechaebites, Jer.</hi> 35.18, 19. and in the curſe to the violaters of the ſame; therefore becauſe <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (though
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179525:16"/>
deceived by the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> a people among the reſt of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> devoted by Gods own commandment, to deſtruction) had lifted up their hands to God, to ſpare them alive, they were bound by their Oath, ſo to do; and ſo were their Children to ſucceeding Generations. So that when <hi>Saul,</hi> after many Generations, out of a perverſe zeal, ſlew them,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21 1, 2.</note> God puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that fact even in <hi>Davids</hi> reign, <hi>Three years, year after year there came a famine upon Iſrael,</hi> until it was revenged on the family of <hi>Saul.</hi> Many inſtances of Gods juſtice in this kind neer us of eminent great and honorable families utterly ruined (the main cauſe, to men appearing, being ſacriledg, impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating Tythes and laying into their own hands thoſe deſtructive morſels of gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>be and other lands formerly dedicated with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn curſe in the Acts of Mortmain) might hereto be added, even from <hi>Henry</hi> 8. who (before his giving away Tythes, and things conſecrated to Gods worſhip unto impropriators hands) proſperous in an hopefull iſſue, yet, as to poſterity, that doom was determined which was pronounced by the Prophet <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> on <hi>Coniah, Write this man Childleſs</hi>—.<note place="margin">Jer 22.30.</note> The curſe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years before ſolemnly and publickly imprecated, came upon divers of our principal Nobility, and other illuſtrious Families, and ſtill doth, whoſe names I ſpare; only I hint this, that all whom it concerns, may be warned to diſgorge thoſe ſacred morſels, which they yet hold, leſt they prove deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to them and theirs; and that the Reader may at once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of what validity all the reſt of the like arguments are, wherewith this Pamphleter and his aſſociates endeavour to puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle the minds of illiterate readers; and that all may conſider what ſevere whips God yet holdeth over thoſe who hunger for ſacred morſels. You know the embleme, the Eagle ſnatching up a piece of fleſh from the Alter, to carry up to her neſt of young ones, with it carried a coal of fire cleaving to the fleſh, which conſumed the neſt, and deſtroyed the whole air.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>Some of our famous Reformers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 14.</note> 
               <hi>did in their days, bear their Teſtimony againſt Tythes</hi> &amp;c.] I anſwer, firſt I conceive that you call them <hi>famous reformers,</hi> ironically, and by way of irriſion. Next I ſay, whatever they, or the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> by you cited, ſpeak againſt Tythes, is of no more value
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179525:17"/>
then mans teſtimony againſt Gods Ordinance. Laſtly, that one <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaw not all, it is no wonder, the moſt learned know but in part now, that the ſun from the riſing appears not in his full light at once, none can rationally wonder; and why ſhould we that the reformation was not perfected all at once?</p>
            <p>You ſay, In your following heads of recapitulation, <hi>He will find the knowledg of thoſe things which be needfull]</hi> Yes, no doubt to confirm him in your errour; but there can be no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſinning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tythes</hi> (you ſay) <hi>were paid to the Levites, that did the common ſervices of the Tabernacle, &amp;c. how the payment of Tythes to Miniſters, ſucceeds the payment of Tythes to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> (you ſay, we) <hi>had need to conſider]</hi> We conſider the Apoſtles rule, 1 Cor. 9.13, 14. which is, <hi>They which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: and they which wait at the altar, are partakers with the altar. Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> Secondly, we conſider, that <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech</hi> received Tythes, in the figure of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Peace:</hi> and that Tythes are due to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his aſſignes, the Miniſters of the Goſpel, not as a Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, but as a moral duty, belonging to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> long before either <hi>Levites</hi> or ceremonial Law were in being; and therefore they continue under the Goſpel, becauſe moral duties are unchangeable. And it is obſerveable, that <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> met not <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull, with bloody Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, like a Prieſt of the Law, but with a ſupply of bread and wine, the elements of a <hi>Goſpel-Sacrament,</hi> which the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are to divide unto the people: That Tythes are not Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical or Ceremonially due, it may appear, becauſe</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are much more ancient then the Levitical Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Tythes are poſitively declared to be the Lords, and ſo to belong to his Miniſters about holy things for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Levitical-law</hi> were all ſignificative, as of ſomthing to be performed by Chriſt, for the work of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; but ſo are not Tythes.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:179525:17"/>4. Tything now uſed, is not after the manner of the <hi>Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Law,</hi> but after the manner of <hi>Abrahams</hi> paying tythes to <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> who was not of the tribe of <hi>Levi:</hi> So our tything, is now to Chriſt, who was of the tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.13.</note> 
               <hi>of which no man gave attendance at the Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The end whereto tythe was ordained, is moral in point of Piety, Juſtice, and Gratitude.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Piety,</hi> for that will maintain the worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for that is to give every man his due: Now the <hi>laborer is worthy of his reward;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.18. 1 Cor. 9.14.</note> and God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed tythes for a reward or maintenance of thoſe who ſerve him in the Goſpel, as well as under the Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Gratitude,</hi> for benefits received of him, to whom we ow and offer ſuch thanks; adde hereto, that theſe are to be paid, to incourage and ſuſtain the laborers in the work of the Lord; as <hi>Hezekiah commanded the people to give the portion of the Prieſts, and the Levites, that they might be encouraged in the Law of the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4.</p>
            <p>And we may here conſider, that in the <hi>Levitical Law,</hi> the Lord had regard to proviſion for Goſpel Miniſters; for he ſaith in one of the branches thereof, —<hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the Ox that treadeth out the Corn;</hi> which the Apoſtle applieth to inforce payment of honorable maintenance of Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: Neither was that equity new, neither the Goſpel it ſelf: The firſt appearance whereof, which we read of, was from the beginning, when God ſaid, <hi>It,</hi> that is, <hi>the ſeed of the Woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. Gal. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt —made of a Woman, ſhall bruiſe thy head;</hi> that is, <hi>the Serpents head,</hi> (in which his life and venome principally lieth.) This Goſpel promiſe lay hid for ages and generations,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.9. Col. 1.26. Exod. 4. Heb. 9.7. &amp; 18.22. Gen. 3.19. &amp; 4.4. Gal. 4. Joh. 1.</note> under dark and myſterious ſhadows and figures: So that though the Law, like <hi>Tamars Zarah,</hi> as it were firſt put out the hand, which was before its birth, marked with a skarlet thred (blood and death;) yet in ſome ſort the Goſpel was firſt born, like <hi>Pharez, Gen.</hi> 38.28, 29, 30. and was, as the day light, by little and little, toward the fulneſs of time (wherein the Sun of Righteouſneſs ſhould ariſe to enlighten the World) mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>Numb</hi> 24.17. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 7.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.1, 10, 12. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>Mich.</hi> 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and at the laſt clearly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179525:18"/>
1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.22. &amp; 8.2, 3. 1. Cor. 15.55, &amp;c. Hoſ. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>For this purpoſe the Son of God was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, that he might deſtroy the works of the Devil, ruine death, and hell.</hi> And becauſe God would manifeſt this his mercy to the World, for the comfort and confirmation of his Elect in all ages, after mans fall, he ſtill ſent out ſome Interpreters and Preachers of his Sacred Myſtery, furniſhed with ſuch means as might every ways enable them thereto, and ſupport them as to their humane neceſſities. And it is not probable, that an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God would ſlack his hand, and appoint a leſs certain, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate, and comfortable maintenance to the Miniſters of the moſt excellent Teſtament (the <hi>Eternal Goſpel</hi>) than he did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prieſts of the more imperfect, which was to ceaſe and be done away: So that the Goſpel-maintenance, as to the Moral equity thereof, was before the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> given many hundred years after the Goſpel-promiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2.</note>Your ſecond Obſervation, is, <hi>That amongſt the Jews, no outward Law was appointed for the recovery of Tythes; but he that did not pay them, robbed God, &amp;c.]</hi> And think you, that robbing God, againſt which the curſe of the whole Nation was denounced, had no puniſhment following it? Think you not, that every ſin ſeparating between the ſinner and God, the ſole Fountain of Bleſſedneſs, was not a ſufficient puniſhment to it ſelf in the guilt thereof? And do you conceive, that we are now bound by <hi>Iſraels</hi> Judicial Laws, any further than ſome Statute Law of this Nation makes them in force to binde us? It ſeems grievous to you, that any Law is made by good Princes and their great Councils for recovery of Tythes; but for which, you and others of your Sect, would venture on Gods Juſtice, as if it were a light matter, by the contempt of Divine Laws, to fall into his hands,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> who is <hi>a conſuming fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But know you, that it is both lawful and neceſſary for thoſe who have Legiſlative power in Republicks, of authority to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Juſtice, to binde their Subjects from running into ſin, and pulling down curſes upon their Souls; and therefore to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Laws to compel them by reſpective puniſhments to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods Moral Laws: As in caſe of prophanation and common ſwearing, for which the Land mourneth, adultery, murder, theft, oppreſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſuppoſe you will allow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:179525:18"/>You ſay again, <hi>That Tythes were not for the Levites onely.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3.</note>] It is eaſily granted. <hi>Jerom</hi> on <hi>Ezek. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 45. ſhews, That there were tythes of four ſorts: Firſt, For the Levites; Secondly, For the Prieſts; Thirdly, For Love-feaſts; Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, For the Poor. Which whether this Pamphleter diſſembleth, that he may have ſomething to ſay, though to no purpoſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to trouble the Reader, I know not.</p>
            <p>You ſay again, <hi>That when the Levitical Prieſthood was changed by the coming of Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4.</note> 
               <hi>the Law for tything was alſo changed, as</hi> Paul <hi>writ to the</hi> Hebrews.] Now <hi>Samſon</hi> will pull the Houſe upon his own head: That very Text which you cite, is point-blanck againſt your ſelf; the Law (that is, the Ceremonial Law) was changed, therefore ſomething was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in its place: What, but the Goſpel and the Miniſtery thereof? And as the Office, ſo of the neceſſity of humane condition, reſpect muſt be had for the ſupplies thereof, whereby it may continue. There was therefore a change of this Law, as to that which was Ceremonial, for example in the manner of paying Tythes to the Prieſts and Levites, the place where, at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or other publick ſtore-houſes thereto appointed; but not in reſpect of the morality, or any branch thereof: So that the Prieſthood after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, nor the Tythes to the ſame belonging; as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſhews, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.8. ſaying, <hi>And here men that dye receive tythes, but there he receives them, of whom it is written, that he liveth;</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt.</hi> So then tythes ſtill follow the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; and ſo the Apoſtle makes a Prieſt, and a receiver of tythes equivalents: Inſtead of ſaying, <hi>Men that dye are Prieſts,</hi> he ſaith. <hi>That men that receive tythes:</hi> And inſtead of ſaying, <hi>He that lives is a Prieſt,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>He that lives takes tythes.</hi> As if in his judgment, Tythes and Prieſthood were as inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in point of right, as Kingdom and Tribute; and ſo the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion due to Chriſt, is ſtill due to his Aſſigns, the Miniſters of the Goſpel, who are his receivers, and in their Miniſtration in his ſtead, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. And ſo hath Chriſt appointed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14.</p>
            <p>But to your Objection, I ſuppoſe, your familiar, on which you rely, is known to you, except coming up <hi>Janus</hi>-like,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179525:19"/>
double faced, you do not ſo well mark it: The one is a Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm, <hi>à dicto ſecundum quid, ad dictum ſimpliciter;</hi> the other is your old acquaintance, <hi>Petitio principii:</hi> We ſay, that changing the Prieſthood, the Ceremonial part of the Law onely was changed; but not the Law for tything, which is Moral. You ſay that <hi>Paul</hi> wrote ſo (that the Law for tything was alſo changed.) <hi>Pauls</hi> words to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> in the cited place, are theſe. —<hi>The Prieſthood changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law</hi> You corrupt the Text, by adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>(of tythes)</hi> ſhew us theſe words, —<hi>The Law for tything was alſo changed,</hi> either in that place, or any other writing of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or in all the New Teſtament, and we will reſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied therewith, and never more ſpeak for tythes. But ſeeing you cannot, for ſhame, and danger of theſe plagues which are threatned, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.18. leave that cauſe, which you cannot uphold without ſo many untruths, and falſification of the ſacred Scripture.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>For the firſt three hundred years, while the purisy and ſimplicity of the Goſpel was retained, no tythes were paid among Chriſtians.]</hi> If this were true, what could it make againſt our right to tythes? The cauſes which hindred their pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are laid down in our anſwer to that which you objected in your third <hi>Page.</hi> Alſo for that you ſpeak concerning the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles free Preaching of the Goſpel, to which I here adde, that <hi>Origen,</hi> who flouriſhed about 226. or 230. in his 11. <hi>Hom. in Numb.</hi> after many other forcible perſwaſions to pay their tythes, by that which Chriſt ſaid to the Phariſees, <hi>This ought you to have done, &amp;c.</hi> he preſently addeth, —<hi>How therefore ſhall your righteouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſs of Scribes and Phariſees, if they dare not taſte the Fruits of their Land. —Priuſquam primitias ſacerdotibus offerant &amp; Levitis decimae ſeparentur?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 1. ep. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi> whoſe Martyrdom fell not long after, ſpeaking of the Levites tythes, ſaith, <hi>Quae nunc ratio &amp; forma in clero tenetur, &amp;c.</hi> And he blameth <hi>Victor,</hi> for appointing <hi>Geminius Actorem</hi> his Attorney, becauſe he would not have him diſtracted from his Miniſtry, and citeth theſe things as a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of his Anceſtors. The ſame Father in his third <hi>Tract, De ſimpl. Praelat.</hi> ſpeaking of the times before him, complaineth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179525:19"/>
of Charities growing cold, —<hi>Tunc domos, &amp; fundos voenunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, —Diſtribuenda in uſus indigentium precia Apoſtolis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferebant: Ut nunc de patrimonio ne decimas damus. —Sic in nobis emarcuit vigor fidei: Sic credentium robur elanguit. —Then they ſold Houſes and Lands, and offered the price to the Apoſtles to be diſtributed, for the uſe of the poor; but now we ſcarce give tythes of our Patrimonies. —Thus hath the vigor of Faith languiſhed in us, ſo hath the power of Believers grown faint.</hi> Much concerning this hath been noted by others, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I content me with theſe two antient witneſſes; but what now would you hence conclude? What, that craft and impurity brought in tythes among Chriſtians? But that were a poor falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Non cauſa pro cauſa:</hi> Such as the old man uſed, who ſaid, <hi>That</hi> Tenterden <hi>Steeple was the cauſe of</hi> Goodwin <hi>Sands: For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>juſt as that was building, they began to appear:</hi> But if in the Primitive Church they had not the uſe of tything, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Readers will conſider that which hath been ſaid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, perſecution everywhere raging, could not ſuffer the people to pay, or Miniſters to receive their tythes. Yet no time can prevent God in his reſerved right; no uſe or practice of paying tythes, while perſecution hindred; therefore there was no <hi>jus in re, non ſequitur.</hi> Tythes came into uſe in Chriſtian Churches ſo ſoon as the owners their ſelves retained uſe and dominion in their Poſſeſſions; except in caſe of Scandal at the firſt plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That as the mystery of iniquity began to work, &amp;c.]</hi> Again,<note place="margin">5.</note> here is a <hi>Fallacia non cauſae pro cauſá.</hi> Say ſoberly, Think you that the working of the myſtery of iniquity was the cauſe of Miniſters Preaching of that, which God had commanded to be done? Or was that mens imagination (as you ſay) the ground whereof, you confeſs, was fetcht from the Law of <hi>Moſes?</hi> It is to be hoped, that your ſecond thoughts will be better. Your ſixth Obſervation is nothing to the purpoſe, and therefore deſerves no anſwer.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>That in the firſt payment of tythes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 15.</note> 
               <hi>they were not paid as tythes, but as Free-offerings, at the bounty of the giver, &amp;c.]</hi> Say now, when, where, or by whom were tythes ever paid other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179525:20"/>
than by Gods Ordinance, from the firſt mention of them, unto this preſent; and ſhew us, if you can, how identity ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of diſparity. <hi>Payment of tythes, not paid as tythes?</hi> You ſay, <hi>As Free-offerings, not as anſwering any Law that required the tenth part, &amp;c.</hi> This hath, and will appear moſt falſe; mean time circular Arguments are <hi>uſque ad nauſeam,</hi> tedious and abſurd tautologies, odious to the prudent Readers. <hi>But,</hi> Abraham <hi>paid tythes to</hi> Melchiſedec, and <hi>Jacob</hi> vowed a tenth to God, which no doubt, he alſo paid: Did theſe acts of theirs anſwer no command, or motion of Gods Spirit equivalent thereto?<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note> How then is it teſtified, that theſe <hi>died in the faith?</hi> Can faith, as to pleaſe God, be without a divine precept? If you would ſuppoſe, <hi>That</hi> Abraham <hi>gave tythes to</hi> Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec, as of meer benevolence to ſome diſtreſſed Prince, how think you came <hi>Jacob</hi> to vow a tenth, rather then ſome other part? how ſo great a part of the world, if not by imitation of Gods people conſtantly and religiouſly paying tythes? What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you conclude of theſe, certainly they were not guilty of Will-worſhip, of whom God teſtifieth, <hi>that they died in the faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was not</hi> (ſay you) <hi>a received Doctrine, that tythes ought to be paid till about the year One thouſand and two.]</hi> It is eaſie to anſwer, That with Unbelievers, the Goſpel which Chriſts Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Lips Preached, was a <hi>Doctrine not generally received.</hi> Was the <hi>Jews</hi> unbelief, which gave that holy Doctrine no better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, any prejudice to the truth of Chriſt? He ſaid of <hi>John Baptiſt, Matth.</hi> 11.14. <hi>If ye will receive it, this is</hi> Elias <hi>which was for to come:</hi> And again, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.12. <hi>I ſay unto you, that</hi> Elias <hi>is come already</hi>—: What if the <hi>Jews</hi> then would not, or Papiſts now will not receive this Doctrine, as their learned Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 1. l. 3. c. 6. de Pontif. Rom. &amp; Tom. 4 de gra. Prim. hom. c. 14.</note> who affi meth, That <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> ſhall come before the end of the world, to oppoſe Antichriſt, and to convert the <hi>Jews.</hi> Doth mans unbelief any whit annul the truth of Chriſt? You ſee the feebleneſs of this your Argument, from the generality of mens not receiving a Doctrine, to conclude it not true. Your nineth and tenth Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, are to no purpoſe againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:179525:20"/>Moreover you ſay,<note place="margin">11.</note> 
               <hi>That tythes were brought in as a duty ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, and were ſo required and enforced, &amp;c.]</hi> This may be an Argument againſt you, it is nothing againſt us. But we ſay more, What can any Law made by man, have for ſo ſure a ground, as the Law and Commandment of God, upon which all Humane Laws and Decrees are, or ought to be grounded? And who gives Divine or Civil property (as to juſtice inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feaceable) but God, <hi>whoſe the Earth is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1.</note> 
               <hi>and all the fulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?</hi> From him we claim our portion. As for the Coercive Laws of Princes, giving us a <hi>jus ad rem,</hi> we look upon Gods good providence therein, and thankfully acknowledge their favors, for the preſervation of Gods worſhip, and our Miniſters ſubſiſtence; without which, it is too evident, that many mens Atheiſtical confidence would embolden them ſecurely to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on the Juſtice of God, as they commonly do, when there are no witneſſes of their ſacriledge preſent: They have no Law of Conſcience to hinder them, from taking away what they can from Miniſters.</p>
            <p>You ſay again, <hi>That till the year Twelve hundred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12.</note> 
               <hi>or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, it was the common practice, for every one to beſtow his tythes where he pleaſed.]</hi> Suppoſing it a free-gift, the owner had fair colour ſo to do. But were this true, as it is far from it; what were the common <hi>practice of every one,</hi> againſt the Law of God, more or leſs than a general Rebellion againſt him? And your ſelf in your next Obſervation, ſhew the miſchief en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing on ſuch arbitrary diſpoſitions; to wit, <hi>inriching thoſe lives of Drones, Abbeys, and Monaſteries:</hi> And you alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, <hi>That all exemptions from payment of tythes, came from the Pope.</hi> You ſay here, <hi>To beſtow his tythes;</hi> as if they were alms of free benevolence, and not duty by God injoyned: But we claim a right, not depending on your charity, knowing it too well. You are not ſo kinde to the Prophet,<note place="margin">1 Kings 17.6.</note> as the Ravens at the Brook of <hi>Cherich,</hi> they brought him Bread and Fleſh <hi>in the morning,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>in the evening;</hi> but you would rather ſtarve your Prophet, and pick out his eyes. Your fifteenth and ſixteenth Obſervation, we conceive make nothing againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:179525:21"/>Next you talk of tythes, <hi>That they are the ſame thing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther claimed by an Abbey, or Impropriator, or a Prieſt, and ſtand upon the ſame ground and foundation, &amp;c.]</hi> That they are the ſame in <hi>materiâ ſubjectâ;</hi> it is true, but to no purpoſe urged: Would you intimate, that there is in the Creatures tythed ſuch an inherent miſchief, as that <hi>quatenus ipſum,</hi> they muſt needs be evil, which are once tythed, whether taken by Gods Law, or by man impropriated? If ſo, the madneſs of your Argument ſufficiently appears. Sacrificing <hi>fleſh to idols,</hi> did not in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> judgment,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.25, 27, 28.</note> ſo pollute it, but that it might be eaten, <hi>asking no queſtion for Conſcience ſake.</hi> That you mention an <hi>Impropriator,</hi> or a <hi>Prieſt, and tythes,</hi> ſtanding on the ſame ground. If you mean by <hi>Prieſt, a Miniſter of the Goſpel,</hi> and tythes impropriated, you croſs your own Conceſſions, and the Dictates of Gods Law. Truly by your obſcure grumbling, you ſeem to be very angry, and that you would fain bite, but that you know that your Toothleſs Argument cannot hurt us. And this, poſſibly ſo diſcompoſed the <hi>Animal,</hi> that (as if he had forgotten on which ſide he is) in his ſeventeenth Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he doth ingenuouſly confeſs, <hi>A ſtate of a Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to corruption, and error, clearly to be diſcerned and traced in that; as the power of truth was loſt, ſo was the fruit thereof, which cauſed ſuch earneſt preſſing to needful contributions;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 15.</note> 
               <hi>and when that would not ſerve, Laws and Decrees were made to force them: But in the beginning it was not ſo; for while the purity and ſimplicity of the Goſpel was retained, there needed no preſſing; for their charity then abounded, not onely to the tenth part</hi> (that is, tythes) <hi>but for greater parts. Antonii gladios potuit contemnere, ſi ſic omnia dixiſſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">18.</note>Next you ſay, <hi>That the right of tythes was never cleared, even among the greateſt Papiſts.]</hi> What is that to us? <hi>Ipſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deant;</hi> were ever all Caſes of <hi>Conſcience</hi> cleared among them? adviſe with your own <hi>Caſuiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further you ſay, <hi>In all ages there were thoſe that withſtood the payment of them.]</hi> What then? we know it to our grief: Hereto you may cite this preſent age, with a—<hi>witneſs our ſelf at</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:179525:21"/>Conclude now (we challenge you thereto) but conclude <hi>categorically,</hi> Whatſoever hath been withſtood by ſome in all ages, is not good or juſt. The payment of Tythes to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, hath been withſtood by ſome in all ages; <hi>ergo,</hi> the payment of Tythes to Miniſters, is not good or juſt.</p>
            <p>To ſuch a concluſion your <hi>medium</hi> looks, if you deal ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally; and if ſo, who ſees not the falſhood of your <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor</hi> Propoſition, which can neither by you, nor any Sophiſter in the World be proved? For if that were univerſally true, that whatſoever hath been withſtood <hi>by ſome in all ages,</hi> is not good or juſt; What would become of the holy <hi>Goſpel it ſelf?</hi> You know what the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 28.22.</note> 
               <hi>As concerning this Sect, we know that every where it is ſpoken againſt.</hi> What truth was ever yet ſo evident to all men, that it found no contradiction? Blind <hi>Harpaſte</hi> will contend, that the room hath no light. Antiquity wanted not an <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> ſo paradoxical,<note place="margin">Fir. Lactant.</note> as to affirm that the ſnow is black; of all truths, Satan will be ſure, that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhall never want Adverſaries: ſome <hi>Jewes</hi> or other, to gain-ſay the preaching thereof, and to withſtand the Miniſters, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> reſiſted <hi>Moſes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> ſome tinkerly <hi>Alexander</hi> the Copper-Smith.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.4.</note> O but <hi>ſome of the Martyrs</hi> (ſaith our <hi>Antagoniſt) among other things, ſuffered in flames,</hi> you ſay, <hi>for that,</hi> ſci. <hi>denying payment of Tythes.</hi> We anſwer, poſſibly a <hi>Martyr</hi> may not know all things, and therefore may err in ſome; but ſtill we muſt remember, that it is the Cauſe, not the Puniſhment, which makes the <hi>Martyr.</hi> Few are perſwaded, that either the <hi>Conclave</hi> which <hi>canonized Garnet,</hi> had power to make him a Saint; or that your <hi>Neoteric</hi> Saints have authority or warrant from God to <hi>unſaint the Evangeliſts, Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> ever ſince their times, owned for Saints;<note place="margin">Rom. 1.7. Rom. 16.15. 1 Cor. 1.2. 2 Cor. 1.1. Eph. 1.1. &amp;c.</note> and ſo by calling, we fear leaſt their next attempt ſhould be to deveſt St. <hi>Mathew,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> &amp;c. and to ſend them out among the vulgar, by the names of <hi>Mat, Jac</hi> and <hi>Tom:</hi> But now juſtifie your aſſertion, and ſhew us any one <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who ever was of your opinion, in denying the payment Tythes, and ſuffering death for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Next you demand,<note place="margin">Page 16.</note> 
               <hi>Whether any perſon have a true and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179525:22"/>
property in the tenth part of another mans encreaſe]</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch legality, by the Laws of man, I conceive you make no queſtion; concerning divine Law, if your quaere be; that upon the matter, is to doubt, whether God hath property in mans encreaſes, or hath power and right, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the ſame to whom he will? For the firſt part of ſuch a queſtion, I take it to be indiſputable, with all thoſe who take Gods Word to be their rule and guide; he ſaying expreſly, <hi>all the Tythes of the Land;</hi> whether <hi>of the ſeed of the Land, or the fruit of the Tree, is the Lords; it is holy unto the Lord — ſo of the Tythe of the Herd, or of the Flock, the tenth ſhall be holy unto the Lord,</hi> Levit. 27.30, 32. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe he ſaith, <hi>Ye have robbed me,</hi> though the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſaid (as many amongſt us now, think it is no robbing of God, to take away,<note place="margin">M l 3.</note> or detain Tythes from his Miniſters) <hi>Wherein have we robbed thee?</hi> God ſaith, Ye have robbed me in <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Offerings;</hi> and therefore were they curſed; even the <hi>whole Nation.</hi> As for the ſecond part of the doubt, all know, that the right and abſolute <hi>Proprietor,</hi> who holds not of any other, but is the <hi>Lord Paramount,</hi> hath right and free power to aſſign his propriety to any other, or others. Now God doth as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſay, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.24. <hi>&amp;c. The Tythes—I have given to the Levites to inherit:</hi> Of which, he yet reſerved to himſelf the Heave-offering, as it were a Quit-rent for their acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his Soveraign right over all. Now from his grant we claim a moral, and ſo an unalterable right due to thoſe, whom he appointeth to ſerve about holy things, and not ſolely from the Laws of good Princes and States, though as your ſelf pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently confeſs in the ſame <hi>Paragraph, Tythes are to be paid, becauſe commanded by the State, and that Law and equity obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the payment.</hi> That which you after ſay, <hi>That the perſon that claims them, may have no particular intereſt,</hi> is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to the forecited Scriptures, and your own Conceſſions; as alſo by that which immediatly you grant, it appeareth falſe; where you ſay, if a true legal <hi>Property be in another perſon to the tenth part of my encreaſe, I ought in conſcience to yeeld and ſet it forth, becauſe it is not mine.</hi> To which we ſay, Firſt, What can be a true or legal Property, if that be not ſuch, which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179525:22"/>
God himſelf gives, makes the conveiance, and in his holy Word teſtifieth, that he hath given and ſetled as Inheritance, and for ſuch ſervice, on thoſe whom he hath appointed to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter about holy things? Next we ſay, that you can have no right in Tythes; that they ſhould become yours either by pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe (for who hath right to ſell Gods part, and that <hi>invito Domino?</hi>) Nor by deſcent or preſcription.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt</hi> (you ſay) <hi>claims theſe to be due,</hi> jure divino, <hi>and produce the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>for it, &amp;c.]</hi> What other mens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are, or have been, cannot make our right and claim by Gods divine <hi>donation</hi> by the moral Law, void; and therefore we trouble not our ſelves about them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have</hi> (you ſay again) <hi>diligently for two years and more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 17.</note> 
               <hi>laboured to enform my ſelf, &amp;c.]</hi> Here you bring an argument from the time you have ſpent in ſtudying this point, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied unerring faculty of apprehenſion. For if this were not, no time can profit to good information. Concerning the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of this reaſon, I leave to others to judge, who better know your abilities of Art and Nature than I yet do; but now give me leave to ask, what Authors ſtudied you? Very likely, ſome, who were in the ſame error with you; others who could have informed you better, you condemn unknown; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your aim is to uphold a party, for the carrying on a ſecret deſign, you did <hi>not receive the love of the truth,</hi> and therefore cannot want <hi>ſtrong deluſions:</hi> and ſo may you ſtill be of their <hi>form,</hi> who <hi>are ever learning, and never able to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the truth,</hi> if you ſtudy to deceive your ſelf and others: which if it be not ſo, I am confident that you may find enough in the writings of ſound and Orthodox Divines, to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you, if at leaſt you will not ſhut your eyes; if the vail be laid over your eyes, none but God can make you ſee; whom we pray, in his good time to remove it.</p>
            <p>You ſpeak again, <hi>of changing the Law by Chriſt, &amp;c.]</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the change of the <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> you have been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; that change is granted you, without advantage to you, or apparent damage to us. See what hath been ſaid to your 14 pag. Further we ſay, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> changed not the moral Law, in any one jot, or title thereof, as to the morality of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179525:23"/>
it;<note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> he proteſted againſt it, <hi>who is the faithful and true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> So that the precepts thereof, having no repeal appearing in all Gods Word, binde for ever unto the worlds end. Shew us if you can, where the Law-giver ever repealed the Law for tything. Bring us any one Text of holy Scripture, either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declaring it, or by neceſſary conſequence concluding it: Which ſeeing you cannot do, abuſe not the Scripture, making it to ſpeak what you pleaſe, to hold up your party: In a right uſe of Scriptures, we muſt carry ſenſe from them, not bring it to them. Your pretending to an abſolute change of the Law, cauſeth your ignorant and credulous Readers preſently to think, they are diſcharged from all duty to Moral precepts; not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that it muſt continually binde all men; and that the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judicial Law</hi> were poſitive for a time, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to <hi>Iſrael</hi> onely,<note place="margin">12ae. q. 122. 1. 2m.</note> as <hi>determinationes moralium;</hi> which being changed, the Moral Law ſtill continues. A diſcharge of obedience hereto granted, what an Harveſt would the Devil reap from theſe pernicious Tares, which you ſcatter in the Lords field? and what unſpeakable confuſion would follow? what (out of Hell) can be imagined more damnable? Conſider therefore what deſigns of Satan your captious diſputes carry on: You will ſay you intend no ſuch thing;<note place="margin">Parum intereſt quo animo fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceris, quod fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſe malum eſt.</note> but it skills not with what intent you do that which is evil to be done.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>Much more colour had the Quiriſters, &amp;c.] Homo ſuavis;</hi> a merry man, I trow: But I am not at leiſure to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change words concerning odde Crotchets.</p>
            <p>But ſay you, <hi>How doth Goſpel-Miniſtry ſucceed to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, &amp;c.]</hi> We have ſpoken hereof before, and ſay more; firſt, they ſucceed the Legal Prieſthood, as they are Miniſters of holy things; and therefore muſt live of Chriſts portion, which is tythes, though their office in ſome things differ, as ſhall appear in its place. Next the Apoſtle will ſhew you. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12. <hi>The Prieſthood,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law:</hi> Where note, that he ſaith not, that the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> is aboliſhed, but <hi>changed:</hi> So the Law in the Morality thereof, is not aboliſhed, but the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and things thereto belonging, are changed. Now changing preſuppoſeth a ſuffection or ſubſtitution of ſome other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179525:23"/>
thing, in place of that which is removed: So the Miniſters ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in place of the <hi>Levitical Prieſthood;</hi> and their honorary and maintenance accompanieth the ſame. Now the portion due to <hi>Melchiſedec</hi>'s Prieſthood, which is a permanent order, is tythes; theſe being due to <hi>Chriſts Prieſthood,</hi> are due to <hi>Chriſts Miniſters.</hi> As for your buzzing about here and there, and no where ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling, concerning the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> it is nothing to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And what, ſay you, was the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> aſſured of for ſome hundred years? After you have done trifling, we ſhall have it; that the Church for ſome <hi>hundreds of years ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver called for tythes:</hi> Your own citations of <hi>Jerom, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, &amp;c.</hi> ſhew this to be groſly falſe; except by <hi>ſome hundreds,</hi> you mean onely the firſt three hundred, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the rage of perſecution, neither permitted <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to pay, nor <hi>Miniſters</hi> to receive their tythes; concerning which, we have already ſpoken, in anſwer to the ſame objection.</p>
            <p>You ſay again, <hi>What is this to the payment of tythes?]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 18.</note> What that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid tythes? very much. Firſt, this imports a right in <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> to take them, and therefore a <hi>debitum</hi> in <hi>Abraham</hi> to pay them; who having a ſpecial direction, by ſome inſpiration, which had the force of an injunction, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s act was of duty, not arbitrary benevolence; yea, by the Moral Law, which before the exact tranſcript thereof on the Tables of Stone, was the very ſame with the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> which bound not onely <hi>Abraham,</hi> but all perſons reſpectively, to all times and places. For, to worſhip God is a Moral Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, though for the time, the determination thereof,<note place="margin">12 ae. q. 99.</note> as to the manner how, appertained to the Ceremonial, which being <hi>antiquated</hi> and changed into another manner of worſhip under the Goſpel; yet is ſtill the ſame in point of Morality, which bound and unchangeably bindeth all. You poſſibly may ſay, <hi>Abraham</hi> paid tythes but once; but there needs no other proof, that he conſtantly paid them at other times, as well as that once ſpecified to <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> becauſe God teſtified concerning him, ſaying, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>I know him, that he will command his children, and his houſhold after him; and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice and judgment;</hi> which is after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards interpreted, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32 46. <hi>By doing all the words of this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179525:24"/>
Law.</hi> Adde hereto, that he onely is good and juſt, who is conſtantly ſo, and accordingly <hi>Jacob</hi> alſo paid tythes; becauſe the Morality of the Law, univerſally binding to this duty of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and Juſtice, bound all men and ever reſpectively to do the ſame; how elſe fell <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> upon a <hi>tenth,</hi> rather then on a <hi>fifth, ſeventh,</hi> or <hi>twelfth</hi> part? <hi>Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> as alſo to do any thing in faith, which God commandeth not.</p>
            <p>You ſay more, that—<hi>few are now left, who will onely ſtand to it, and the generality are of a contrary minde.] Few are now left:</hi> We may thank your rage for that. But I demand, doth the appearing paucity of any Truths, Profeſſors diſparage their Cauſe? What then ſhall we think of <hi>Eliah</hi> crying, — <hi>I onely am left?</hi> Were there not then many thouſands on the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſide, whom he knew not of? might it not even then, have been anſwered to him, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to his ſervant, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.6. —<hi>Fear not, for they that be with us, are more then they that be with them?</hi> But what you mean by, <hi>onely ſtand to it,</hi> I know not, but doubt —<hi>hic ambiguo ludimur:</hi> Mean you onely <hi>ſtand to it,</hi> that <hi>jus of receiving of tythes,</hi> and ſo wave and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim all right, which in confirmation of the ſame, good <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or Donations and Bequeathments, which well-affected men have given us, by ſeveral Laws and Acts, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ages paſt? That were fooliſhly and ingratefully done, ſo to value theſe grants, to which, you confeſs, your ſelf bound to obey, <hi>Even for Conſcience ſake.</hi> That the generality are againſt Right and Truth, I do no more wonder, then that you are—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo</hi> (you ſay) <hi>the greateſt part of the people of</hi> England <hi>deny tythes to be due by Gods Law.]</hi> To this, and that which immediately precedeth, I think no more anſwer then this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; if ſo, it is the more ſhame for them. Concerning the end of paying tythes, you have been anſwered: As for <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators,</hi> they are out of the verge of our preſent queſtion, which concerns the Miniſters portion; yet here we may uſe the ſaying of <hi>Boniface,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury. Our complaints</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hereof, are not much unlike to a dogs barking at theeves and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179525:24"/>
robbers breaking open, digging through and rifting his Maſters houſe. —Quia defenſionis auxiliatores non habeat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spelm. Concil. &amp; decret. pag. 239</note> 
               <hi>ſubmurmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans ingemiſcat, &amp; lugeat:</hi> Becauſe he cannot have helpers for defence, yet growling he will grumble and whimper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this</hi> (you ſay) <hi>leaves every man free to give to him that teacheth)</hi> I am ſure you are not very free to give to him that teacheth; and for all this preceding <hi>Miſcellany,</hi> you leave us in doubt, what you mean by, <hi>this leaves? this what?</hi> your irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute concluſion, and confuſed reſolution? Do theſe make for your dream of the Caſtle in the air, <hi>Competent maintenance for Miniſters,</hi> and that <hi>arbitrary, voluntary contribution?</hi> If you mean <hi>voluntary,</hi> to import <hi>willingly</hi> performed, as all good works muſt be, we accord. <hi>Paul</hi> Preached the Goſpel willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that act of Preaching was a voluntary act of <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 9.16, 17.</note> yet <hi>wo had been unto him, if he had not preached the Goſpel, becauſe a diſpenſation of the Goſpel was committed unto him</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning thoſe you ſpeak of, who you ſay,<note place="margin">Pag 19.</note> 
               <hi>are transformed as Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, who have the form, but want the power, who teach for filthy lucre, &amp;c.]</hi> We may take up the Eunuchs quere —<hi>Of whom ſpeaks he this? of himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8.34.</note> 
               <hi>or of ſome other man?</hi> Where is the <hi>power of godlineſs</hi> on your part, when you broach many falſhoods, ſetting up impious doctrines of men, inſtead of <hi>Gods oracles? Non ſoles te reſpicere cum aliis maledicis?</hi> Is it <hi>filthy lucre</hi> in us to require the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which God hath appointed us, or in you, who would take it from us? Gods Word doth evidently enough ſhew, to any whoſe eyes are not cloſed by prejudicate opinion, That, as there was a <hi>Legal ſervice,</hi> to which belonged a legal maintenance, a Temple and an Altar ſervice; to which, God allotted Temple and Altar portions or maintenance to them, who there ſerved; ſo, by the ſame Moral equity, there is a <hi>Goſpel ſervice,</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, adminiſtration of <hi>Holy Sacraments, &amp;c.</hi> to which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the things, or temporal perquiſites belonging to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof, which is laid down in ſundry places of holy Scripture. See <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Now if there be a portion to be ſet out unto God, and his Miniſters, out of all and every the temporal goods of every one inſtructed in the Goſpel, according to the ſum and purport of theſe places of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179525:25"/>
holy Scripture, and no certain portion or maintenance for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, be found in Gods Word, but tythes; then are tythes, the portion and maintenance allotted by Gods Word to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for their ſervice: But there is a portion to be ſet out to God and his Miniſters, out of all the temporal goods of every one inſtructed in the Goſpel, and no other determinate certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for Miniſters maintenance, mentioned in holy Scripture; <hi>Ergo,</hi> Tythes are the principal portion allotted by Gods Word to Miniſters for their ſervice: And no reaſon can our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries alleage, to make it probable, that God would have Goſpel-Miniſters means of ſubſiſtence, leſs certain and definite then the Prieſts and Levites means was under the Law. To conclude, a Law for payment of Tythes, for the maintenance of Gods publick worſhip, all confeſs; ſhew us in all Gods Word, where that Law was ever repealed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 19.</note>But you ſay, <hi>He always took care for ſuch as he ſent forth, and they never wanted, &amp;c.]</hi> And what reaſon can you ſhew, why they now ſhould? I preſume not to ask, why ſo many of Chriſts faithful Miniſters have of late been driven into great wants, and ſo are ſtill? Your device of <hi>competent maintenance,</hi> doth here but <hi>corvis hiantibus illudere.</hi> They who were ſent out by Chriſt (you ſay) <hi>reaped the fruit of their labor:</hi> What proves this, but that they ought to do ſo ſtill?</p>
            <p>Concerning Churches, which you ſay <hi>were gathered;</hi> we ſay you ought to conſider, a great difference between a ſetled or conſtituted <hi>Church,</hi> and that which in the Primitive Age of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> was ſetling, and there to be conſtituted: Therefore that which was then done, cannot reaſonably preſcribe a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for Miniſters of a <hi>Church conſtituted.</hi> There was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides perſecution, unadviſed zeal of voluntary poverty; a Bird as rare to be found in this age, as a Phenix or black Swan: There was danger of ſcandal given; we know none now, except taken, not given, in requiring our Tithes, of ſuch as you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herewith</hi> (ſay you) <hi>let our now called Churches be proved, &amp;c.]</hi> God be bleſſed, we have a more juſt and certain proof then your <hi>Lesbian</hi> rule to try our Calling by; Chriſt ſaying, <hi>By this ſhall all men know, that ye are my Diſciples, if you love one another;</hi> and for the reſt, <hi>The laborer is worthy of his hire:</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:179525:25"/>
This is appointed us by the Lord of the Vineyard by God, out of his own reſerved part; not contracted for, or arbitrarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by man. This we underſtand, that which God knew to be a proportionable <hi>honorary;</hi> not that which fickle man fancieth to be ſo. This is no mercenary wages, ſuch (as your <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> own party confeſs) are upon Covenant, Compact, Agreement or Promiſe. Now it cannot appear that ever the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was grounded on Covenant, Compact, Agreeement, Promiſe, &amp;c. but on Gods Providence and Ordinance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercenary wages</hi> is definite, particular as to the ſum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> on between party and party; ſo was not the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> maintenance in any of the <hi>Churches,</hi> to which they preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Yea, ſay you, for their preaching was free. Why they took not Tythes: you have heard formerly, that they had maintenance from the <hi>Churches,</hi> is above all diſpute; but you would have us preach freely; that is, taking no Tythes: becauſe in the Primitive <hi>Church,</hi> Charity abounding, you ſay, it appeareth not that Tythes were paid: To which, we ſay, be you ſuch firſt, as thoſe Chriſtians were to their Teachers, and then talk of gathering <hi>Churches,</hi> and our ceaſing to take Tythes. In the mean time, you cannot reaſonably require us to leave our good way, ſeeing you will not leave your evil one, of ſharking Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Wages is or ought to be proportionable to the merit of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> thoſe, that ſerve by Covenant; but the maintenance of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> could not, can not be ſuch: for they Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Spiritual things, and reap Carnal. And now, Why quarrel you our receiving theſe ſupplies of the World, to which we Preach? And from what part thereof ſhould we reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably expect to reap, but from that, on which we ſow?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> God hath determined that we ſhall live of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which we preach according to the equity of the moral Law; for this one and the ſame juſtice is to be obſerved in the Law and Goſpel.<note place="margin">12ae. q. 108. 2. o. 19.</note> The School-men well note, that the Goſpel commands no other Moralities, then the ſame which the Law commanded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And here</hi> (you ſay) <hi>rulers ſhould have wiſdom, &amp;c.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> We take you for a pretty Counſeller of State; and the Apoſtle ſaith of the Magiſtrate <hi>He beareth not the Sword in vain; for he is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179525:26"/>
the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath on him that doth evil.</hi> But in vain carrieth he the Sword, who hath not wiſdom to direct it: And is that wiſdom which you here offer our Magiſtrates, for Counſel of State, to leave <hi>Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to his own rule?</hi> What to puniſh no offenders? To cry to <hi>Chriſt</hi> as thoſe rebellious Tribes, 1 King. 14.16. <hi>See to thine own houſe David?</hi> What would become of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active Magiſtrates, and ſuch a Laiſh? For defect of Juſtice in the due execution thereof,<note place="margin">Judg 18.7. Gen. 18.25. Ezek. 5.8.</note> the <hi>Lord the Judg of all the Earth will do right;</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>becauſe they had not kept his judgments—Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, behold, I, even I am againſt thee, and will execute judgment in the midſt of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See alſo Ezek. 11.9. 2 Chron 24.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>in the ſight of the nations.</hi> So when <hi>Joaſh</hi> hearkened to wicked Counſel, and did not juſtice upon delinquents, the <hi>Lord</hi> brought upon <hi>Princes</hi> and people the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Army, <hi>ſo they executed judgment upon</hi> Joaſh. Thus will it ſtill come to paſs, that for want of <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> due execution of juſtice, God will come, and puniſh both people offending, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> conniving, or not puniſhing. And do you not mark what a parcel of ſingular wiſdom here is preſented to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is his ſpirit diminiſhed, that it cannot, or will not ſend forth, and fit Miniſters for his ſervice, or that he needs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, &amp;c.]</hi> That God can fit teachers, even by infuſed habits of knowledg, none doubt; but from his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to conclud his Will, were but a wide inference. His Spirit is not diminiſhed, he can make many Worlds; Doth this conclude that he will? He can do whatſoever he will do; Will you thence infer, that he will do what ever he can? He needs no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities;</hi> neither did he in the days of <hi>Prophets,</hi> yet had he then his <hi>Naioth</hi> in <hi>Ramah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.22, 23. a School of <hi>Prophets.</hi> So had he in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times; yet when the learned St. <hi>Paul,</hi> brought up at <hi>Gamaliels</hi> feet, wrot directions to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.13, 16. 3 Tim. 2.15,</note> he ſaith, <hi>give attendance to Reading, Exhortation and Doctrine;</hi> the fruit whereof, he preſently <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joins, for in doing this, thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelf and them that hear thee: ſo ſtudy to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto God, a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that needs not be aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth.</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:179525:26"/>
All this your party believe they can do, without any <hi>Analytical order;</hi> but if the <hi>Orator</hi> ſhould hear you, he would ſay, This is not <hi>dividere,</hi> but <hi>frangere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, to our purpoſe again: I demand, Doth Gods power to give other means of enlarging mens hearts to his ſervice, annul his Ordinance in the uſe of accuſtomed means? What then would the brain-ſick Super-ordinarian not conclude againſt Preaching of the Goſpel, and uſe of holy Sacraments?</p>
            <p>Againſt uſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> you bring an Argument, <hi>à fine:</hi> You ſay, <hi>Students go thither to learn Greek and Hebrew, the original; that they may underſtand what Chriſt ſpake, and the Apoſtles preached.]</hi> And do you not think that were worth their time and charge? What were all knowledge in the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this? But ſure you are not ignorant, that our <hi>Grammar-Schools</hi> ſend few Students to the <hi>Univerſities</hi> without a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent knowledge of the <hi>Greek;</hi> neither that there are many other excellent things, beſides Tongues, to be learned at the <hi>Univerſities.</hi> As for the <hi>Mother-tongue of Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> I ſuppoſe you are not to learn that it was <hi>Syriac,</hi> much differing from the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> both in character and form of words. I here remember you, that the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> after they had received the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as occaſion ſerved, and need required, ſpake all tongues; but writ the <hi>Canon</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> in <hi>Greek;</hi> as the <hi>Prophets</hi> wrote the <hi>Old</hi> in <hi>Hebrew.</hi> If they that heard them ſpeak in their own Language, could not underſtand their Doctrine, but that it ſeemed fooliſhneſs to them; If they had heard them ſpeak in unknown Tongues, would they no ſay <hi>that ye are mad?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.23.</note> But the cauſe of their not underſtanding their Doctrine in their own native tongue, was, becauſe the iudgment denounced, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.9, 10. was upon them; and becauſe <hi>the God of this world had blinded their eyes, which believed not:</hi> So that the <hi>light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt</hi> could not ſhine unto them. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Tongues, none but the ſtupidly-ignorant will deny to be a ſhining light: Poſſibly a blinde man, or he that winks, is not benefitted by it; but would you conclude, that therefore they who are of entire <hi>ſenſories,</hi> and willing to ſee, are, as you ſay, <hi>Nothing the nearer for it?</hi> What think you, that the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179525:27"/>
of God thought good to furniſh his Apoſtles and Diſciples <hi>with the gift of Tongues,</hi> and interpretation thereof; was that a vain and fruitleſs <hi>Donation?</hi> Were they, who thereby had the myſteries of ſalvation written in Scriptures, brought home to them in their mother-tongue, <hi>no nearer to the knowledge of the Goſpel?</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith the ſame, which Reaſon and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience confirm,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.11.</note> —<hi>If I know not the meaning of the voice, I ſhall be to him that ſpeaks, a Barbarian; and he that ſpeaks, ſhall be a Barbarian to me:</hi> And are they not <hi>nearer to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Goſpel,</hi> who underſtand the <hi>Greek,</hi> in which it was originally written, then they who are ignorant of that Tongue? <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſs, quinteſſence of dunſery! Who ever heard of ſo profeſſed a Purple <hi>John,</hi> as you here perſonate? What, was the Scripture written in Engliſh? or were the Interpreters thereof aſſiſted with ſuch infallibility of ſpirit, even in things leſs then fundamental, that they could not erre in any thing? which if you hold not, you muſt confeſs, that they who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the original muſt be <hi>nearer the knowledge</hi> of the Scriptures, then they who do, and needs muſt take up that which they do know, upon truſt. <hi>Qui benè didicit, benè docet:</hi> And on the contrary, he that never well learned, can never teach well. I may boldly affirm, that the want of learning, knowledge of tongues, and good arts have bred all theſe Schiſms and diviſions amongſt us, which render us odious and contemptible among the Nations at this day; and that it was Satans maſter-piece againſt unhappy <hi>England,</hi> to beget a contempt of learning, by emboldning a rude vulgar, to contemn the perſons of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p>To your Objection again, we ſay, That Gods Spirit needed no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> to inſtruct men; but all ſober men know, that they have need of <hi>Univerſities,</hi> wherein they may be inſtructed. What then? God can make an Aſs ſpeak; but ſurely it were not wiſely concluded, <hi>Gods Spirit is not diminiſhed, &amp;c.</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will have no more <hi>Univerſities,</hi> but ſuch Teachers, as that dull Beaſt, ſhall ſerve our turns to make us Saints of the new Edition. And ſeriouſly, were all men of your minde (at leaſt, of which you would ſeem to be) to take away our <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity bred Miniſters,</hi> by taking away their ſetled livelihood,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:179525:27"/>
neceſſity would ſo inforce, that ere long you muſt be ſerved by ſuch <hi>animals,</hi> as could onely <hi>bray pure nonſenſe by the glaſs—. Hoc Ithaci cupiunt</hi>—. Conſider whether this be not a <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itical</hi> plot, whereof I heard one of them ſay, at the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our troubles, —<hi>There is a deſign ſet upon you, which when you hear, will make your ears tingle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>Our Conſciences muſt be judge, who thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are, &amp;c.] Auditum admiſſi riſum teneatis amici!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> What? Profeſſed blindmen challenging Prerogative to judge of colours? Ambitious <hi>Abſolom</hi> did but wiſh,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>O that I were made a Judge in the Land</hi>— But you plead priviledge, <hi>Our Conſcience</hi> (you ſay) <hi>muſt be judge:</hi> And do you not ſee what a Church and Miniſtry we were like to have, if theſe men might be judges? Think you that they would allow any, but ſuch as they knew were ſurely involved in their Hereſie? But now ſpeak clearly, and miſtake not Opinion for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Opinion is grounded on probability, or that which but ſeems ſo unto deluded mindes; but Conſcience, on the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Word of God, in which can be no falſhood. Shew us now (if you be true men) that this is indeed your Conſcience, and we will go along with you: But excuſe us, if we ſubſcribe not unto ſuch dull and ſtupid opinions, for which you cannot ſhew, that <hi>Christs Miniſters</hi> were ever, in your ſenſe, <hi>made manifeſt.</hi> But you would have <hi>Magiſtrates puniſh, and reſtrain the evil:</hi> We wiſh it ſo, but doubt that you would wince, when you were under the laſh for <hi>Sacriledge;</hi> and your Opinion could not ſave your—</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>Would not this eaſe the Magiſtrate, and be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God?]</hi> To ſo impious and vain a queſtion, it is enough to anſwer, No.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who</hi> (ſay you) <hi>made him a Judge, &amp;c?]</hi> He or they who made him a <hi>Magiſtrate and a reſtrainer of the evil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A third ſort</hi> (you ſay) <hi>plead for Decrees, &amp;c.]</hi> I am loath to be expenſive of precious time, in examination of that which others plead; and I content me to ſay, concerning the rubbiſh, which you here ſcrape together, That thoſe things have been ſufficiently anſwered, by the learned and moſt induſtrious Dr. <hi>Tilſley, Animad. on Hist. of Tythes;</hi> to whom I refer
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179525:28"/>
the Reader, who deſireth further to be ſatisfied concerning thoſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And then</hi> (you ſay) <hi>about that time, it came to be received and believed, that tythes ought to be paid, &amp;c.]</hi> I cannot but think you diſſemble your knowledge, who ſay, That it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a thouſand years after Chriſt, before <hi>it came to be received and believed, that tythes ought to be paid. Origen, Cyprian, Jerom, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, &amp;c.</hi> believed them to be due, and payable, or elſe they would not have pleaded ſo earneſtly for them; and you know, that theſe lived ſome hundred of years before the time which you mention: Conſider what your ſelf have confeſſed, and for ſhame contradict not that.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>That in</hi> England, <hi>as well as other Nations, every man might have given his tythes where he pleaſed, till about the year One thouſand two hundred.]</hi> If that were true I could not but think it great pitty, that they were ſo long ignorant. But muſt we ſtill be troubled with your <hi>Crambe,</hi> and often repetitions of one and the ſame falſhood? ſurely it is already <hi>nauſeous</hi> to the underſtanding Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 21.</note>—<hi>Pleaded for Humane right]</hi> To this, and many things elſe gathered out of Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> Hiſtory of Tythes, I anſwer again, That it skills not much what others plead: God gave Miniſters the <hi>jus</hi> and right of Tythes, from that time that he had a Church: I ſay, <hi>Jus in re,</hi> a right in Tythes, though <hi>Humane Laws</hi> may be ſaid to give them <hi>Jus ad rem;</hi> that is, a Law and Cuſtom of Court, to claim and recover them as their right. To this, if <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted their power and authority, by Laws and Decrees; they did juſtly and religiouſly therein: For therefore God put the power into their hands, well knowing, how malicious Satan is againſt Miniſters of the Goſpel; and how (in his ambition to bring men to his Kingdom of Darkneſs and Atheiſm) the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Impoſtor works (as you do) on the worldly minder of <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in Religion; who wouldly gladly be of the cheapeſt one, that they might ſpare their purſes, and the neweſt, that they might be in the <hi>faſhion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:179525:28"/>Now for <hi>Statutes</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Parliaments,</hi> ſuppoſe they have power concerning mutual Humane rights, <hi>i. e. Meum</hi> and <hi>tuum;</hi> God onely hath right in his reſerves: <hi>Suum cuique,</hi> is the Rule of Juſtice; and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Give to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>that which is</hi> Caeſars; to every one that which is his; onely let Gods Portion be ſacred and inviolable. We look therefore on Statutes, as effects of Gods mercy towards his Church, making Kings and high Powers her <hi>Nurſing-fathers;</hi> and yet we ſay, that we ground not our Claim and Intereſt therein. God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by uſed a Coercive power to reſtrain the Sacriledgious, becauſe of the hardneſs of their hearts, who regard not Gods Laws, but fear Mans.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law</hi> (you ſay) <hi>doth not give any man a property.]</hi> But ſure the Law of God doth; of, and by which we hold, from whence we claim our portion. And we further ſay, That if no Humane Law, Act, or Decree, had been made for us on this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, yet had we a firm right to that, which God aſſigned us by his Will, revealed in his Word: Yet we thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that we ow very much to the Laws and Grants of good <hi>Princes, Magiſtrates, Councils,</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> for our actual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of our dues, without which, it may too eaſily appear by you, and your party; how little comfort and ſupport, mens conſciences would afford Miniſters, notwithſtanding your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>ſufficient maintenance</hi> for them, whoſe Judges you would appoint your ſelves: Was not <hi>Ticonius</hi> your Tutor,<note place="margin">Auguſt. Ep. Vincent. Cic. Acad. q l. 4.</note> or one of that Sect, who ſaid, <hi>Quod volumus, ſanctum eſt?</hi> or ſome <hi>Protagoras,</hi> affirming, <hi>Id cuique verum eſſe, quod cuique videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>He that ſaith, they are onely due by Humane Right,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> We know not any of ours, who ſay ſo: We ſay they are due by the Law of God and Man, and recoverable by Humane Laws to God ſubordinate: As, <hi>Stante Repub. Iſraeliticâ,</hi> peculiar Rights and Intereſts by the Moral Law due and claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, were juſtly recovered by the Judicial, which God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as a <hi>ſubſidium</hi> thereto, and Band of Obedience; the execution whereof, was by men appointed to judge: ſo now, For Magiſtrates are ſtill to execute juſtice according to thoſe Laws, which by Statute or Statutes, are made Judicial to us:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:179525:29"/>
And if our Magiſtrates may juſtly judge for me, I may as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly claim and recover my right by the ſame Law and Equity: Adde hereto, That Councils may and ought to make Laws, to binde the people to obey Gods Moral Law, and by juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, appoint reſtraints of tranſgreſſors thereof, that it may be well with them and their children: For, <hi>Salus populi ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Lex.</hi> This may appear, if we conſider either firſt or ſecond Table; As in caſe of prophanation and common ſwearing, or prophanation of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or againſt Murder, Adultery, Theft, we have wholſome and neceſſary Laws. Now if for the obedience to God, Humane Laws be good and neceſſary in reſpect of one Moral duty; why not in others? As, if for the maintenance of Gods worſhip in the <hi>quotâ parte</hi> of time by God reſerved, and thereto ſtill neceſſary: Why is it not as juſt and neceſſary in the <hi>quotâ parte</hi> of our ſubſtance, by the ſame Law of God reſerved to, and neceſſary for the ſame? To the matters in your following Cavils, concerning Civil Rights, Miniſters Proprieties, and Courts wherein they have been, or ought to be recovered, you vainly trouble your Reader; our claim being from Divine Law, whereto all Laws and Courts ought to be ſubordinate.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note>You ſay further, <hi>That the Act</hi> (for Tythes) <hi>gives nothing, but commands what was before.]</hi> Herein you ſay true; For God gave them from the beginning, and man confirmed them in ſundry times following.</p>
            <p>Next, you demand <hi>how Laws of Kings and Parliaments, &amp;c. binde the Conſcience?]</hi> Your ſelf have formerly anſwered; but the Apoſtle more definitively, ſaith <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 5. <hi>Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoul be ſubject unto the higher powers. — Ye muſt be ſubject</hi> (needs be ſubject) <hi>not onely for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> And St. <hi>Peter, Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man, for the Lords ſake.</hi> And—will this double band hold <hi>Samſon</hi> if it doth, ſin not againſt Conſcience, Satan-like endeavoring to ſeduce others, and draw them in ſociety of ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note>
               <hi>Tythes</hi> (you ſay) <hi>be not due by the Law of God.]</hi> This is a ſhameleſs begging of the queſtion, which will never be approved by us, or proved by you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:179525:29"/>But you ſay, <hi>Who hath ſet them up, the Law of man at beſt?]</hi> Here is another begging of the queſtion at another door, as alſo in the following words, where you ſay, in the place where God diſanulled his own command. We offer here again to joyn iſſue with you, and challenge you to ſhew us any one Text of Gods Word, whereby it appears, that God ever diſanulled or repealed his Law of Tything. For the reſt, if you could cite and urge as many Decrees of Princes, or Acts of Parliaments againſt us, as you have cited for Tythes; yet no Decrees of men can Impeach our Right therein; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God by the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of his holy Word, hath ſetled it, for an Inheritance upon the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>You demand, <hi>Who put this power into the hand of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> 
               <hi>to raiſe a compulſory maintenance for Miniſters:]</hi> The Apoſtle will tell you, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>The Magiſtrate is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath on him that doth evil;</hi> Is not execution of wrath a compulſory means, think you? Or is not Sacriledg evil in your Theology? That you further ſay, that <hi>the Miniſters of Chriſt never lookt for, or durſt own ſuch a way of proviſion.</hi> We ſay, Firſt, That the maintenance of Miniſters ought to be willingly aforded them, not grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly or ſparingly, as alſo their miniſtration; this is, as to the firſt intention of the Law; but if men will be obſtinate, Compulſion is a ſecond intention hereof. Secondly, Suppoſe that Miniſters did not own ſuch a way of proviſion for recovery of Tythes, before ſuch Acts of Parliament were made for them; What hindereth but that they may juſtly uſe ſuch Laws, now Enacted and in Force?</p>
            <p>You proceed —<hi>What Nation in Europe, will not ſay they have a Chriſtian Magiſtracy?]</hi> Do you not forget how great a part of Europe is under the Turk? Your many following impertinences ſhould have had no anſwer, but that you ſay, <hi>heavy puniſhments are inflicted upon ſuch as cannot for conſcience ſake conform unto them:</hi> To which I ſay, it was never well ſince mens Conſciences were tied to their Purſe-ſtrings, and that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions not ſo much as probable, muſt go for Conſcience. Shew us Gods Word for your Conſcience, and we will ſubmit to the ſame bond; but we think it an abominable Idolatry, to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179525:30"/>
ſet up opinions of beguiled Men, inſtead of Gods ſacred O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</p>
            <p>Concerning—<hi>This day of clear and Sunſhine light]</hi> We ſay,<note place="margin">Iſai. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> To this Law we appeal, and willingly ſubmit; Doth this ſavor, in you tender ſenſory, of the old <hi>Popiſh Spirit?</hi> Who ſees not your endeavour to re-eſtabliſh Popery, though you ſo much ſeem to ſpeak againſt it? And now let me <hi>bonâ cum veniâ,</hi> tel you, that either your hypocriſie, or ignorance is ſomthing groſs. And is this as you ſay, <hi>a ſhame to our reformation?</hi> Or is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of you deformers a ſhame to Chriſtian Religion? It is probable that you carry on the Jeſuits deſign of reducing <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to darkneſs of Popery again, by decrying Miniſters right, to a ſetled maintenance; that by taking them away, you may remove the <hi>Candleſtick</hi> out of his place, the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel from us, and then you may poſſibly bring many to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Atheiſm. I muſt needs ſay, that this perſonated <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lote</hi> ſpeaks much againſt Popery, but works what he can for it; on whom I look as on Thames-water-men, with their faces one way, but labouring might and main, to carry their Paſſengers and Veſſel another.</p>
            <p>You add—<hi>Were the Law juſt commanding Tythes, &amp;c.]</hi> What will he not queſtion,<note place="margin">Pag. 24.</note> who doubteth of the equity of the Law? I hope you mean humane Law, which yet is founded on Gods Law; and have you not learned of <hi>Socrates, to doubt of all things?</hi> Concerning <hi>treble damages,</hi> or other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which the Law hath appointed obſtinate tranſgreſſors; I ſuppoſe you know, that the plaintifs charges of the Suit, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly exceed the dammage juſtly awarded him, towards his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration therein; ſo that even under the tender hands of juſt Judges, the remedy is more burdenſome, than the diſeaſe; theſe puniſhments therefore are but juſt. What injuſtice is it, think you, to force a Thief or Poſſeſſor <hi>malae fidei</hi> to reſtore the goods of another man, which he hath injuriouſly poſſeſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of, and ſtill deteineth? What injuſtice can be in a legal reinveſting the true owner? And in caſe that the iniurious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſubmit to the Law, to compel him by ſome ſevere
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:179525:30"/>
puniſhment by Law provided in ſuch caſe? And if this be juſtice in one caſe, Why ſhall it not be ſo in another kind of wrong or robberry? Why not in caſe of Sacriledg, the worſt of robberies, if in inferior thieveries? O, but you ſay our conſciences tell us, that detention of Tythes from Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, is no ſin. What if a Thieves Conſcience (as you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Conſcience) ſhould tell him, that had robbed you, that ſtealing is no ſin; Would you not purſue him, and proſecute law againſt him? I doubt in your next ſcruple, your weak and tender Conſciences will tell you, that 'tis a ſin, to pay your Land-lords any Rent, or at leaſt their ſin, to Diſtrain or Sue for any, though you can, but will not, for your Conſcience ſake forſooth pay him any: And will not the next queſtion in your Schools, be whether it be lawful <hi>In foro Conſcientiae,</hi> to pay any Debt?</p>
            <p>—<hi>To ſet out Tythes, &amp;c.]</hi> You ſay, this is againſt his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; once again we require you to ſhew us any one Text of Scripture, prohibiting ſeting out of Tythes; that we may know, that it is Conſcience, and not Opinion, grounded on humane fancy, malice, greedy deſire of enriching your ſelves by pillaging the Miniſters, which moveth you to think ſo.</p>
            <p>You ſay,—<hi>This age ſo much pretends to reformation]—and every one cries wo, wo, and he complain's, that help's to make it ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are you not a chief pretender to Reformation? Why then trouble you the ſacred peace of the Church? And truly, I fear, that it will come to paſs which you next ſay, that Papiſts (your honoured Patrones) ſhall riſe in judgment againſt you, and condemn you; they own ſome Order, Unity, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Law; they have ſome ſhew of Devotion and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Charity; but in our new Sectaries, I ſee very little of theſe, if any at all. Your following objections in this Page, are but quarrelſom, captious, as to the preſent, not deſerving anſwer.</p>
            <p>You ſay—<hi>By conſcientious men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> 
               <hi>far more heavy than the loyns of the Law]</hi> Conſcientious men, and Opinatours, are with you, <hi>convertible terms;</hi> as concerning abuſes in offices, we are ignorant; But what if there were ſuch things? What were this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179525:31"/>
to our Cauſe? You ſay nothing againſt thoſe wealthy Kerns, who by detaining Tythes, begger poor Miniſters and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, which we know to be true: In this, 'tis marvel, but you think <hi>they do God ſervice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 16.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>The Pope himſelf hath no ſuch penalties.]</hi> No? what think you of his holy Houſe, forſooth, his Inquiſition Preaching with fire and faggot? You ſay, <hi>You write what you can prove by manifold inſtances.</hi> It may be ſo in ſome things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent; and poſſibly you are acquainted with the Popes Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and (what ever you ſeem under your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſguiſe) are a right truſty <hi>Advocate</hi> for them.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>Prieſts are not able to pay tenths unto the Protector, &amp;c.]</hi> What Prieſts you talk of, we enquire: We own not that title in any, but <hi>Chriſt, a Prieſt for ever after the order of</hi> Melchiſedec, <hi>that faithful High Prieſt in things pertaining to God, Heb.</hi> 2.17. And as we conceive, ancient <hi>Councils, Fathers,</hi> and the Rubrick of our <hi>Church Liturgy,</hi> attribute that name to Miniſters of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Cyprian. ep. Caecilio. l. 2. ep. 3.</note> by way of analogy and alluſion to that, which was under the now-antiquated Ceremonies of the Law. So <hi>Irenaeus, l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20. ſaith, —<hi>Sacerdotes autem ſunt omnes Domini Apoſtoli—ſemper Altari &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eo ſerviunt:</hi> That is in reſpect of their ſucceeding the <hi>Levitical Prieſthood,</hi> and alluſion to their ſervice. So <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.32. <hi>Sacrificium Deo cor contribulatum;</hi> and <hi>Cap.</hi> 33. —<hi>Incenſa</hi> Johannis <hi>in Apocalyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, orationes ait eſſe ſanctorum:</hi> For, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Adv. Jud. l.</hi> 17. the old Prieſthood was to ceaſe, <hi>ut novus ſacerdos veniret, qui in aeternum futurus eſſet;</hi> that is onely Chriſt. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.23. an elegant figure whereof immediately preceded Chriſts coming, when <hi>Zachary,</hi> the Levitical Prieſt, was to come out and bleſs the people, he was dumb: For then God would bleſs his people by his Son Chriſt, the <hi>Eternal Prieſt, after the order of Melchiſedec;</hi> who not onely auſpicated his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſundry bleſſings, but aſcending into Heaven, lifting up his hands,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.2, &amp;c. Luk. 24.50, 51.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed his Diſciples.</hi> When he was to come into the World, the Prieſt, the ſon of <hi>Aaron,</hi> could not ſpeak; that by that ſign, God might teach his people to expect another Prieſthood, and Prieſt, in whom not onely <hi>Jews,</hi> but <hi>all the Nations of the World ſhould be bleſſed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.8.</note> And this was alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:179525:31"/>
in that the <hi>Levitical Prieſts</hi> were after the <hi>morning Sacrifice</hi> onely, to lift up their hands, and bleſs the people; but not after the <hi>Mincha</hi> or <hi>evening Sacrifice;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maimon. tract. de Orat. c. 14. Heb. 1.1, 2. &amp; 13.10, 15.</note> for in the <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of time,</hi> God ſpake unto his people by his own Son Chriſt. To our purpoſe again, the <hi>Lords Table</hi> may be called <hi>an Altar;</hi> and <hi>praiſes of God,</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> as it is written, <hi>By him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let us offer the Sacrifice of praiſe to God continually: So will we render the calves of our lips, Hoſ.</hi> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. So are all the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of <hi>Chriſt Prieſts;</hi> not by propriety of ſpeaking,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.6. &amp; 5.10. &amp; 20.6. 1 Pet. 2.5.</note> but as they are alſo called <hi>Kings,</hi> by analogy and repreſentation. Nor do I remember where Miniſters are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Prieſts</hi> in the Goſpel. Here it is neceſſary to conſider, 1. How Miniſters may be called Prieſts. 2. How not, or wherein there appears a real difference between them, and <hi>Levitical Prieſts,</hi> properly ſo called.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Prieſthood being changed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.12.</note> he implyeth, that the Office of Miniſtration in the publick worſhip of God is not aboliſhed, or taken quite away; ſo that there is nothing ſubſtituted in the place thereof, but that the Office, as to the morality thereof, ſo continues as that <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logically,</hi> Miniſters of the Goſpel may in ſome ſenſe be called Prieſts. The Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> makes them convertible terms,<note place="margin">Joel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Let the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord, weep</hi>—: And the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaking of the calling of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 66.21, &amp;c.</note> ſaith, <hi>I will alſo take of them for Prieſts, and for Levites, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Levitical Prieſt</hi> ſerved at the Altar, that is, Did there that ſervice, which by Gods Law he was there to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: And ſo the Miniſter is to do that ſervice in the Church, which God hath, under the Goſpel, appointed and ſetled on him in his Calling thereto, and ſeparation from the people, in preaching the Goſpel, Praying, Adminiſtration of the Holy Sacraments, and thoſe other Miniſterial Functions, which are peculiar to his Calling.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Prieſts had their certain and determinate allowance and maintenance aſſigned them out of the encreaſes of the Earth (by Gods donation) for his ſervice;<note place="margin">Hebr. 7.5.</note> never being left to the curteſie, or charity of men, no not the faith <hi>Moſes</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179525:32"/>
of; and ſo have the Miniſters of the Goſpel: In both which, it was and is ſacriledge, to alienate, take away, detain, or change the whole or any part thereof, otherwiſe reſerved by God to his own ſervice, and aſſigned to the Miniſters thereof, or to reduce the ſame to common uſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Miniſters of the Goſpel ſucceeding the Legal Prieſts in the publick ſervice of God, as perſons in their Office ſacred, to which they are ſet apart, or ſeparated, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15. may not deſert, or be diſtracted from their Calling, nor impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to any other. Thus, and in ſuch like reſpects, they may analogically be ſtiled <hi>Prieſts;</hi> as hath been ſaid, <hi>thanksgiving</hi> may be called a <hi>Sacrifice, Pſal.</hi> 116.17. Spiritual, not bodily or proper;<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.2.</note> as Prayers are <hi>Spiritual incenſe. Let my prayer be directed as incenſe in thy ſight, and the lifting up my hands, as the evening ſacrifice;</hi> and as I ſaid, the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> may be called an <hi>Altar;</hi> not properly, but by way of alluſion to that, to which it ſucceeded: So may <hi>Goſpel Ministers</hi> be ſtiled <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Herein obſerve, That the <hi>Legal Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> differ.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Legal Prieſts</hi> were to be onely of that tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and family of <hi>Aaron, Exod.</hi> 40.13, 14. But the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> (if lawfully called) are limitted to no one ſtock or family, but may be of any: So that the <hi>Legal Prieſts</hi> were in ſome ſort, born to the Prieſthood; but Miniſters are ſeparated thereto: Therefore the Lord taking to himſelf, a people under the Goſpel <hi>out of all Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 66.20, 21.</note> ſaith, <hi>And I will alſo take of them for Prieſts, and for Levites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Judg 6.37, &amp;c. Deut. 32.2, &amp;c.</note>2. The <hi>Levitical Prieſt</hi> was to execute his Function among the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> onely: Then <hi>Judea</hi> like <hi>Gideons</hi> Fleece had the dew of Heaven, the Doctrine and Myſteries of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the floor of the world beſide was dry; as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147, 19, 20. <hi>He ſheweth his Word unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>his Statutes and his Judgments unto</hi> Iſrael; <hi>he hath not dealt ſo with any Nation. And as for his Judgments, they have not known them.</hi> And ſo Chriſts injunction bound his Diſciples for a time, <hi>Go not into the way of the Gentiles;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.5. &amp; 28.19.</note> but after his Aſcenſion, the Miniſters are to go into all, or any part of the world, to Preach
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:179525:32"/>
the Goſpel <hi>to every creature:</hi> Now the <hi>floor</hi> hath the <hi>dew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 16.15. Rom. 11.25. Eph. 2. Col. 3.11. Gal. 3.28.</note> and the <hi>fleece</hi> is dry, ſince that <hi>blindneſs is come upon Iſrael.</hi> Now <hi>the ſtop of the partition wall is taken down;</hi> and in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there is no difference between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, bond and free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Levitical Prieſts</hi> offered real, external, viſible, material, proper, and bloody Sacrifices; but the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel offer onely ſpiritual Sacrifices, Prayers, Praiſes, Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, as they are <hi>an holy Prieſthood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5. Revel. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>to offer up ſpiritual Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, acceptable to God by Jeſus Christ: For he hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto his Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Levitical Prieſt</hi> was to officiate in outward Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of a <hi>worldly Sanctuary,</hi> which were <hi>ſhadows of good things to come,</hi> which Rites are now antiquated:<note place="margin">Heb. 9.1. &amp; 10.1. Col. 2.20. 1 Cor. 9.11. 1 Pet. 2.5.</note> But the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel</hi> officiates in things ſpiritual and permanent; therefore the <hi>Levitical Prieſthood</hi> is utterly ceaſed. Theſe things which then prefigured <hi>Chriſt</hi> to come in the fleſh, and to die for our Redemption, after his coming and fulfilling all things fore-ordained, prefigured under the Law, and foretold by the Prophets, are done away and aboliſhed; as not onely dead, but a killing letter, a miniſtration of Condemnation: Before which, the Law killed <hi>non effectivè,</hi> or <hi>per ſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.2. 2 Cor. 3.7, 9. 12ae. q. 97. 2, 3m.</note> but <hi>occaſione ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptâ, non datâ;</hi> by reaſon of mans infirmity. But now after the Paſſion of Chriſt, the Ceremonial Law is not onely <hi>Lex mortua,</hi> but in the profeſſion and obſervation thereof, <hi>Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fera;</hi> becauſe thereby <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall <hi>nothing profit men;</hi> becauſe ſuch Ceremonies hold out an expectation of <hi>Chriſt the Saviour</hi> of the elect to come: Which whoever now profeſſeth,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.2, 4.</note> is <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian,</hi> renouncing the true and onely Redeemer already come in the fulneſs of time, and ſo cutting himſelf off from all hope of Salvation; <hi>there being no other name given under Heaven among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 4.11,</note> neither is there ſalvation in any other. Now the preſent Miniſtry is of the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel of Chriſt;</hi> and the Miniſters thereof,<note place="margin">Revel. 14.6.</note> are <hi>Ambaſſadors of Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Deputies</hi> for the Goſpel on Earth, who <hi>is a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchiſedec;</hi> who changeth not by Death and Succeſſion, as the <hi>Levitical Priest, but liveth ever;</hi> and is a <hi>faithful High Prieſt over the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:179525:33"/>
Houſe of God:</hi> Other Prieſthood, in propriety of ſpeaking, we own none.</p>
            <p>To conclude, we muſt conſider, that ſome names which once were venerable and honorable, have in proceſs of time, become opprobrious and diſgraceful terms, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. The word <hi>Tyrant. Servius in Aenei. l.</hi> 7. tells us that with the <hi>Grecians, Tyranni &amp; Regis nulla diſcretio eſt.</hi> And <hi>Suidas</hi> ſheweth alſo that it was once,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Nomen melioris ominis, ac levius,</hi> until <hi>Dyonyſius,</hi> and others like, by their cruelty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honored it: Since, it ſignifieth the worſt of men, becauſe of bad, the greateſt; ſuch as <hi>Jerom</hi> deſcribeth, <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triad. de virg. ſervand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The name <hi>Papa,</hi> (as hath been ſaid) was once of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, until the eminent impiety of ſome ſo called, embaſed the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The name <hi>Magus,</hi> was once among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable title, as alſo among others. <hi>Suidas</hi> gives <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>lovers of God:</hi> And <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Magi differunt à maleficis; aliqui honeſti, &amp;c.</hi> ſuch for continence he ſpecifieth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>adv. Jovin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serv. in lib. 4. Aenei.</note> Yet the <hi>Romans</hi> condemned <hi>Magic, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſa enim ars habita eſt.</hi> And <hi>Jerom in Eph. Proem.</hi> notes, that the <hi>Epheſian Idolaters</hi> were given to <hi>magic, Which ever</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>follows idolatry.</hi> This might be inſtanced in many great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Poſſibly, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was once alſo of honeſt ſignification, which ſome learned men give by <hi>Caupona,</hi> a <hi>Victualer:</hi> So <hi>Vatablus, Pagnin</hi> and <hi>Val. Shindler,</hi> after the <hi>Chaldee, John</hi> 2.1. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.27. he gives this reaſon, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Spies. Si fuiſſet meretrix, hi viri ad illam non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſſent, ob ſuſpiciones, &amp; ſcortatorum advenientium metum.</hi> The ſeventy whom the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> Writers,<note place="margin">Joſh. 2.1.</note> generally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, becauſe it was then their <hi>Vulgar Greek,</hi> render it by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>meretricis,</hi> and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>meretrices,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3. deriving it from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſcortatus fuit,</hi> but the <hi>Rabbins</hi> derive the word which we ſpeak of, from, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, among other things ſignifying <hi>cibatus eſt</hi> in the <hi>Chalde:</hi> It may ſeem, that the ill behavior of ſuch Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, had cauſed the word ſo much to decline to infamy.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:179525:33"/>5. Certainly, that ſacred name of <hi>Prieſt,</hi> in proper ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and in <hi>Analogical</hi> among <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by the rebellion of ſome of them againſt God and his Chriſt, and their impurity of example in the declining condition of the <hi>Church,</hi> in the mouths of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> from an honorable ſignification became diſgraceful; though thoſe of better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, knew and know how to uſe it to the reverence of <hi>Goſpel Ministers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have thus much digreſſed for their ſakes, who do not,<note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> but would underſtand theſe things, and now again to our adverſary and his courſe eloquence.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>Oh ſhameful Reformation! what compel a man himſelf to ſet out the tythes of his own goods, to maintain a hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Prieſt, &amp;c.]</hi> The <hi>Orator</hi> would here ſay, <hi>Let this perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be in the equity of Greeks, Qui maledictis inſectantur eos, à quibus de veritate diſſentiunt: Shameful Reformation! Hireling Prieſt! O ſhameful ſcurrility!</hi> I ſay not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>bona verba quaeſo;</hi> poſſibly your canine eloquence would break you, if it had no vent. For my part, I have no liſt to bark again at ſo angry a Cur; had I any ſuch cuſtom or minde, I could ſay with <hi>Jerom, Poſſum remordere ſivelim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Dominon. ep. l. 2.</note> 
               <hi>poſſum genuinum den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem laeſus infigere.</hi> But I ſay onely conſider with whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle araigneth revilers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. and what is the root of rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing—<hi>Perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt mindes, and deſtitute of the truth;</hi> and mark well, if in that glaſs, you do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern your own countenance.</p>
            <p>That you wiſh for, <hi>Old Prieſts, and old Eccleſiaſtical Courts</hi> (that is, Popiſh) I eaſily believe, that herein you do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble: But if there be any ſuch abuſes, as you pretend; what is that to the cauſe of tything? doth an abuſe by man, in your <hi>logick</hi> conclude, a juſt cauſe to take away the holy uſe of that which hath been abuſed? if that were ſo, how little good would be left us of all the Creatures of God? and what <hi>cruelty</hi> is it,<note place="margin">Pag. 26.</note> think you, ſeverely and according to Law, to puniſh obſtinate offenders, who can, but will not let go that, which they have robbed juſt owners of?</p>
            <p>Next you ſtomack it, that ſome ſay <hi>Minſters have as good right to the tenth part, as the owner hath to the other nine.]</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:179525:34"/>
which is moſt true: Conſider for the better underſtanding hereof. 1. The common or civil right of men, which the Laws of Nations give, and confirm to every poſſeſſor <hi>bonae fidei,</hi> by purchaſe, diſcent, &amp;c. this right to the creatures, a <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi> may have, in that determinate portion which he poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. 2. The divine right which man had in his Creation, but loſt in his fall, and utterly forfeited in the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor; this was reſtored again to believers in the ſecond <hi>Adam, Chriſt;</hi> of which he ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22, 23. <hi>All are yours, and ye are Chriſts:</hi> This belongs only to the Elect. In both theſe kinds, we are to obſerve. 1. a Right common to any, ſo all or any may have a civil right to any kind of Creature. 2. A Right peculiar to ſome as being ſeparated from the common Condition, by ſome ſpecial Act of Gods Providence, of which ſort are Tythes given by him, to thoſe, who ſerve about holy things, in his publick Worſhip: which being laid down, it may appear that Miniſters of the Goſpel have as good right to the Tenth or Tythe, as the owner hath to the other nine parts; if at leaſt you will grant that God giveth as good right, by his divine donation, as any ſale or aſſignment of man can make.</p>
            <p>But you ſay—<hi>Yet am I not bound to pay them, &amp;c.]</hi> True, if neither Laws of God,<note place="margin">Pag. 26. Mark. 5.3.</note> nor man can bind you; but that like the Maſterleſs <hi>Gadaren,</hi> poſſeſſed of the Devil, you break Chains and Fetters, and no man can bind you; but if divine or humane Law can hold, you are bound to pay, and that by ſuch a Bond, as no Laws, Decrees, Statutes or Diſpenſations of Man, can diſcharge you from; but to ſpeak to them, whoſe Conſciences tell them, that the Law of God is, and ought to be their rule. How poſterity ſtands bound in publick Grants, Donations, Vows or Covenants, conſider in the example of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> before mentioned; how in private legacies and bequeathments, the Apoſtle will inform you <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Though it be but a mans Teſtament, yet if it be confirmed, no man diſanulleth it.</hi> That is, no man ought to make it void by any violation thereof; but this belongeth to another queſtion; our claim being grounded not on the aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or grant of man, but on the revealed. Will of God, who
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:179525:34"/>
commanded <hi>To give Tythes of all the encreaſe of their Land, &amp;c.</hi> Numb. 18.21, 26, 30. <hi>And to make their Teachers partakers of all their good things,</hi> Gal. 6.6. Doth this bind men (think you) to pay the ſetled maintenance of Miniſters Tythes Predial, Perſonal, and Mixt? Or are you reſolved, to ſuſpend your obedience to God herein, until you be delivered into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding <hi>Chains of darkneſs to be reſerved unto judgment?</hi> Be well adviſed in time, for there will be no change in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>And doth your next Suppoſition conclude it arbitrary,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.</note> to work or live inordinately? Or were there not the like propoſitions, between Tythes and yearly values of the Lands, on which they grew under the Law, to any that can be pretended to? What ſober man amongſt you, ever grumbled at the <hi>nimietie</hi> of wealth? Who quarrelleth at the largeneſs of a Lords Eſtate, who is a Peer of the Land, or a Gentlemans, or Yeomans, as too much for him and his Family, except ſome lawleſs, impious Leveller? Though perhaps one of theſe Eſtates be fourty times more than the Miniſters incom; and poſſibly the Laicks revenue is ſpent in Luxury, Debauchery, or Idleneſs at leaſt, while the poor Miniſter is envied, and grudged his portion of Gods bleſſing, the Earths encreaſe, which he gives you with him, (that I may not ſay, for him) the Miniſter I ſay, ſpending many carefull hours Night and Day for your Souls Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Comfort and Salvation—<hi>Sudat &amp; alget</hi>—like <hi>Jacob</hi> over <hi>Labans</hi> Flock at <hi>Padan-Aram,</hi> in the day <hi>conſumed with drought, and by the froſt in the night, and his ſleep departeth from his eyes,</hi> Gen. 31.40.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>A tenth part of the encreaſe is generally more worth, than the Land on which it grows]</hi> What have you dwelt at <hi>Gerar,</hi> where <hi>Iſaac</hi> reaped an hundred-fold in a Year? Or is it becauſe you have little skill in the Georgicks? I am confident, that this one untruth would yield you a Million by the year, if you could make it true; but were it as you ſay, did ever much encreaſe of fruits make an exception in Gods grant of them, as that the Tythes ſhould be holy to him and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and paid to the Prieſts of the Sanctuary, or Miniſters of the Goſpel; provided that they did not exceed ſuch, or ſuch
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:179525:35"/>
a value? Methinks in reaſon, the more bountifully God giveth encreaſe of the Earth, the more willing men ſhould be to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him that part thereof, which he hath reſerved (as it were a Lords-rent) unto himſelf, and his own ſervice; and here excuſe me, that I tell you your objections ſeem not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the declamation of ſome ill-contrived Orator, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinctly hudled out, that neither doth the Speaker well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, nor the hearer eaſily underſtand what he ſaith, more then that, <hi>quod vult, valdè vult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your following Cavils and Caſes, Paſturing and Stocking Land,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.14.</note> may ſhew, that you have craft enough to beguile the Miniſter of due maintenance; but <hi>curſed be the deceiver:</hi> and it were but loſt labour, to teach others this skill, ſeeing that too many without your Magiſtery have enough of the knave already.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 28.</note>Next you talk, <hi>Of new payment of Tythes, &amp;c.]</hi> To which we anſwer, That payment of Tythes, is evidently as old as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> and for ought you know, as <hi>Adam.</hi> To the reſt of your Objections preſent, we ſay, <hi>Abuſus non tollit uſum;</hi> that which hath been abuſed by ſome, may yet be returned to the true ſervice of God again. So the cenſers of the rebellious <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> made covers for the Altar of God; and truly the annexed reaſon is remarkable—<hi>For they were offered before the Lord, therefore they are hallowed, Numb.</hi> 16.38. And is not the ſame reaſon good for reducing Tythes (abuſed to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious uſes in former times) unto the preſent true worſhip of God, ſeeing they were hallowed, not by the dedication of a rebellious <hi>Corah,</hi> but by God himſelf; and that to his own holy ſervice? And what els means our Saviour by the Parable of the ſtrong mans Fort,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.22.</note> and reprizal of all his impropriated Veſſels, but Chriſts overcoming Satan, and recovering the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſouls of his Elect, from his Power and Captivity? Body and Soul muſt periſh eternally, if that alteration which is wrought in the ſinner, by the Spirit of Sanctification, make him not acceptable and beloved of God, as a ſon, who was before his reconciliation by Chriſt, an enemy. How elſe ſaith the Apoſtle (ſpeaking of many ſorts of pollution by ſin,—<hi>Such were ſome of you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:179525:35"/>
ye are juſtified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God:</hi> Upon the accompt of reducing that to a good uſe, acceptable to God, which hath been abuſed unto evil, we retain our Churches, and Oratories, and worſhip <hi>God in Spirit and in Truth</hi> therein, though they have been in times of Popery, houſes of Idols, and Idolatry.</p>
            <p>To your many following impertinencies, if I ſhould follow you in your <hi>Wilde-Gooſe-Chaſe,</hi> I ſhould tire the patient Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; therefore I onely adde, That there is much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween tythes of Mines, Quarries of Iron, Braſs, Tin, Lead, Coles, and that which the Earths ſuperficies brings forth, as Corn, Graſs, Fruits, Wood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though by your leave, all theſe are increaſes of the Earth; and therefore tythable. Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> by you cited, limits his ſentence, with a <hi>Till they be ſevered from the Land:</hi> So that though no tythe be paid of the Land, yet are they to be paid from the Land.</p>
            <p>Your frequent talking of Popery, is but to make your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautious Reader believe, that you are no Papiſt; and that you may inſinuate into the peoples mindes an <hi>odium</hi> againſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whereas indeed in ſuch ſeeming-oppoſition, you do your uttermoſt endeavor to bring in Popery.</p>
            <p>You further ſay, <hi>When I bought my Land, I bought not the tythes, &amp;c.]</hi> This you ſay, ſome object; to which you frame your anſwer: But we require our liberty to anſwer for our ſelves. Neither could you, nor any man buy out Gods part; for that no man had power to ſell you: So that in your convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, there needed no ſpecification of <hi>Covenant</hi> for, or exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from a tenth part of the increaſe of the Land, that being preſuppoſed payable by Gods reſervation thereof unto his own ſervice. What ever man buyeth or ſelleth, in point of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutative juſtice, Gods part cometh not within the compaſs thereof; neither can it be ſold or alienated; neither can any ſale or purchaſe of man leſſen or impeach his right, or any part thereof, which he never granted to any but thoſe whom he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth to ſerve about holy things.</p>
            <p>Next, you bravely ſay, <hi>I anſwer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 29.</note> 
               <hi>that I have already proved all Land is tythe-free, &amp;c.]</hi> Indeed I think he meant it—<hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis tamen excidit auſis:</hi> Tell me now in ſadneſs, who can free
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:179525:36"/>
the earth from the charge of tythes, but that ſupream power of God, who gave them for an inheritance, unto thoſe whom he deſigned to his publick ſervice? Here we require your expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this term, <hi>Tythe-free;</hi> mean you this in reſpect of any Humane Law, Ordinance, Proviſion, or Preſcription of Men thereto pretended? If ſo, it is to no purpoſe, ſeeing, as hath been ſaid, None but God hath power of giving or alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating tythes. Now, once again, we challenge you to ſhew us, where God in holy Scripture, ever repealed his Law of tyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Further we ſay, that all the habitable parts of the Chriſtian world, which yield increaſe, are tythable, and none exempted there-from, by Gods Law; in which, if you beat our ears, with a thouſand beggings of the queſtion, you ſhall never obtain it of us.</p>
            <p>That you ſay, <hi>Tythes are a burden which the Pope laid on us,]</hi> Is a fallacious aſſertion; the Heathen could here teach you, that <hi>quod in divinis rebus ſumes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plaut. Mil. glor.</note> 
               <hi>ſapienti lucro eſt:</hi> But God laid this duty on us, which you call a <hi>burden;</hi> and this grant of his, no Ordinance or Law of Man (though enjoyning the ſame duty) can more drown, than a Leaſe can a Fee-ſimple. Mans Laws are alterable, but the morality of Gods Law is not.</p>
            <p>Next you talk of <hi>Theeves and Robbers]</hi> Whom you mean, I onely gueſs at, and ſay, <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos de ſeditione que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes? Clodius accuſat maechos</hi>—What? great Theeves, make hue and cry after true men? you <hi>Church-Robbers,</hi> ſtealers of tythes (of whom you are at beſt, an a better) are the Theeves and Robbers,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> in Gods judgment, if there be any ſuch on theſe borders.</p>
            <p>You ſay next, <hi>That you may by as good reaſon, be eaſed of your tythes, as of the Popes yoke.]</hi> Which is in effect to ſay, that you may as juſtly caſt off Gods Law, as the Popes; is this Popery, ho? The reaſon offered as to the queſtion, if formed, would appear to be a <hi>fallacia non cauſae pro cauſa.</hi> Your <hi>Land,</hi> you ſay, <hi>was purchaſed when the Popes authority lay heavy on this Land.</hi> That being caſt off, you would infer, that we <hi>may with as good reaſon caſt off tythes</hi> which he commanded to be paid: Yea, but conſider a ſuperior command and cauſe, I mean, a Divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing that duty of paying tythes (although the Pope had not at all commanded ſuch payment) and your <hi>fallacy is diſſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:179525:36"/>You ſay, <hi>Firſt to preach that tythes are due,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 29.</note> 
               <hi>and then to limit them to Pariſhes, &amp;c.]</hi> And why not? Gods Word warranting the one, and mans juſt accommodation requiring the other? Once again I ſay, as concerning Pariſhes, there is a parochial or particular dueneſs of tythes, or that of Pariſhes, to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter there officiating in Gods publick ſervice: And there is a general dueneſs of tythes, that is to ſay, of tythes to be paid to the body of the Miniſtry; which is by Gods providence diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted into ſeveral parochial Cures, where they are by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes of the Earth, thence ariſing, to be maintained, that they may there preach the Goſpel, and adminiſter the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unto the people there inhabiting.</p>
            <p>You ſay again, <hi>That tythes were at firſt, as charity at most, as a freewil-offering of the owner.]</hi> This is an abſurd falſhood, and a ſhameleſs begging of the queſtion; and you ſeem to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute <hi>non ad idem;</hi> but circularly. Speak plainly; Do you mean, that <hi>Mans charity giving,</hi> and not <hi>Gods Law commanding,</hi> brought tythes to be the Miniſters maintenance? If ſo, it is apparantly falſe, by Gods ſeveral commands to pay them to the <hi>Levitical</hi> Prieſthood; wherein I ſuppoſe, you will not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that Mens charity was the firſt, or principal moving cauſe; or do you mean, that <hi>the freewil of man,</hi> in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of tythes, preceded that command of God, as a cauſe the effect? or that <hi>poſito Dei mandato,</hi> man did yield a free and chearful obedience, in paying tythes, as God had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Which voluntary act, was as <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſuch as that wo had been to him, if he had not done it? Expreſs your terms and ſenſe, and let us have no after-reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: We know that Gods Children yield a chearful and a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary obedience; they do their duty commanded, not moillingly, grudgingly, or of neceſſity; and,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9 7. 1 Pet. 5.2. 1 Cor 9.17.</note> that God loves and rewards chearful obedience, and ſuch are all acts of true Religion, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, not compulſory; the Spirit of God making us willing of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing; ſo carrying about our wills, and affections, as <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomers</hi> ſay, the <hi>primum mobile</hi> doth the inferior orbs of Heaven in their <hi>Diurnal motion</hi> from Eaſt to Weſt, contrary to their <hi>Natural motion,</hi> yet by an admirable influence, <hi>Citra violenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am:</hi> So we can admit tythes paid by Gods ſervants, to be a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:179525:37"/>
free-will offering, <hi>reſpectu offerentis,</hi> but not <hi>ex parte praecipientis;</hi> as if man inſtituted, and paid them without Gods Command for the ſame; and as if they were works of Supererogation. We know, that in every good which we do, God worketh both <hi>velle &amp; perficere:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> we acknowledg, that they are not rightly performed by any pure Naturals of man, but of Gods free Grace, both <hi>Jubentis quod vult, &amp; praeſtantis quod jubet.</hi> So <hi>Iſrael</hi> brought a <hi>willing Offering unto the Lord, every man and woman, whoſe heart made them willing, to bring for all manner of work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod, 35.29.</note> 
               <hi>which the Lord had commanded to be made by the hands of Moſes.</hi> But our Adverſaries would fain have it, that Tythes were but as ſome votive Obligation of the Owners, which they needed not to have dedicated or paid, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept themſelves pleaſed. This is the Witcheſs <hi>Herodias</hi> which they ſo ambitiouſly purſue, that they might once conclude an Arbitrary maintenance for Miniſters: and do but mark the Circle, to which this mole is Conjured. Fain would they have Gods Ordinance undermined, and diſſolved into ſuch <hi>Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Principles,</hi> as might bear this caſtle <hi>in the Air,</hi> that Tythes ſhould henceforth, be only what men in Charity and Free-will would give their Miniſters. Thank you for you kindneſs, gentle Sir. but get you Alms-men where you will, we are none of them. The Papiſt hath too much advantage already, in their large maintenance, open Preſſes for their Students Works, liberal Contributions for any advancement of his Cauſe; while our Preſſes are too much ſhut to good Studies, Contributions; rare is Honeſty, and if the Jeſuite could but yet more diſcourage us, by taking away the remainder of Miniſters neceſſary main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance by Tythes, his work were done, and <hi>England</hi> undone. To the reverend Miniſters, I entreat leave to ſay—<hi>If they be Prophets,</hi> and <hi>if the Word of the Lord be with them, let them now make Interceſſion to the Lord of Hoſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 27.18.</note> 
               <hi>that the Veſſels which are left in the houſe of the Lord—go not to</hi> Babylon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now limit them</hi> (that is Tythes) <hi>to Pariſhes, &amp;c.]</hi> That which you ſpeak,<note place="margin">Page 30.</note> may paſs muſter among your Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinences, as to the preſent queſtion; concerning Pariſhes, I have already ſpoken;<note place="margin">Gen. 14.18.</note> here I only add, 1. That the firſt place of Scripture mentioning a Prieſt, mentioneth Tythes paid
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:179525:37"/>
unto him. 2. The firſt place alſo wherein, Houſe of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2</note> or Church is ſpoken of, there alſo are Tythes, the maintenance of the Prieſt-hood vowed to God; as ſome note by that name, whereby Pariſh-Churches were anciently called; that is, <hi>tituli—lapis iſte quem poſui in titulum erit Domus Dei:</hi> So <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus</hi> in the life of <hi>Evariſtus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome. Anno</hi> 112. ſaith—<hi>hic titulos in Urbe Roma diviſit Presbyteris:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Platins. vit. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrius compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth Anno 96. Concil. To. 1. Pag. 106. e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. 1606.</note> And the <hi>Nicen</hi> Council, <hi>c.</hi> 21, mentionth Pariſhes, as <hi>Carraza</hi> reciteth the Canons thereof, out of the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Julius:</hi> So that by thoſe diviſions, the Congregations were aſſigned to ſuch and ſuch Churches, and the Tythes thence ariſing, belonged to the Miniſters there ſerving, as hath been noted, from <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. what the Popes you ſpeak of got of firſt-fruits, impropriate Tythes, &amp;c. is a loſs to our Clergy, and therefore not advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly urged by you againſt them.</p>
            <p>That which you further ſay, that—<hi>No man can preſcribe to have Tythes, &amp;c.]</hi> Were ſomthing againſt thoſe who make preſcription the ground of their claim, which concerns us not, who claim from divine donation.</p>
            <p>Again you ſay—<hi>many may preſcribe to be free from Tyithes, or part thereof]</hi> Conſider of what value preſcription can be againſt Gods unchangeable moral Law, and your ſecond thoughts will tell you, that antiquity of error can never make any good Preſcription. Chriſt yielded the Phariſaical gloſſes antiquity on their ſide, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.21. &amp;c. ye have heard of old time, that it was ſaid by <hi>(or to)</hi> them, &amp;c. which he preſently corrected with his— <hi>but I ſay unto you,</hi> &amp;c. The reſt of your following diſcourſe ſavoureth ſtrongly of your ſiding with the Popiſh party: as your ſtomaking the Title of the head of the Church, which we underſtand to be the ſupream Governor, under God, of inchurched men: neither is this, as you ſay here, <hi>The Kings new Authority, as the head of the Church.</hi> For what ſay we more therein, than <hi>Tertullian</hi> many hundred years ſince ſaid—<hi>We honor</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Emperor as we ought—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t hominem a Deo ſecundum— &amp; ſolo Deo mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem—Sic enim omnibus major eſt, dum ſolo vero Deo minor eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Scap. c. 2.</note> I conceive that you are not to learn that <hi>Caput</hi> importeth a Chief, Firſt, or Principal.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:179525:38"/>But you ſay, <hi>That all Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. were no longer to hold of the Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 30.</note> 
               <hi>but of the King; and not to claim their benefices by Title from the Pope, but of the King, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that Act of Parliament: and here the ſucceſſion from the Pope was cut off and diſcontinued, &amp;c.]</hi> A grief to all good hearts, think the Papiſts; But why ſhould this trouble you, if you be none of them? What is this to us, who acknowledg neither dependance on, nor Succeſſion from the Pope?</p>
            <p>You ſay more—<hi>And ſo all their Right, Title and Claim, was and is at an end]</hi> What becauſe the Popes donation is at an end, muſt Gods alſo be involved in the ſame ruin? How will that concluſion follow? The abuſe and uſurpation is taken away, <hi>ergo,</hi> the right uſe and juſt poſſeſſion muſt down? Are Gods Laws, grounded on the Popes Decrees and Grants? I never yet heard that claimed by any of you: And what wilde Logick ſtands your diſcourſe upon? Country-men, open your eyes, and let not theſe Wolves in Sheeps-clothing any longer beguile you; the Fox under a ſtupid Animal's skin, enough diſcovers his appetite to catch Geeſe, and to bring you and your Children into the miſerable darkneſs of Popery and the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thereof. Conſider before it be too late, how eaſily they will do it, if by taking away the Miniſters of Chriſt from you, depriving them of lively-hood, they bring into their places, Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits; if they get footing here again, their little finger will prove heavier than your Miniſters loyns were to you; Tythes would not long ſuffice them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">John 9.21.</note>Next yout talk of <hi>Impropriators Claim by purchaſe.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one of them we only ſay, as the Parents of the once blind man anſwered the <hi>Jews, he is of age, ask him, he ſhall ſpeak for himſelf.</hi> Here we thank you for your ingenuous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion—<hi>thoſe</hi> (you ſay) <hi>that ſold him</hi> (Impropriations) <hi>had no good Title, neither can theirs be made good, which is derived from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 31.</note>
               <hi>By which</hi> (you ſay) <hi>it doth plainly appear, that no man at this day, can claim Tythe of another, either by divine or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Right, &amp;c.]</hi> If you ſpeak of Impropriate Tythes, we have nothing here to do with them; If of Appropriate, we ſay, if begging the queſtion would ſerve your turn, we would
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:179525:38"/>
at once confeſs— <hi>actum eſt de decimis:</hi> but you are here come to the ſame point of your Circle, in evident begging the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ſaying—<hi>no man at this day can claim Tythes of another, either by Divine or Humane Right: prae clara verba, ſed verba;</hi> What? <hi>Caeſar's, Veni, Vidi, Vici?</hi> A ſingular faculty you ſeem to yourſelf to have; no ſooner do you think a thing, but it muſt <hi>plainly appear</hi> to be ſo; but that we ſufficiently know your quality of begging the queſtion, we might think that ſome <hi>miles glorioſus</hi> were entred into the <hi>Scene,</hi> telling how many thouſand flying Enemies he fetcht down with his limed Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts, and ſlew in one day. To the next we ſay, that we are not called to meddle with State-Intereſts; and concerning the <hi>Pope</hi> and his, we have here nothing to do; only we mark how the declining of the <hi>Pope's Supreamacy</hi> ſticks in your Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now</hi> (ſay you) <hi>to plead for ſuch wages of unrighteouſneſs]</hi> You dare call Gods <hi>Donation, wages of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they who care not what, (though blaſpemy) but how much they ſpeak. To that which you ſay, concerning Prieſts receiuing <hi>Augmentations;</hi> I ſay, I know no Prieſt ſo much favoured here, I know ſome reverend Miniſters who are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which</hi> (you ſay) <hi>they may as well take away</hi> (meaning Gleb-land) <hi>as their predeceſſors did the revenues of Abbeys and Monaſteries]</hi> Yet your ſelves confeſs,<note place="margin">Page 33.</note> that they were the <hi>Hives</hi> of lazy <hi>Drones.</hi> We wiſh that in their juſt diſſolution, they had been better imployed; but affirm that none can ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the taking away things conſecrated to Gods ſervice; but you conſtantly grumble at the decay of Popery; we wiſh that your vizard were pulled off, that ſpeaking bare-faced your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautious reader might diſcerne, on which ſide you are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſe Tythes</hi> (you ſay again) <hi>are often as much worth as the Land]</hi> I once heard one,<note place="margin">Page 34.</note> who being cenſured for repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a groſs untruth, replied, that he had told it ſo often, that his ſelf began to think that it was true. But I hope you here ſpeak Philoſopher-like—<hi>ex aliorum ſententia,</hi> not your own, but others opinion.</p>
            <p>—<hi>Forthwith throw away Tythes, &amp;c.]</hi> We thank you, as much as though we did, and ſhall think of your Motion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:179525:39"/>You ſay—<hi>So long as they continue, there can never be any poſſibility of raiſing maintenance in ſuch places]</hi> If you mean ſo long as impropriations continue, &amp;c. <hi>per nos, alia pax eſto;</hi> if otherwiſe, your argument hence derived, as to the taking away Tythes, is very feeble, being a <hi>fallacia non cauſae, pro cauſâ.</hi> For what hinderance can paying and receiving of ſythes be to thoſe places, where none are payable as <hi>praedial,</hi> as in Towns and Cities, wherein are no fields? But conſider you that fear God, what <hi>Azariah</hi> acknowledged. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.10. <hi>Since the people began to bring the Offerings</hi> (with their Tythes, as appears there, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6.) <hi>We have had enough, for the Lord hath bleſsed his people:</hi> which was according to that which God ſpeaks, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Bring ye all the Tythes into the Store-houſe—and prove me now herewith, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a bleſſing,</hi> that there ſhall not be room enough to receive it.</p>
            <p>Next you ask concerning Towns and Cities, or Lands Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate, where there is no competency of maintenance by Tythes—<hi>Muſt they never have an able Miniſter? Have they no ſhare in our Goſpel, becauſe they have no maintenance?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the cauſe why ſuch as you ſpecifie have no greater ſhare of our Miniſters pains, is not ſo much becauſe they have no maintenance, as becauſe they will have none; while <hi>Gadaren</hi>-like they value their ſwine, or temporal intereſts, more than the Goſpel. And now think you that they do not put the <hi>Word of God from them, and judg themſelves unworthy of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life;</hi> not only who contradict the Word when it is preached, but they alſo who take a courſe, that it may never be preached unto them? I ſpeak of them, who dwelling in populous Towns and Cities, will not agree together to levy ſome ſuch means for the ſupport of an able Miniſter, as may keep him alive, and enable him to the ſervice of God. But to paſs by this fault of Towns-men and Citizens, &amp;c. we can juſtifie by thouſands of witneſſes, that the Goſpel hath been powerfully and diligently preached in ſundry Towns, by able Miniſters, where no maintenance was either raiſed by any Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriator, or otherwiſe could be by any appropriated Tythes,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:179525:39"/>
there growing, I will add without any reward of their pains, either retributed by the auditors, or expected by thoſe preachers.</p>
            <p>You demand again — <hi>Have you not a more righteous Rule?]</hi> What than that, which Gods Word preſcribed? This and your following <hi>farrago libelli,</hi> may be ſatisfied with this anſwer, that it is a dangerous thing to account a mans ſelf more wiſe than God, and a fooliſh preſumption to endeavour any amendment of his Ordinances; needs muſt he find his human wiſdom fooliſhneſs, who oppoſeth it to divine. Your objection from the inequality of paying, is vain; for who can be ignorant that there were inequalities of Eſtates under the Law, or that every man was bound to pay according to that which he had, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which he had not? Your following cavils are more ſuitable to the gallfull pen of ſome apoſtate <hi>Julian,</hi> or jeering <hi>Lucian</hi> than the writing of any profeſſed Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>To that which you ſay, of <hi>Throwing away Tythes as an old relique of Popery]</hi> We anſwer, that when you have proved them to be ſuch, you may have ſome ground for ſuch a motion; till then we require your patience, if we hold faſt Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and the Miniſters juſt maintenance.</p>
            <p>Further you ſay, <hi>Halt no longer between two, &amp;c.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aeſchylus Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonem ebrium (n ſcena quâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam) induxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quo vitio labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ipſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eta tragicus, co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentitus He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roas. Athenae. l. 10. c. 7.</note> We muſt tell you Sir, here you entitle us to your own faults, as that drunken Poet <hi>Aeſchylus</hi> did the noble <hi>hero Jaſon,</hi> and other Grecians to his own vices; 'tis you who halt between Papiſt and a Schiſmatical pretender to Reformation. So <hi>Ahab</hi> would have put the crime of troubling <hi>Iſrael,</hi> on the Prophet of the Lord: as for us, God knows that our ſouls deſire is to cleave ſtedfaſtly unto him and his ſacred Ordinances; and we have not yet temporized (as too many have done) God preſerving us in our ſuffering of hard things; Is this halting with Sir <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nonſenſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next you talk of <hi>A more Goſpel-like way of maintenance,</hi> &amp;c.] To which 'tis eaſily anſwered, that not only you, but no Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Men or Angels of Heaven, can preſcribe a more Goſpel-like way, than that which God hath appointed, and Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
            <p>The light which you talk of, we own not for ſuch, who have a <hi>more ſure word of Propheſie, unto which as unto light, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:179525:40"/>
ſhineth in a dark place,</hi> we attend <hi>until the day dawn</hi>—As for thoſe <hi>ignes fatui</hi> of Mens inventions, we neither value them, nor find any cauſe to follow them.</p>
            <p>Next you ſpeak of a <hi>way to eſtabliſh the Nation upon a ſure foundation of true freedom, as to the conſcience]</hi> We ſay, 1. Uſe not your Liberty for a cloke of malitiouſneſs. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that you be not of their number, of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.16. 2 Pet. 2.18.19.</note> who when they <hi>ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity—while they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of corruption.</hi> 3. If you diſſemble not, but bear good will to your Countries freedom, and good conſcience; we cannot but pitty the ſeeming diſproportion between your zeal and knowledg, as we would pitty to ſee mettle in a blind jade.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 15.19.</note>As for giving content to ſeparate Congragations, our rule is the ſame which, God of old gave the Prophet — <hi>Let them return unto thee, but return not thou unto them.</hi> And as for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying ſuch as are ſelf-excommunicate, and divided from the womb of the Church, we pitty them, but muſt leave them to Gods tribunal: for our ſelves we have learned of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10. <hi>If I yet pleaſe men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt.</hi> That on which you ſpend your Rhetorick about con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention for Tythes, as if that were a ſufficient cauſe why they ſhould be taken away, is very childiſh. Tell me, have there not been, and ſtill are many bloody contentions about the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel of Chriſt? What, would it be a ſure foundation of true freedom, as to the conſcience, to obey the command of thoſe Rulers, Elders and Scribes, <hi>Annas, Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Not to ſpeak at all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>nor teach in the name of Jeſus?</hi> Is it your beſt preſcript for the cure of the head-ache, to cut off the head? <hi>medice cura teipſum.</hi> But ſeriouſly, your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a <hi>fallacia accidentis,</hi> a wholſom way were for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple duly to pay and ſet out their Tythes according to Laws divine and humane. I conceive that no man would be ſo ill-adviſed, as to ſue for his right, if he might have it without trouble and charge of Law.</p>
            <p>That you ſay, <hi>Paying unreaſonable, &amp;c.]</hi> You ſpeak like your ſelf. But doth paying Tythes <hi>hinder Tillage, and the ſtaff
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:179525:40"/>
of bread</hi> as you pretend? Here is again another <hi>fallacia ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentis,</hi> if that be true which you ſay; or a <hi>fallacia non cauſae, pro cauſa,</hi> if falſe. It is not paying of Tythes, which is the obſtruction to plenty, but mens unbelief; God himſelf ſaying, <hi>Prove me now if I will not—pour you out a bleſſing, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note> Of what kind? Of the encreaſes of the Earth? And what is the condition to which that promiſe relateth? Is it not paying Tythes, and leaving their Sacriledg?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let no man</hi> (ſay you) <hi>henceforth think it ſtrange, &amp;c.]</hi> We ſhall not think it ſtrange, that ſome men refuſe to pay Tythes, while there is a Devil to tempt them to Sacriledg; nor wonder that ſome will pay Tythes, becauſe we have a good God, who though he juſtly permit many to ſtrong deluſions, that they may periſh, yet will he preſerve his elect, and encline their hearts to obey his Laws and Ordinances, that it may be well with them, and theirs.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>HAving thus anſwered theſe cavils, I propoſe the enſuing concluſions to the good readers conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All are bound to do the moſt high Lord God homage and ſervice, of whom it is written, <hi>Him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> This is a rule ſo evidently juſt, that the very heathens in their twelve Tables of their Law acknowledged it, on this ground,<note place="margin">Az or. l. 6. c. 63. Cic. de leg. l. 2. 12ae. q. 44. 6. Lex natura is non poteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leri, quoad pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma principia.</note> that God is the Lord, and diſpoſer of all things. For as School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſay, the Law of Nature cannot be extinguiſhed, as to its firſt Principles. Now there is no Nation of the World ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and barbarous, but that it believes there is a God, who created, and ſtill governeth this Univerſe: So that the brutiſh <hi>Poticius</hi> for his ignorance of God, was eſteemed a kind of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox</hi> in <hi>Nature,</hi> a <hi>Prodigy</hi> and <hi>Monſter of Man-kind.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cic. Plaut.</note> God's Word teacheth us, that he muſt be worſhiped, but, as his ſelf commandeth in it, which is his revealed will; as 'tis written,<note place="margin">Mic. 6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath ſhewed thee O man what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:179525:41"/>2. We muſt be faithfull and true to him, whom we adore as our God, the ſearcher of hearts: not encroaching upon any part of that, which the holy Word declareth (as a reſerved right) to belong unto the Lord our God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What ever carnal reaſon, or wiſdom of the fleſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, or ſuggeſt to the contrary; we muſt duly and willingly render and pay unto him all his Rights, and Duties belonging unto him as a ſupream Lord of all: As it is written, <hi>Give unto God the things that are Gods;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat, 12.21. 1 Chro. 29 14. Pſal. 115.16.</note> which when we have truly done, we muſt acknowledg with <hi>David, Of thy own hand have we given thee;</hi> all is thine: <hi>The earth hath he given unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men;</hi> only reſerving to himſelf, as it were a ſmal <hi>Lords-rent,</hi> as an acknowledgment of his Soverain Dominion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The things which God hath reſerved, as a Tribute or Rent to himſelf, are, 1. Either of the time meaſured unto man for this preſent life; out of which he hath reſerved a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth part, or a Sabbath and holy reſt, that we may be enabled to ſubſiſt and ſerve him; without which we cannot be happy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or of the bleſſing and encreaſes of the Earth; out of which, God in his bounty, feeds, clothes, every way neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary accommodates us in our humane neceſſities; only reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto his own ſervice, little more than a tenth part, and that for man's good alſo; that by ſuch means a Miniſtry, able to edifie, comfort and enform him, concerning the Will of God for his ſalvation, may be maintained; to which Miniſtry, he hath appointed that his reſerved part, the tenths; to thoſe I ſay, whom he calleth to labour in his ſervice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A part of the Earth, or land which he hath given man to Till, Sow, Plant, and yield Encreaſe: as he reſerved a part of our time of life, for our ſerving him, ſo hath he alſo a part and portion of our place, or the earth on which he will be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; (for without time when, and place where, there can be no humane Action) That is, Church, and Churches, Houſes ſet a part from all common uſe, to his ſervice and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip accommodate. So was there a Temple and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Churches among Chriſtians, even from the Primitive age, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. Alſo, to the Levites there were Cities appointed, out of every Tribe; <hi>Num.</hi> 25.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:179525:41"/>
23. &amp;c. even 48 walled Cities with their Suburbs; their other revenue being generally provided for them, by Tythes, Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c. out of the whole Land beſide. Now, our Savior releaſed none of theſe Rights, as to the morality thereof; that is, the equity of his ſervants maintenance, and neceſſary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, in his worſhip: Therefore he avowed the Temple to be his Fathers Houſe; and the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">John. 2.16. Mal. 1.11. R v. 8. Mat. 21.13.</note> 
                  <hi>From the riſing of the Sun, even to the going down of the ſame — in every place, incenſe</hi> (that is Prayers of the <hi>Saints) ſhall be offered unto my name, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> So <hi>Chriſt</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelf to be Lord of the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> and ſo alſo, is he Lord of that portion of the Earhts encreaſes, reſerved to the publick Worſhip of God: and in caſe of detention thereof,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> he ſaith expreſly—<hi>Ye have robbed me—in Tythes and Offerings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Law had three branches: The Moral, Ceremonial, and Judicial. The firſt whereof, was and is the rule by which all perſons, at all times, and in all places, are to compoſe their lives, as to God, which is the ſubſtance of the firſt Table. The ſecond Table preſcribeth the mutual duty of man to man. The Ceremonial Law, preſcribed ſeveral religious Rights, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which, God would have his <hi>Iſrael</hi> to worſhip him, until the fullneſs of time wherein Chriſt was to come in the fleſh, and fullfill all thoſe things for mans redemption, which thoſe rights prefigured, and under which God's people were to be exerciſed and trained up all the time of their minority, as a Child under a Schoolmaſter, in expectation of a Savior and Redeemer to come. The judicial Law appertained to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the well government of them, by adminiſtration of civil Laws, for the peace, welfare and tranquillity of that people: therefore theſe are often joyned together in holy Scripture, Precepts, Ceremonies and Judgments. The firſt whereof, appertaineth to the right forming of holy manners. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to Rights and ſacred Ceremonies, determining the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Gods worſhip for that time. The third, to the civil government of the people. And theſe three are as it were the nerves of every well governed State; holy Manners, religious Worſhip, and due execution of Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:179525:42"/>6. Divine poſitive Laws or Inſtitutions, bound, as did moral Preceps, though with ſome conſiderable differences. Some poſitive Laws were binding only to ſome particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; as that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Of the tree of knowledg of good and evil, thou ſhalt not eat of it:</hi> this bound (as to the precept) only <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> who were but one fleſh. Some poſitive Law,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.24.</note> as they were temporal, having their beginning and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in time, thoug they were binding to a multitude, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet were they not ſo to all men, as Circumciſion, raiſing up ſeed to the diſeaſed brother, &amp;c. which bound <hi>Iſrael</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, until Chriſt came in the fleſh, that the trueth of the promiſe concerning his being of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and family of <hi>David</hi> might appear in that diſtinction of Tribes. So the many Sanctions appertinent to Prieſts and Levites,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note> the Service and Rights which having a ſhadow of good things then to come, were to ceaſe when the truth was come, and had accompliſhed all thoſe things, which were thereby prefigured. So the judicial Precepts were poſitive for the time, while <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels</hi> republick continued, and ſo were binding, and ſtill are as they have their ground in moral equity. To theſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible thoſe precepts prohibiting Mariages in certain degrees of conſanguinity, which poſitive Law maketh inceſtuous, then commencing when mankind was encreaſed unto multitudes and ſocieties of men, which could not bind in the family of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſuppoſing God's Ordinance for the progagation of all mankind by one man and one woman.</p>
               <p>For the Ceremonial Laws, they bound not before their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ſignified to <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the divine Lawgiver; neither do they, becauſe they are not poſitive unto this time. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that opinion is erroneous and dangerous, which ſaith—<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae lex &amp; ratio depoſcit &amp; precipit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Azor. inſtit. l. 6. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>ut Deo Sacrificia offeramus, quibus peccata noſtra expiemus.</hi> For ſacrificing was no Law of Nature, but a Poſi ive Law; the Law of Nature was as the Original to the Moral, which was a tranſcript or duplicate thereof; and there was a poſitive precept for <hi>Abels</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing, without which it could not have been acceptable to God, as done in faith; but now in propriety of terms, offering Sacrifice for expiation, is no more juſtifiable, than Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:179525:42"/>
Chriſt hath by his own oblation of himſelf once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.10, 14, 18. vid. ib. c. 9. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>perfected for ever them that are ſanctifyed—now where remiſſion of theſe</hi> (that is ſins) <hi>is, there is no more offering for ſin.</hi> Theſe Laws are now not only <hi>mortuae,</hi> but <hi>mortiferae;</hi> not only dead, but a killing Letter. Whereas the moral Law (in all negative precepts thereof) binds <hi>Semper &amp; ad ſemper.</hi> And the Affirmative (as may be ſeen in the fourth and fift pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept) bind <hi>ſemper,</hi> though not <hi>ad ſemper.</hi> So we are all our life time bound to ſanctifie the Sabbath, but we are not bound at all times of our life ſo to do, becauſe it is not always the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath or Seventh day, and we are not bound to any impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in Nature.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Ceremonial and Judicial Laws, as poſitive, had ſome mixtures with morality; and the moral had ſomthing Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial or Poſitive for a time;<note place="margin">Erat partim morale &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale. 12ae. q. 100. 3. 2m. Alens. parc. 4.2.</note> which was the reaſon why the fourth precept was alterable, from the ſeventh day reckoned from the Creation, to the Seventh day from Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The moral precepts, as ſimply, ſuch, are unalterable, and indiſpenſable, as to all times, places and perſons. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did God ever diſpenſe with the morality of his own Laws:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> Neither did Chriſt, in any one jot or tittle diſſolve them; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſeems contrary, is but expoſitory in the reſult; as Chriſt doing moſt of his great works on the Sabbath, was no diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the fourth precept, but only an interpretation thereof; ſhewing that works of neceſſity and mercy,<note place="margin">Luk. 13.15. &amp; 14.5.</note> are works of the Sabbath. So God commanding <hi>Iſrael</hi> to borrow of the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> and take away the things ſo borrowed;<note place="margin">Exod. 11.2. Gen. 18.</note> by that Act of his juſtice doing <hi>Iſrael</hi> right (he being the great Judg of all the World) in giving them their juſt wages, for their unjuſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude (which wages the <hi>Egyptians</hi> detained from them) doth but interpret the eigth Commandment—<hi>Thou ſhal not ſteal;</hi> That is, not by any means take away another mans goods <hi>invito domino</hi> i. e. <hi>bonae fidei poſſeſſore.</hi> Now firſt we muſt conſider, That due wages belonging to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in point of morality, which ſaith the labourer <hi>is worthy of his hire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 10.7.</note> was in the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> hands, who therefore were thereof but <hi>malae fidei poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſores,</hi> from whom, as from a thief or uſurper it was legally to be recovered; that might not be done without warrant from a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:179525:43"/>
competent Judg; therefore God's warrant empowred them ſo to do;<note place="margin">2 Chron. 19.6.</note> as the ſentence of thoſe who now judg for God, may warrant a labourer, or ſervant to recover his due hire, or wages unjuſtly detained from him. Secondly it is conſiderable, That we may not take from him, who though of ſome other Nation, is yet united, in the ſame bonds of community and amity with the republick,<note place="margin">Exod. 13.18. Numb. 14.3, 11. &amp;c. Deut. 17.16. Gen. 44.14.</note> of which we are a part (which the <hi>Egyptians</hi> from that time were no longer to be) except in caſe of legal proceeding, or lawfull hoſtility; wherein as thou maiſt take away the life of an enemy, ſo maiſt thou his goods; but in an unjuſt War, the murder, or latrociny is double injury.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In man's fall, ſome moral Laws were to his underſtanding more unextinct than others: So were the precepts of the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which concerned our duty to, and worſhip of God, more obliterated than the precepts of the ſecond Table, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the maintenance of humane ſociety; as, <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother: Thou ſhalt not kill, Commit adultery, ſteal,</hi> &amp;c. The very Heathens knew, that ſuch things were unjuſt, impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and deſtructive to humane ſociety; therefore they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited them in their 12 tables, or abridgment of their Laws; and accordingly, ſeverely puniſhed the offenders. Towards the divine precepts of the firſt table, which enjoyned the due wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of one true God, their unerſtandings were more darkened, though even thereof they had ſome very ſlender remains by natural principles not utterly extinct, as may appear in their worſhipping of thoſe whom they took to be Gods.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Scripture affirms not only that which is therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>totidem verbis,</hi> but that alſo, which by neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence followeth the true ſenſe thereof; as appears in that which Chriſt ſaid to the Saduces,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye erre, not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> Wherein?<note place="margin">Exod. 3.6.</note> In that which God ſaid unto <hi>Moſes, I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob.</hi> Why, here's not a word or ſyllable concerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead, concerning which Chriſt there ſpake; true, if we conſider expreſs words; but from neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence it followeth, <hi>If God be the God of the living, and not of the dead;</hi> then <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob,</hi> are not ſo dead, but that they ſtill live with God in their Spirits, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:179525:43"/>
therefore their bodies ſhall riſe again to be with God, the God of the living, which they not underſtanding, knew not the Scriptures and Power of God to raiſe the dead, in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declared. This may alſo appear in that which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church believeth concerning the ſacred Trinity, which is no where named in holy Scripture <hi>totidem Syllabis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 5.</note> but by certain conſequence from thence proved. The ſame alſo we muſt underſtand concerning Baptiſing Infants, and the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Chriſtian Sabbath, and ſo of paying Tythes to Goſpel Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. God's precepts be they never ſo ancient, having no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal appearing in holy Scripture, are ever binding, unto the end of the World, and no man can with any ſecurity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience attempt to free himſelf from the bond of any duty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Gods moral law at all, or from his poſitive precepts, without clear evidence of the lawgivers will for the ceſſation thereof.</p>
               <p n="11">11. No moral Law of God is temporary, as concerning the future; but as it bindeth every man without exception, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, ſo doth it ever bind. Such is the Law of tything, which is enjoyned in the firſt, fourth, fifth, and eighth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the moral Law; as will appear in its place.</p>
               <p n="12">12. No man, councels, or authority of men, may diſpenſe with any one precept of Gods Law: Chriſt diſavoweth any diſſolution of it by himſelf, in the leaſt jot, as to the morality thereof. Therefore it is a ſin, and ſuch as ſhall exclude a man from the Kingdom of Heaven, to attempt it, though with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of many, or moſt ſuffrages of men, under any pretence whatſoever. So when God ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image,</hi> What will it avail the Idolater to plead before his Tribunal, that a great part of the people ſay, that <hi>Idols are Laymens books?</hi> Shall their diſtinction of <hi>dulia</hi> and <hi>latria</hi> excuſe them? What that ſome think the Sabbath pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and therefore that it ought to vaniſh away with the ceremonial Law? What that ſome think that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty freeth them from Obedience, to their civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates; and that it was proper to the Jewiſh policy only; that ſome impious <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> thought fornication no ſin; or
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:179525:44"/>
that <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> freeth them from Gods Law, forbidding all uncleanneſs and filthy luſt? If all Nations and people ſhould, or poſſibly could diſpenſe with theſe, or any one precept of <hi>Gods Moral Law,</hi> ſuch conſent could not amount to more or leſs, than a general <hi>apoſtaſie</hi> from God, and his ſacred Law. What if people and Nations ſhould cry down tythes; as when the <hi>Hunnes, Goths,</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> invading the Weſtern parts of the Chriſtian World, Tythes and Churches were pulled down, Univerſities, Colledges, and Schools of good learning were overthrown, as our adverſaries would fain have it now: Could all this do any more, than make their outrages more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous, hateful to God and Man, and more odious to all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, to whom their deteſtable and unhappy memory ſhould come; and for preſent, themſelves inſtrumental to pull down Gods curſes and plagues upon themſelves and their Countrey, unappy in the birth and breeding up of ſuch prodigious miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants?</p>
               <p n="13">13. No combination or conſent of multitudes, may change or alter Gods ſacred Ordinances, under any pretence of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, or of more convenience or bettering them by any means. The vain and impious dream of ſome <hi>competency</hi> for Miniſters maintenance, inſtead of tythes, is meer rebellion againſt God and his Laws, no better than an high and mad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to correct his wiſdom, rectifie his providence, and attempting to controul and amend his Decreed and Sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, oblikely cenſuring them as defective or erroneous; which is an acme and heighth of more than <hi>Luciferian</hi> reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, he ſaid, <hi>Similis ero altiſſimo. I will be like the moſt high;</hi> but,<note place="margin">Iſa. 14.14.</note> upon the matter, theſe would be <hi>ſupra altiſſimum,</hi> above the moſt high, to controll and alter his Decrees. Had the <hi>Jews</hi> attempted to have changed the maintenance of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> in the whole or any part thereof, by God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and declared; though they had given them more than the value of their tythes and offerings, in money or ſome other kinde of commodity: Would God have connived any more at ſuch ſacriledge, than at the rebellion of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates? they would have changed Gods Ordinance in the authority of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons Miniſtery: And
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:179525:44"/>
can we reaſonably conceive, that for ſuch as now attempt to take away the Miniſters, and Gods publick worſhip, branch and root; the Earth hath not yet more back-doors to open for ſuch Conſpirators, that they may go down, body and ſoul, alive to Hell? Be adviſed, it is the ſame God ſtill, and therefore it is a dangerous undertaking to meddle with that,<note place="margin">Heb. 13 8.</note> which he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, reſerved for his own part, and aſſigned as an <hi>honorary</hi> for their ſervice; whom he calleth and deſigneth thereto, not whom the aſſembly of <hi>Corah</hi> would ſubſtitute and ordain to ſerve in the Sanctuary. And now if you will reſt on the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> ſentence, <hi>Goſpel Miniſters,</hi> in the change of the Law, ſucceeding the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> muſt likewiſe be maintained; not by an arbitrary allowance, by the will of man, but by that which God appointed for them. So the Apoſtle applieth the ſame <hi>moral equity</hi> for the Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> The <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> portion was tythes and offerings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> even ſo hath God appointed or ordained, <hi>That they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. To what relateth that <hi>(even ſo,)</hi> but unto that which he before ſpake of? even as <hi>Legal Prieſts</hi> lived, or were maintained by tythes and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; ſo muſt Miniſters of the Goſpel be maintained by tythes and offerings.</p>
               <p>I demand of our <hi>Competency-men,</hi> how, <hi>even ſo,</hi> if tythes be taken away, and Miniſters left to the peoples benevolence? <hi>even ſo,</hi> muſt ſignifie <hi>nothing ſo:</hi> but <hi>even ſo,</hi> by your wills, they who preach the Goſpel, ſhall have nothing except a meals meat, when they will flatter you.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Without all controverſie, there was a certain determinate allowance for <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> under the Law; and what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can be ſhewed, why we ſhould conceive, that God hath not appointed as competent and comfortable means for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſubſiſtence? What <hi>Scripture</hi> can be produced to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or ſolid reaſon urged to make it ſo much as probable; that God who ſo diſpoſed of <hi>Legal Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites,</hi> that they were, as I may ſay, fed out of Gods own hand and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved part, ſhould remit the Miniſters of a <hi>better teſtament,</hi> and a <hi>better hope,</hi> to the unkinde hands of unconſtant men to be maintained in a <hi>dubious and uncertain condition</hi> of ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence?
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:179525:45"/>
Would he have them under the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> depend on his own holy Providence; and Miniſters of his dear Son <hi>Jeſus,</hi> on men? For you muſt obſerve, that though the <hi>quota pars</hi> for Prieſts and Levites, was determinate in Tythes and Offerings, yet in the whole, or dividends thereof, it muſt needs ariſe more or leſs, as God bleſſed their Land with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes, much or little.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.2.</note> Add heerto, if God would not truſt the Magiſtrates of his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no nor <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo faithfull a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in his houſe, ſo dear, ſo familiar as he was with God, to leave the determination of the Prieſts and Levites portion unto him, but limited him in every particular thereof; How much leſs would he leave the Goſpel-Miniſters livelihood, to the fidelity and diſcretion of any modern Truſtees, ſpecially in the declining age of the world, which he foreſaw would be more unconſtant to all good, in the coldneſs of charity towards the end? The face of the Skie, and great deeps, is variable, bur mens minds are incomparably more fluctuant. Had the prodigious changes which we have ſeen in this giddy age, been foretold us; Who could have believed ſuch a report? The Changes, I ſay not in matters of ſmall moment, or examples of obſcure condition, or men of vulgar quality, but of the moſt eminent in their kinds. There were changes in the primitive Church, when the moſt evident gifts of the holy Ghoſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed among Chriſt's Diſciples: one while the <hi>Lyſtrians</hi> were hardly reſtrained from ſacrificing to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> as Gods;<note place="margin">Act. 14.28.</note> preſently they ſtone them, as the worſt of men. Now the Phariſees emiſſaries report—<hi>Never man ſpake as this man ſpeaks;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 7.</note> ere long the people would ſtone him as if he had been a blaſpheamer: now they make the ſtreets and Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ring of their Hoſanna's; preſently they roar out their <hi>Crucify,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Crucify.</hi> Truth begets enemies, where pride begets impatience of reproof. <hi>Ahab</hi> diſcovered the true cauſe, why he conceived that <hi>Michaiah</hi> propheſied no good to him,<note place="margin">1 King. 22.8.</note> in ſaying, <hi>I hate him.</hi> They that have ſome appearance of Religion in them, know not all, and therefore may have ſome erroneous Opinions; and though poſſibly they will hear, like, and love you, while you comply with their judgments; yet if you diſſent, they preſently bid defiance. So the <hi>Galatians</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:179525:45"/>
who received <hi>Paul as an Angel of God, even as Chriſt Jeſus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.14, 15.</note> preſently took him for an enemy, becauſe he told them the truth which croſſed their opinion. So the <hi>Jews</hi> hearing <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, that he muſt be ſent far off to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 22.21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>gave him au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto this word, and then lift up their voices, and ſaid, away with ſuch a fellow from the earth: for it is not fit that he ſhould live. Herod</hi> heard <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt gladly, and did many things, but when <hi>John</hi> reproved <hi>Herods</hi> inceſt, <hi>John</hi> muſt to Priſon and die. And are not men as wicked now, as in thoſe days? What hath been the cauſe of ſo much cruelty towards fruitfull Miniſters and Preachers of the truth of Chriſt, but Auditors impatience of reproof? And had you but the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious liberty, which you ſo much affect to have, all Miniſters your Almsmen, Who ſhould with ſafety to his life and liberty roprove you, who have been ſo impatient of hearing truth, though you have not yet ſuch a bond on Miniſters tongues, as you would have? What Prophets could you hope to have, but ſuch as would Act with you, and in your progreſs toward hell, have ready their—<hi>go up and proſper?</hi> But you ſay, we are Godly people; yea, and your Actions have prettily well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared you ſuch unto the World. 'Twas godlineſs with you to ſpoile our goods, to ſequeſter, and impriſon us: though we are ſilent, theſe injuries cry at the gates of Heaven, and poſterity willl freely ſpeak of this your pretended godlineſs. Oh Sir! but we ever held out the profeſſion of reformation: truly, as thoſe creſted pictures, which comming on ſhew Sainct, but going off, devil. And what competent maintenance faithfull Miniſters were like to have of ſuch Profeſſors, but that of <hi>Ahabs</hi> allowance? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.27. <hi>Put this fellow in Priſon and feed him with the bread of affliction, and with the water of affliction</hi>—here would be your competency for the Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Tythes and Offerings (as grounded on the Moral Law) are due to thoſe who ſerve about holy things of the Goſpel: for all, except <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Semiatheiſtical Antinomians,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that the moral Law doth now as ſtrictly bind <hi>(quoad vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum)</hi> as before Chriſt came into the World to take away the curſe of the Law; he took not away our duty therein
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:179525:46"/>
commanded; he did not in reſpect of our obedience, diſſolve one jot or tittle of the morality thereof. If therefore the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law ſtill binds men to pay Tythes, it binds to pay them to Miniſters, whom God hath called and aſſigned to receive that his part reſerved and appointed by him for their ſervice in his publick worſhip, and to none other. Chriſt repeating the firſt Commandment of the moral Law, enjoining our ſerving God, ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>him only ſhalt thou ſerve:</hi> which another Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth, <hi>honor the Lord with thy ſubſtance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 8 9.</note> 
                  <hi>and with the firſt fruits of all thy encreaſe:</hi> The <hi>quotam partem</hi> whereof he determineth by Tythes; which are therefore enjoined in the firſt precept in the moral Law.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe in the fourth precept for ſanctification of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath by Prayer, hearing the Word, &amp;c. And how ſhall they hear, without a Preacher? And how ſhall Miniſters Preach without neceſſary means to keep them alive, and to furniſh them with accomodations neceſſary to the performance of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial charge, which is to give attendance to reading, &amp;c. that they may both ſave themſelves and their hearers; when they have not ſo much as means to preſerve their lives, and to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them with food and raiment, much leſs to buy books?</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, Tythes are commanded in the fifth precept, for honouring of our Spiritual parents,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.15. 1 Tim. 5.17. Mal. 3.</note> who are to be counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of double honor; that is, relief and maintenance. This is the firſt Commandment with promiſe, which the Prophet toucheth when he ſpeaks of Tythes and Offerings duly paid; this cannot be in an imaginary competency, but in that which God hath appointed a definite ſetled maintenance, for thoſe that ſerve him in his publick Worſhip, which he never left in Law or Goſpel, to the will or courteſie of man. Now other definite or ſetled means for Miniſters maintenance, he never appointed any,<note place="margin">Decimà cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam partem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, nat. Alenſ. part. 4. q. 2. m 2.</note> but by Tythes, Offerings, and other like per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites appertinent to thoſe who ſerved in the <hi>Tabernacle, Temple,</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> conſtituted; therefore theſe muſt be their maintenance, if any.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, As Tythes are God's part, reſerved to himſelf and his aſſignes, ſo are they commanded in the eighth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which in the negative part ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal:</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:179525:46"/>
and God's Prophet ſheweth, that taking away or detention of Tythes, is ſtealing: and the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Mal. 3. Rom. 2.</note> that Sacriledg (the worſt thievery) is found under the Goſpel, as it was alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law: why ſaith he elſe, <hi>Thou that abhorreſt an Idol, committeſt thou Sacriledg?</hi> If there be nothing now ſacred in the time of the Goſpel, as ſome prophane men affirm; How unadviſedly did <hi>Paul</hi> ask that queſtion concerning a thing which is not in being, neither can be? And if there be any thing amongſt us ſacred, Are not thoſe things ſuch, as God hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated and hallowed? And did he not Conſecrate, and ſet apart from common uſe Tythes, for their maintenance, whom he appointed to ſerve in his publick Worſhip? Now the eighth precept in the negative part, forbiddeth all taking away and detention of others right; in the affirmative therefore it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to yield, give and preſerve what thou canſt, every ones right; ſo Tythes belong to the eighth precept: and indeed, the end of ordaining Tythes, is evidently moral, as in point of piety, equity and gratitude, as hath been noted; and that to which all men of all ages in the World, places and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are reſpectively bound; as well under the Ghoſpel, as the Law. And <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> paying Tythes, had the word of promiſe, <hi>To Abraham and his ſeed,</hi> in the faith whereof, he was juſtified,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.9, 10, 11.</note> before he had received <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of the faith which he had yet being uncircumciſed.</hi> So that the Goſpel was preached before (the giving of the Law by <hi>Moſes</hi>) to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gal. 3.8. Whence it appears that paying Tythes is a Goſpel duty, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, before their payment under the Law given on <hi>Sina;</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> payed them, before the Levitical Law deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined them. In which determination, God did not infer any new thing, or right of Tything into his Church, but according to the neceſſity of the preſent ſtate thereof, ſo regulated, and ordered Tythes for the Prieſts and Levites, to govern the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the Law, which was their Schoolmaſter to Chriſt; who being come, altered nothing of the morality of his Law, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the changeable rites, like outworn garments and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly rudiments,<note place="margin">Zeck. 3.4.</note> were then to be caſt off (as <hi>Joſhuas</hi> filthy garments) and other habits of ſanctity, and religious Goſpel-worſhip
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:179525:47"/>
to be put on with Chriſt the new Man, the ſame body his Church,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> en ire in every part, under the ſame ſacred head Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">John 1.</note> remaining the ſame: the Law then was given by <hi>Moſes</hi> Miniſtry, but grace and truth by Chriſt, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly fullfilled all that, which was prefigured in thoſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. And we read, that <hi>Abel</hi> offered firiſtlings of his flock,<note place="margin">Qui credidit, obtulit deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas. Alens. Part. 4. Ib. Alens. Heb. 1.6. A naturae ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionalis lege eſt, ut D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us colatur &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noretur. Alenſ. quo. ſ.</note> and the fat thereof; he of <hi>Adam's</hi> poſterity was <hi>primus verè fidelis,</hi> before the deluge; after which, and the growth of Idolatry, the firſt we read of paying Tythes, was <hi>Abraham, the father of the faithfull.</hi> Now God was to be Worſhiped, before, and after the giving of the Law, at all times, and by all perſons; which the very Law of Nature dictated to reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men; and God's Worſhip (ſuppoſing his Ordinance by the Miniſtry of man) could not be without Miniſters to officiate; neither could they ſubſiſt without maintenance, being fraile fleſh and blood, ſubject to all humane neceſſities; to which when Chriſt the Lord of all, in the form of a ſervant, vouchſafed to ſubject himſelf, he was once neceſſitated to ſend to Sea for <hi>Tribute-mony.</hi> Now the maintenance of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, is the maintenance of his worſhip; and therefore Tythes are now as due to <hi>Goſpel-Miniſters,</hi> as they were to <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> under the Law; for God is now to be Worſhipped, as he was in the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John. 4.</note> even: <hi>From the riſing of the Sun, unto the going down of the ſame;</hi> for he is not <hi>the God of the Jews only, but alſo of the Gentiles;</hi> even of all the Spiritual ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, Tythes are God's own part, reſerved to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters his Aſſignes: Therefore he complaineth, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. That the Jews robbed him, though they made ſuch a crime ſtrange to them. And wherein was his ſpoile? What Thief can obrepe, or come on him at unawares, who neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps? Beſides, <hi>Infinito nihil poteſt decedere;</hi> Wherein could the robbery be, but in the hinderance of his Worſhip, and that by taking from him the ſervice of his Miniſters, the Prieſts and Levites, who being deprived of Tythes and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, could neither perform their charge, nor give atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance therein, for want of maintenance thereto alotted them by God?</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:179525:47"/>16. <hi>Sacriledge</hi> is robbing of God by taking away,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note> or inverting to common uſes thoſe things, which are dedicated to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, holy uſes, or the neceſſary maintenance thereof; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were conſecrated by God himſelf,<note place="margin">Levit. 19.8. Numb. 5 9, 10, &amp; 16.37.</note> as tythes and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or by man, Gods Spirit conſenting and moving thereto. Of the firſt ſort, all thoſe things are, which are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to his worſhip, commanded in the <hi>Moral Law;</hi> of the ſecond ſort, are all thoſe <hi>votive</hi> things conſecrated by man, to the ſame end and purpoſe: As moneys, for the preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the poor <hi>Chriſtians (with ſuch Sacrifices God is pleaſed.)</hi> Alſo the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or ornaments, and neceſſary utenſiils of the publick <hi>worſhip of God</hi> in the Church, dedicated to the commodation thereof; alſo Lands, on which Churches now are,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.18, &amp;c. 2 Chron. 3.1</note> or the <hi>Temple</hi> or <hi>Synagogue</hi> were erected (as <hi>Auraunahs</hi> floor which <hi>David</hi> bought, on which he built an Altar, and on which afterwards, <hi>Solomon</hi> built the <hi>Temple of the Lord at Jeruſalem;</hi>) as alſo thoſe parcels of Land on which <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues</hi> were built, or <hi>Churches</hi> now are: Underſtand thoſe ſacred, <hi>durante uſu.</hi> Alſo <hi>Gleabland</hi> given by <hi>Act of Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> and conſecrated for additional ſupplies of <hi>Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> accommodations and maintenance; concerning which, that ancient Decree of <hi>Pius</hi> the Firſt, in the year of our Lord, One hundred forty and ſeven, is very conſiderable, which thus ſaith, <hi>Praedia divinis uſibus tradita, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Carranza.</note> Farms or Countrey Houſes and Lands <hi>given to holy uſes, ſome men apply to humane, that they may ſerve themſelves, taking them away from the Lord God, to whom they were dedicated. Quod ſiquis praeſumpſerit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">—Quaſi ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laedium, eo quod laedit ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um. Alenſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part. 2. 22ae. q. 99. &amp; 151. Zanch. Urſin. Danaeus. Eth. Chriſtian. l. 2. c. 15. Polan. Synt. Theol. l. 10. c. 63.</note> 
                  <hi>ſacrilegus habeatur, &amp; ſicut ſacrilegus judicetur: Let him be eſteemed ſacriledgious, and proceeded againſt, as ſuch.</hi> The Schools define Sacriledge thus, <hi>Eſt ſacrae rei violatio, vel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem uſurpatio;</hi> it is committed—<hi>Cum res conſecrata, vel ſacro uſui deputata uſurpatur.</hi> And they ſay, <hi>All that is Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which is done ad irreverentiam rei ſacrae. Suidas</hi> thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Qui ſacra diripit, ſacrilegus eſt.</hi> Ours thus, <hi>Sacriledge is taking away of things ſacred, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to holy uſes, or the maintenance or furtherance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> Whether thoſe things were conſecrated by God himſelf, by reſervation to his ſervice, and by expreſs <hi>mandate</hi> have been
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:179525:48"/>
hallowed to the ſame; or thoſe things which man (as above noted) hath conſecrated; whereof ſee <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that alienating or detaining things ſo hallowed, or returning them to <hi>common uſe,</hi> is the <hi>ſin of ſacriledge;</hi> ſuch therefore, is ſtealing, detention, or alienation of tythes appointed for the neceſſary ſupport of <hi>Gods ſervice</hi> and <hi>publick worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. The horridneſs of this ſin, further appears by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs curſe of God inevitably following it, as you may ſee it denounced by his Prophet,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note> even on a whole Nation, where ſuch a ſin is committed, and connived at by men; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly this curſe is <hi>a flying Book</hi> of the largeſt Folio ever men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. <hi>The length thereof is twenty cubites, and the breadth thereof, ten cubites. This is the curſe which entreth into the Houſe of the thief, and it ſhall conſume it, with the timber there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and the ſtones thereof.</hi> And ſhall this puniſhment, ſo ſwift, ſo great, like a <hi>Spiders Web</hi> catch onely little Flies, and let the great break thorow? Shall the little Theif come under the laſh, and ſhall the <hi>ſacrilegious</hi> eſcape the whip?</p>
               <p>Some have obſerved in particular examples cited, how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely it hath been revenged on ſome in all ages;<note place="margin">Joſephus de Bel. Jud. l. 1. 2 Maccab. c. 3.</note> as on <hi>Pompey, Craſſus, Heliodorus, &amp;c.</hi> read but our own <hi>Annals,</hi> and they may ſufficiently enform you herein; read what hath befaln <hi>Improrpiators;</hi> ſee what yet <hi>viſible Monuments</hi> of Gods juſtice in the conſumptions of goodly <hi>Monaſteries, Princes Palaces, Houſes of Biſhops, Nobles, Gentry,</hi> to this day appear. I ſay no more, though I could ſay much herein: Seldom doth the <hi>houſe of the ſacrilegious</hi> flouriſh to many generations; for as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">In Joh Tract. 50.</note> comparing private robbery and ſtealing of things publick. <hi>Quanto vehementius judicandus est fur ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legus, qui auſus fuerit, non undecunque tollere, ſed de eccleſia tollere? Qui aliquid de eccleſia furatur, Judae perdito compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now herein, three things commonly beguile men.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The multitude of offenders, who think, <hi>via trita, via tuta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe they vainly conceive, that if in their poſſeſſion there be a ſin, their <hi>Anceſtors</hi> from whom deſcended the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation, muſt bear it; not conſidering, that except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:179525:48"/>
all that which they wrongfully poſſeſs, they are guilty of the ſame ſin.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe they think that alienation of Tythes or Gleab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is at worſt, but a treſpaſs againſt a poor <hi>Miniſter</hi> of a deſpicable condition in reſpect of this world, and poſſibly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſome juſt exceptions in point of abilities, or manners. But we muſt know,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That multitude can give no patronage to ſin, it rather haſtneth Gods judgments on offenders.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It cannot excuſe thee, that a ſin lieth heavy on an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others ſoul, if thou becomeſt guilty of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, What ever the Miniſter be; firſt, he ſtands or falls to his own Maſter; ſecondly, in his Charge, he is the Steward of Gods Houſe: And in this matter of paying Tythes, the Pariſhioner is not to reſpect, of what quality and condition he is; for the debt is due to the <hi>Miniſters Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter;</hi> So that he receiveth it not in his own, but Gods right; ſo that whether he be faithful in his ſervice, or not, he is not reſponſible to his fellow ſervant, committed unto his charge, but unto his <hi>Maſter,</hi> with whom no doubt the accompt of an evil ſervant will be ſevere enough.</p>
               <p>To conclude, it were happy if theſe who have ſwallowed down ſacred morſels, would be perſwaded to diſgorge thoſe poyſoned bits, before it be too late; and that they would caſt out that, which they ſacriledgiouſly poſſeſs, whether by power, purchaſe, or preſcription,<note place="margin">Acts 27.6. &amp; 19.38.</note> as thoſe Marriners of <hi>Alexandria</hi> did their lading; wiſely reſolving, that it was better that thoſe things <hi>ſhould periſh for them, than with them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The concluſion of the laſt Propheſie of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 4.4, 6.</note> is, <hi>Remember ye the Law of</hi> Moſes; <hi>leſt I come and ſmite the Earth with a curſe:</hi> The ſame <hi>Moſes,</hi> in bleſſing the ſeveral Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaid of <hi>Levi: Let thy Thummim and thy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim, be upon thy holy One.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 33.8.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall teach</hi> Jacob <hi>thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wents, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>thy Law. Bleſs Lord his ſubſtance, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the work of his hands: Smite thorow the Loyns of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:179525:49"/>
again.</hi> Now it is to be noted, that <hi>Prophets Prayers</hi> are alſo <hi>Propheſies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now my dear Brethren, concerning whom my hearts deſire and prayer to God is, <hi>That ye may be ſaved:</hi> Conſider what theſe <hi>Pamphletiers</hi> intend you, when they would teach and perſwade you to commit <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge,</hi> laying a ſtumbling-block before the blinde, to make them fall upon Gods curſe, and to cauſe the ſame to come upon this whole <hi>Nation:</hi> Which I much fear, already groaneth, as under many other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities; ſo alſo under this ſin of <hi>Sacriledge.</hi> The holy <hi>Lord God</hi> open their eyes, whom it concerneth, that they may not ſleep in death. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179525:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
